LP 1 M1 - Introduction to Azure Cloud Shell

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-cloud-shell/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 1.1.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-cloud-shell/1-introduction

Introduction

Azure Cloud Shell is a browser-accessible command-line experience for managing Azure resources. It provides the flexibility of choosing the shell experience that best suits the way you work, either Bash or PowerShell. Traditionally, to interact with Azure resources via command-line, you need to install the necessary components into your local computer (PC, Mac, Linux). With Cloud Shell, you have an authenticated, interactive shell that isn't part of a local machine.

You're an IT admin for Contoso Corporation, responsible for the cloud infrastructure on which the company hosts its applications. These applications use different cloud resources, such as Azure VMs, Azure blob storage, Azure networking, and others. On many occasions, you're asked to perform operations on these cloud resources at moments when you’re not using your work laptop. In some cases, you have a friend’s laptop, a smartphone, or another personal PC.

This module explains what Azure Cloud Shell does, how it works, and when you should choose to use Cloud Shell as a solution to meet your organization's needs.

Learning objectives

In this module, you'll:

- Describe Azure Cloud Shell and the functionality it provides.

- Determine whether Cloud Shell meets the needs of your organization.

- Recognize how to use Cloud Shell and persist files for multiple sessions.

Unit 1.1.2 - What is Azure Cloud Shell?

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-cloud-shell/2-what-is-azure-cloud-shell

What is Azure Cloud Shell?

Azure Cloud Shell is a command-line environment you can access through your web browser. You can use this environment to manage Azure resources, including VMs, storage, and networking. Just like you do when using the Azure CLI or Azure PowerShell.

Because Microsoft manages Cloud Shell, you always have access to the most recent versions of the Azure CLI and PowerShell modules right from any browser. You don't have to worry about keeping modules up to date. With Cloud Shell, you just open your browser and sign in. Just like that, you have access to a command-line environment fully connected with your account's permissions and the resources to which you have access. All that works in an infrastructure that's compliant with double encryption at rest by default. You don't need to take any further action!

Azure Cloud Shell also provides cloud storage to persist files such as SSH keys, scripts, and more. This functionality lets you access important files in between sessions and with different machines. Finally, you can use the Cloud Shell editor to make changes to files, such as scripts, that are saved into this cloud storage directly from the Cloud Shell interface.

Unit 1.1.3 - How does Azure Cloud Shell work?

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-cloud-shell/3-how-azure-cloud-shell-works

How does Azure Cloud Shell work?

As an IT admin for Contoso Corporation, you're frequently on-call to perform administrative tasks and resolve workload disruptions to resources in your organization's Azure subscriptions. When visiting a family member during a weekend that you're on call, the development team notifies you of a problem with an Azure virtual machine (VM). The VM became nonresponsive during scheduled maintenance for the upgrade of an application that runs on it. Because the developers weren't granted access to the underlying Azure virtual machine hosting infrastructure, they're only able to remotely access the VM when it's operating normally. So, you're being called to diagnose and remediate the problem.

Since you're visiting family, you don’t have access to your administrative workstation and diagnostic scripts. You do have access to a laptop with an internet browser. Using the laptop, you browse to the Azure portal, authenticate against your organization’s Azure subscription, open Azure Cloud Shell, mount an Azure File Share, access your diagnostic scripts, and diagnose and remediate the problems with the VM, returning it to operation.

Access Cloud Shell

You have a few different options for accessing Azure Cloud Shell:

- From a direct link: https://shell.azure.com

From a direct link: https://shell.azure.com

- From the Azure portal

From the Azure portal

- From code snippets when accessing Microsoft Learn:

From code snippets when accessing Microsoft Learn:

When you open a Cloud Shell session, a temporary host is allocated to your session. This VM is preconfigured with the latest versions of PowerShell and Bash. You can then select the command-line experience you want to use:

After you select the shell experience you want to use, you can start managing your Azure resources:

Cloud Shell sessions terminate after 20 minutes of inactivity. When a session terminates, files on your CloudDrive are persisted, but you need to start a new session to access the Cloud Shell environment.

Access your own scripts and files

When using Cloud Shell, you might also need to run scripts or use files for different actions. You can persist files on Cloud Shell by using the Azure CloudDrive:

After uploading files, you can interact with them as you would in a regular PowerShell or Bash session:

Now that your file resides on CloudDrive, you can close the session and open another session on a different device and still access the same file. Cloud Shell also lets you map an Azure Storage File Share, which is tied to a specific region. Access to an Azure File Share lets you work with the contents of that share through Cloud Shell.

If you need to edit scripts hosted on the CloudDrive or File Share, you can use the Cloud Shell editor. Select the curly brackets {} icon on the browser and open the file you want to edit, or use the command code and specify the filename; for example:

code

code temp.txt

Note

The code command only works in the Classic mode in Cloud Shell. To enable Classic mode, select the More icon ( ... ), then select Settings > Go to Classic version .

code

Cloud Shell tools

If you need to manage resources (such as Docker containers or Kubernetes Clusters) or want to use non-Microsoft tools (such as Ansible and Terraform) in Cloud Shell, the Cloud Shell session comes with these add-ons already preconfigured.

Here’s a list of all add-ons available to you within a Cloud Shell session:

Category

Name

Linux tools

bash zsh sh tmux dig

Azure tools

Azure CLI AzCopy Azure Functions CLI Service Fabric CLI Batch Shipyard blobxfer

Text editors

code (Cloud Shell editor) vim nano emacs

Source control

git

Build tools

make maven npm pip

Containers

Docker Machine Kubectl Helm DC/OS CLI

Databases

MySQL client PostgreSql client sqlcmd Utility mssql-scripter

Other

iPython Client Cloud Foundry CLI Terraform Ansible Chef InSpec Puppet Bolt HashiCorp Packer Office 365 CLI

Unit 1.1.4 - When should you use Azure Cloud Shell?

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-cloud-shell/4-when-to-use-azure-cloud-shell

When should you use Azure Cloud Shell?

As an IT Admin for Contoso Corporation, you need alternatives to interact with Azure resources from the command line even when not using your default administrative device.

You can use Azure Cloud Shell to:

- Open a secure command-line session from any browser-based device.

- Interact with Azure resources without the need to install plug-ins or add-ons to your device.

- Persist files between sessions for later use.

- Use either Bash or PowerShell, whichever you prefer, to manage Azure resources.

- Edit files (such as scripts) via the Cloud Shell editor.

You shouldn't use Azure Cloud Shell if:

- You intend to leave a session open for more than 20 minutes for long running scripts or activities. In these cases, your session is disconnected without warning, and the current state is lost.

- You need admin permissions, such as sudo access, from within the Azure CLI or PowerShell environment.

- You need to install tools that aren't supported in the limited Cloud Shell environment, but instead require an environment such as a custom virtual machine or container.

- You need storage from different regions. You might need to back up and synchronize this content since only one region can have the storage allocated to Azure Cloud Shell.

- You need to open multiple sessions at the same time. Azure Cloud Shell allows only one instance at time and isn't suitable for concurrent work across multiple subscriptions or tenants.

Unit 1.1.5 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-cloud-shell/5-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Check your knowledge

Unit 1.1.6 - Summary

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-cloud-shell/6-summary

Summary

Azure Cloud Shell is a browser-accessible command-line experience for managing Azure resources. Rather than having to configure an Azure CLI or PowerShell session from your workstation, you can access Cloud Shell on any standard, compliant browser.

Cloud Shell provides the flexibility of choosing the shell experience that best suits the way you work, allowing you to work either in Bash or PowerShell, right from the browser. Cloud Shell also provides you with the mechanisms to persist files between sessions, and provides access to a minimalist version of the Visual Studio Code editor for more complex operations.

Learn more

Check out these articles to learn more about Azure Cloud Shell.

Azure Cloud Shell Overview

Azure Cloud Shell – Browser-Based Command Line

LP 2 M1 - Understand Microsoft Entra ID

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/understand-azure-active-directory/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 2.1.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/understand-azure-active-directory/1-introduction

Introduction

Welcome to the Microsoft Entra ID learning module! Microsoft Entra ID is a cloud-based identity and access management service provided by Microsoft. Microsoft Entra ID is a comprehensive solution for managing identities, enforcing access policies, and securing your applications and data in the cloud and on-premises.

This module aims to equip you with a comprehensive understanding of the following:

- Describe Microsoft Entra ID.

- Compare Microsoft Entra ID to Active Directory Domain Services (AD DS).

- Describe how Microsoft Entra ID is used as a directory for cloud apps.

- Describe Microsoft Entra ID P1 and P2.

- Describe Microsoft Entra Domain Services.

Whether you're a beginner or an experienced IT professional, this module provides you with the knowledge and skills necessary to understand Microsoft Entra ID effectively. So, let's explore the exciting world of Microsoft Entra ID!

Unit 2.1.2 - Examine Microsoft Entra ID

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/understand-azure-active-directory/2-examine-azure-active-directory

Examine Microsoft Entra ID

Students should be familiar with Active Directory Domain Services (AD DS or traditionally called just "Active Directory"). AD DS is a directory service that provides the methods for storing directory data, such as user accounts and passwords, and makes this data available to network users, administrators, and other devices and services. It runs as a service on Windows Server, referred to as a domain controller.

Microsoft Entra ID is part of the platform as a service (PaaS) offering and operates as a Microsoft-managed directory service in the cloud. It’s not a part of the core infrastructure that customers own and manage, nor is it an Infrastructure as a service offering. While this implies that you have less control over its implementation, it also means that you don’t have to dedicate resources to its deployment or maintenance.

With Microsoft Entra ID, you also have access to a set of features that aren’t natively available in AD DS, such as support for multi-factor authentication, identity protection, and self-service password reset.

You can use Microsoft Entra ID to provide more secure access to cloud-based resources for organizations and individuals by:

- Configuring access to applications

- Configuring single sign-on (SSO) to cloud-based SaaS applications

- Managing users and groups

- Provisioning users

- Enabling federation between organizations

- Providing an identity management solution

- Identifying irregular sign-in activity

- Configuring multi-factor authentication

- Extending existing on-premises Active Directory implementations to Microsoft Entra ID

- Configuring Application Proxy for cloud and local applications

- Configuring Conditional Access for users and devices

Microsoft Entra constitutes a separate Azure service. Its most elementary form, which any new Azure subscription includes automatically, doesn't incur any extra cost and is referred to as the Free tier. If you subscribe to any Microsoft Online business services (for example, Microsoft 365 or Microsoft Intune), you automatically get Microsoft Entra ID with access to all the Free features.

Note

By default, when you create a new Azure subscription by using a Microsoft account, the subscription automatically includes a new Microsoft Entra tenant named Default Directory.

Some of the more advanced identity management features require paid versions of Microsoft Entra ID, offered in the form of Basic and Premium tiers. Some of these features are also automatically included in Microsoft Entra instances generated as part of Microsoft 365 subscriptions. Differences between Microsoft Entra versions are discussed later in this module.

Implementing Microsoft Entra ID isn't the same as deploying virtual machines in Azure, adding AD DS, and then deploying some domain controllers for a new forest and domain. Microsoft Entra ID is a different service, much more focused on providing identity management services to web-based apps, unlike AD DS, which is more focused on on-premises apps.

Microsoft Entra tenants

Unlike AD DS, Microsoft Entra ID is multi-tenant by design and is implemented specifically to ensure isolation between its individual directory instances. It’s the world’s largest multi-tenant directory, hosting over a million directory services instances, with billions of authentication requests per week. The term tenant in this context typically represents a company or organization that signed up for a subscription to a Microsoft cloud-based service such as Microsoft 365, Intune, or Azure, each of which uses Microsoft Entra ID. However, from a technical standpoint, the term tenant represents an individual Microsoft Entra instance. Within an Azure subscription, you can create multiple Microsoft Entra tenants. Having multiple Microsoft Entra tenants might be convenient if you want to test Microsoft Entra functionality in one tenant without affecting the others.

At any given time, an Azure subscription must be associated with one, and only one, Microsoft Entra tenant. This association allows you to grant permissions to resources in the Azure subscription (via RBAC) to users, groups, and applications that exist in that particular Microsoft Entra tenant.

Note

You can associate the same Microsoft Entra tenant with multiple Azure subscriptions. This allows you to use the same users, groups, and applications to manage resources across multiple Azure subscriptions.

Each Microsoft Entra tenant is assigned the default Domain Name System (DNS) domain name, consisting of a unique prefix. The prefix, derived from the name of the Microsoft account you use to create an Azure subscription or provided explicitly when creating a Microsoft Entra tenant, is followed by the onmicrosoft.com suffix. Adding at least one custom domain name to the same Microsoft Entra tenant is possible and common. This name utilizes the DNS domain namespace that the corresponding company or organization owns. The Microsoft Entra tenant serves as the security boundary and a container for Microsoft Entra objects such as users, groups, and applications. A single Microsoft Entra tenant can support multiple Azure subscriptions.

Microsoft Entra schema

The Microsoft Entra schema contains fewer object types than that of AD DS. Most notably, it doesn't include a definition of the computer class, although it does include the device class. The process of joining devices to Microsoft Entra differs considerably from the process of joining computers to AD DS. The Microsoft Entra schema is also easily extensible, and its extensions are fully reversible.

The lack of support for the traditional computer domain membership means that you can't use Microsoft Entra ID to manage computers or user settings by using traditional management techniques, such as Group Policy Objects (GPOs). Instead, Microsoft Entra ID and its services define a concept of modern management. Microsoft Entra ID’s primary strength lies in providing directory services; storing and publishing user, device, and application data; and handling the authentication and authorization of the users, devices, and applications. The effectiveness and efficiency of these features are apparent based on existing deployments of cloud services such as Microsoft 365, which rely on Microsoft Entra ID as their identity provider and support millions of users.

Microsoft Entra ID doesn't include the organizational unit (OU) class, which means that you can't arrange its objects into a hierarchy of custom containers, which is frequently used in on-premises AD DS deployments. However, this isn't a significant shortcoming, because OUs in AD DS are used primarily for Group Policy scoping and delegation. You can accomplish equivalent arrangements by organizing objects based on their group membership.

Objects of the Application and servicePrincipal classes represent applications in Microsoft Entra ID. An object in the Application class contains an application definition and an object in the servicePrincipal class constitutes its instance in the current Microsoft Entra tenant. Separating these two sets of characteristics allows you to define an application in one tenant and use it across multiple tenants by creating a service principal object for this application in each tenant. Microsoft Entra ID creates the service principal object when you register the corresponding application in that Microsoft Entra tenant.

Unit 2.1.3 - Compare Microsoft Entra ID and Active Directory Domain Services

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/understand-azure-active-directory/3-compare-azure-active-directory-domain-services

Compare Microsoft Entra ID and Active Directory Domain Services

You could view Microsoft Entra ID simply as the cloud-based counterpart of AD DS; however, while Microsoft Entra ID and AD DS share some common characteristics, there are several significant differences between them.

Characteristics of AD DS

AD DS is the traditional deployment of Windows Server-based Active Directory on a physical or virtual server. Although AD DS is commonly considered being primarily a directory service, it’s only one component of the Windows Active Directory suite of technologies, which also includes Active Directory Certificate Services (AD CS), Active Directory Lightweight Directory Services (AD LDS), Active Directory Federation Services (AD FS), and Active Directory Rights Management Services (AD RMS).

When comparing AD DS with Microsoft Entra ID, it’s important to note the following characteristics of AD DS:

- AD DS is a true directory service, with a hierarchical X.500-based structure.

- AD DS uses Domain Name System (DNS) for locating resources such as domain controllers.

- You can query and manage AD DS by using Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) calls.

- AD DS primarily uses the Kerberos protocol for authentication.

- AD DS uses OUs and GPOs for management.

- AD DS includes computer objects, representing computers that join an Active Directory domain.

- AD DS uses trusts between domains for delegated management.

You can deploy AD DS on an Azure virtual machine to enable scalability and availability for an on-premises AD DS. However, deploying AD DS on an Azure virtual machine doesn't make any use of Microsoft Entra ID.

Note

Deploying AD DS on an Azure virtual machine requires one or more extra Azure data disks because you shouldn't use drive C for AD DS storage. These disks are needed to store the AD DS database, logs, and the sysvol folder. The Host Cache Preference setting for these disks must be set to None.

Characteristics of Microsoft Entra ID

Although Microsoft Entra ID has many similarities to AD DS, there are also many differences. It’s important to realize that using Microsoft Entra isn’t the same as deploying an Active Directory domain controller on an Azure virtual machine and adding it to your on-premises domain.

When comparing Microsoft Entra ID with AD DS, it’s important to note the following characteristics of Microsoft Entra ID:

- Microsoft Entra ID is primarily an identity solution, and it’s designed for internet-based applications by using HTTP (port 80) and HTTPS (port 443) communications.

- Microsoft Entra ID is a multi-tenant directory service.

- Microsoft Entra users and groups are created in a flat structure, and there are no OUs or GPOs.

- You can't query Microsoft Entra ID by using LDAP; instead, Microsoft Entra ID uses the REST API over HTTP and HTTPS.

- Microsoft Entra ID doesn't use Kerberos authentication; instead, it uses HTTP and HTTPS protocols such as SAML, WS-Federation, and OpenID Connect for authentication, and uses OAuth for authorization.

- Microsoft Entra ID includes federation services, and many third-party services such as Facebook are federated with and trust Microsoft Entra ID.

Unit 2.1.4 - Examine Microsoft Entra ID as a directory service for cloud apps

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/understand-azure-active-directory/4-examine-azure-directory-service-cloud-apps

Examine Microsoft Entra ID as a directory service for cloud apps

When you deploy cloud services such as Microsoft 365 or Intune, you also need to have directory services in the cloud to provide authentication and authorization for these services. Because of this, each cloud service that needs authentication will create its own Microsoft Entra tenant. When a single organization uses more than one cloud service, it’s much more convenient for these cloud services to use a single cloud directory instead of having separate directories for each service.

It’s now possible to have one identity service that covers all Microsoft cloud-based services, such as Microsoft 365, Azure, Microsoft Dynamics 365, and Intune. Microsoft Entra ID provides developers with centralized authentication and authorization for applications in Azure by using other identity providers or on-premises AD DS. Microsoft Entra ID can provide users with an SSO experience when using applications such as Facebook, Google services, Yahoo, or Microsoft cloud services.

The process of implementing Microsoft Entra ID support for custom applications is rather complex and beyond the scope of this course. However, the Azure portal and Microsoft Visual Studio 2013 and later make the process of configuring such support more straightforward.

In particular, you can enable Microsoft Entra authentication for the Web Apps feature of Azure App Service directly from the Authentication/Authorization blade in the Azure portal. By designating the Microsoft Entra tenant, you can ensure that only users with accounts in that directory can access the website. It’s possible to apply different authentication settings to individual deployment slots.

For more information, see Configure your App Service app to use Microsoft Entra login .

Unit 2.1.5 - Compare Microsoft Entra ID P1 and P2 plans

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/understand-azure-active-directory/5-compare-azure-premium-p1-p2-plans

Compare Microsoft Entra ID P1 and P2 plans

The Microsoft Entra ID P1 or P2 tier provides extra functionality as compared to the Free and Office 365 editions. However, premium versions require additional cost per user provisioning. Microsoft Entra ID P1 or P2 comes in two versions P1 and P2. You can procure it as an extra license or as a part of the Microsoft Enterprise Mobility + Security, which also includes the license for Azure Information Protection and Intune.

Microsoft provides a free trial period that can be used to experience the full functionality of the Microsoft Entra ID P2 edition. The following features are available with the Microsoft Entra ID P1 edition:

- Self-service group management . It simplifies the administration of groups where users are given the rights to create and manage the groups. End users can create requests to join other groups, and group owners can approve requests and maintain their groups’ memberships.

- Advanced security reports and alerts . You can monitor and protect access to your cloud applications by viewing detailed logs that show advanced anomalies and inconsistent access pattern reports. Advanced reports are machine learning based and can help you gain new insights to improve access security and respond to potential threats.

- Multi-factor authentication . Full multi-factor authentication (MFA) works with on-premises applications (using virtual private network [VPN], RADIUS, and others), Azure, Microsoft 365, Dynamics 365, and third-party Microsoft Entra gallery applications. It doesn't work with non-browser off-the-shelf apps, such as Microsoft Outlook. Full multi-factor authentication is covered in more detail in the following units in this lesson.

- Microsoft Identity Manager (MIM) licensing . MIM integrates with Microsoft Entra ID P1 or P2 to provide hybrid identity solutions. MIM can bridge multiple on-premises authentication stores such as AD DS, LDAP, Oracle, and other applications with Microsoft Entra ID. This provides consistent experiences to on-premises line-of-business (LOB) applications and SaaS solutions.

- Enterprise SLA of 99.9% . You're guaranteed at least 99.9% availability of the Microsoft Entra ID P1 or P2 service. The same SLA applies to Microsoft Entra Basic.

- Password reset with writeback . Self-service password reset follows the Active Directory on-premises password policy.

- Cloud App Discovery feature of Microsoft Entra ID . This feature discovers the most frequently used cloud-based applications.

- Conditional Access based on device, group, or location . This lets you configure conditional access for critical resources, based on several criteria.

- Microsoft Entra Connect Health . You can use this tool to gain operational insight into Microsoft Entra ID. It works with alerts, performance counters, usage patterns, and configuration settings, and presents the collected information in the Microsoft Entra Connect Health portal.

In addition to these features, the Microsoft Entra ID P2 license provides extra functionalities:

- Microsoft Entra ID Protection . This feature provides enhanced functionalities for monitoring and protecting user accounts. You can define user risk policies and sign-in policies. In addition, you can review users’ behavior and flag users for risk.

- Microsoft Entra Privileged Identity Management . This functionality lets you configure additional security levels for privileged users such as administrators. With Privileged Identity Management, you define permanent and temporary administrators. You also define a policy workflow that activates whenever someone wants to use administrative privileges to perform some task.

Note

Plans change frequently. Check Microsoft's website for the current plans and capabilities.

Unit 2.1.6 - Examine Microsoft Entra Domain Services

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/understand-azure-active-directory/6-examine-azure-domain-services

Examine Microsoft Entra Domain Services

In most organizations today, line-of-business (LOB) applications are deployed on computers and devices that are domain members. These organizations use AD DS–based credentials for authentication, and Group Policy manages them. When you consider moving these apps to run in Azure, one key issue is how to provide authentication services to these apps. To satisfy this need, you can choose to implement a site-to-site virtual private network (VPN) between your local infrastructure and the Azure IaaS, or you can deploy replica domain controllers from your local AD DS as virtual machines (VMs) in Azure. These approaches can entail additional costs and administrative effort. Additionally, the difference between these two approaches is that with the first option, authentication traffic will cross the VPN, while in the second option, replication traffic will cross the VPN and authentication traffic stays in the cloud.

Microsoft provides Microsoft Entra Domain Services as an alternative to these approaches. This service, which runs as part of the Microsoft Entra ID P1 or P2 tier, provides domain services such as Group Policy management, domain joining, and Kerberos authentication to your Microsoft Entra tenant. These services are fully compatible with locally deployed AD DS, so you can use them without deploying and managing additional domain controllers in the cloud.

Because Microsoft Entra ID can integrate with your local AD DS, when you implement Microsoft Entra Connect, users can utilize organizational credentials in both on-premises AD DS and in Microsoft Entra Domain Services. Even if you don’t have AD DS deployed locally, you can choose to use Microsoft Entra Domain Services as a cloud-only service. This enables you to have similar functionality of locally deployed AD DS without having to deploy a single domain controller on-premises or in the cloud. For example, an organization can choose to create a Microsoft Entra tenant and enable Microsoft Entra Domain Services, and then deploy a virtual network between its on-premises resources and the Microsoft Entra tenant. You can enable Microsoft Entra Domain Services for this virtual network so that all on-premises users and services can use domain services from Microsoft Entra ID.

Microsoft Entra Domain Services provides several benefits for organizations, such as:

- Administrators don't need to manage, update, and monitor domain controllers.

- Administrators don't need to deploy and manage Active Directory replication.

- There’s no need to have Domain Admins or Enterprise Admins groups for domains that Microsoft Entra ID manages.

If you choose to implement Microsoft Entra Domain Services, you need to be aware of the service's current limitations. These include:

- Only the base computer Active Directory object is supported.

- It’s not possible to extend the schema for the Microsoft Entra Domain Services domain.

- The organizational unit (OU) structure is flat and nested OUs aren't currently supported.

- There’s a built-in Group Policy Object (GPO), and it exists for computer and user accounts.

- It’s not possible to target OUs with built-in GPOs. Additionally, you can't use Windows Management Instrumentation filters or security-group filtering.

By using Microsoft Entra Domain Services, you can freely migrate applications that use LDAP, NTLM, or the Kerberos protocols from your on-premises infrastructure to the cloud. You can also use applications such as Microsoft SQL Server or Microsoft SharePoint Server on VMs or deploy them in the Azure IaaS, without needing domain controllers in the cloud or a VPN to local infrastructure.

You can enable Microsoft Entra Domain Services by using the Azure portal. This service charges per hour based on the size of your directory.

Unit 2.1.7 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/understand-azure-active-directory/7-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Choose the best response for each of the questions below.

Check your knowledge

Unit 2.1.8 - Summary

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/understand-azure-active-directory/8-summary

Summary

Active Directory provides the core service of identity management. AD DS is the traditional on-premises solution, whereas Microsoft Entra ID is the cloud-based solution. Microsoft Entra ID is frequently adopted at first to facilitate authentication for cloud-based apps, but is capable of providing authentication services for the entire infrastructure. While they provide similar solutions, each offer different capability and are often used together to provide a best-of-breed solution. Microsoft Entra ID is offered as a free service, with paid tiers for additional capabilities, depending on an organization's needs.

Learn more

- What is Microsoft Entra ID?

- Compare Active Directory to Microsoft Entra ID

LP 2 M2 - Create, configure, and manage identities

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 2.2.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/1-introduction

Introduction

Transitioning workloads to the cloud involves more than just moving servers, websites, and data. Companies need to think about how to secure those resources, by defining authorized users. Next, companies need to ensure that users only have access to data that they need, that user authorization is limited only create services available to them, and that users only perform operations authorized for them to perform. Access to cloud-based workloads is controlled centrally in two ways. First by providing a definitive identity for each user that they use for every service. Then second by ensuring employees and vendors have enough access to do their jobs.

Microsoft Entra ID, the Microsoft cloud-based identity, and access management service, helps make these challenges easier to solve. Microsoft Entra ID provides end-to-end identity management; including single sign-on and multifactor authentication to help protect your users and your data. In this module, you learn the basics of creating, configuring, and managing users and groups of users. You also learn to manage licenses and device registration.

Learning objectives

In this module, you'll:

- Create, configure, and manage users

- Create, configure, and manage groups

- Manage licenses

- Configure and manage device registration

- Explore custom security attributes and automatic provisioning

Prerequisites

- Basic understanding of identity management

- Some experience with Active Directory a plus

- Experience with Zero Trust helpful

Unit 2.2.2 - Create, configure, and manage users

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/2-users

Create, configure, and manage users

Every user who needs access to resources needs a user account in Microsoft Entra ID. A user account contains all the information needed to authenticate the user during the sign-on process. Once authenticated, Microsoft Entra ID builds an access token to authorize the user and determine what resources they can access and what they can do with those resources.

You use the Microsoft Entra admin center to work with user objects. Keep in mind that you can only work with a single directory at a time. You can use the Directory + Subscription panel to switch directories. The admin center also has a Switch directory button in the toolbar, which makes it easy to switch to another available directory.

View users

To view the Microsoft Entra users, select the Users entry under Identity , then open the All Users view. Take a minute to access the admin center and view your users. Notice the User Type column to see members and guests, as the following figure depicts.

Typically, Microsoft Entra ID defines users in three ways:

- Cloud identities - These users exist only in Microsoft Entra ID. Examples are administrator accounts and users that you manage yourself. Their source is Microsoft Entra ID or External Microsoft Entra directory if the user is defined in another Microsoft Entra instance but needs access to subscription resources controlled by this directory. When these accounts are removed from the primary directory, they're deleted.

- Directory-synchronized identities - These users exist in an on-premises Active Directory. A synchronization activity brings these users into Microsoft Entra ID. Microsoft Entra Cloud Sync is the recommended synchronization tool for most organizations—it uses a lightweight cloud-managed agent and supports multiple disconnected forests. Microsoft Entra Connect Sync remains available for complex scenarios such as device synchronization or groups with more than 50,000 members. Their source is Windows Server AD .

- Guest users - These users exist outside your organization. Examples are accounts from other cloud providers and Microsoft accounts. Their source is Invited user . This type of account is useful when external vendors or contractors need access to your organization's resources. Once their help is no longer necessary, you can remove the account and all of their access.

Unit 2.2.3 - Exercise - assign licenses to users

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/3-exercise-assign-licenses-users

Exercise - assign licenses to users

Exercise environment needs - this lab assumes you have a basic Microsoft Entra tenant with at least User Administrator rights to complete it. You can get a free trial subscription for at Try Azure for Free .

Create a new user in Microsoft Entra ID

You can skip creating this user if you created the same user in the earlier module.

- Browse to the Identity menu in the Microsoft Entra admin center .

Browse to the Identity menu in the Microsoft Entra admin center .

- In the left navigation, under select Users , then All Users.

In the left navigation, under select Users , then All Users.

- Within the Users page, on the menu, select + New user and Create new user .

Within the Users page, on the menu, select + New user and Create new user .

- Create a user using the following information: Setting Value User principal name ChrisG Name Chris Green First name Chris Last name Green Password make up a unique password

Create a user using the following information:

Setting

Value

User principal name

ChrisG

Name

Chris Green

First name

Chris

Last name

Green

Password

make up a unique password

- When complete, verify the account for Chris Green is shown in the All users list.

When complete, verify the account for Chris Green is shown in the All users list.

Create a security group in Microsoft Entra ID

- Browse to the Microsoft Entra admin center screen.

Browse to the Microsoft Entra admin center screen.

- In the left navigation, under Identity , select Groups and then All groups .

In the left navigation, under Identity , select Groups and then All groups .

- In the Groups screen, on the menu, select New group .

In the Groups screen, on the menu, select New group .

- Create a group using the following information: Setting Value Group type Security Group name Marketing Membership type Assigned Owners Assign your own administrator account as the group owner Members Chris Green

Create a group using the following information:

Setting

Value

Group type

Security

Group name

Marketing

Membership type

Assigned

Owners

Assign your own administrator account as the group owner

Members

Chris Green

- When complete, verify the group named Marketing is shown in the All groups list.

When complete, verify the group named Marketing is shown in the All groups list.

Assign a license to a group

License assignment to groups is managed through the Microsoft 365 admin center.

- Go to the Microsoft 365 admin center at https://admin.microsoft.com .

- Select Billing from the menu on the left.

- Select Licenses .

- From the list of licenses you have available, select one.

- Select Groups from the list near the top of the screen.

- On the Groups page, select + Assign license .

- Search for and select the Marketing group you created earlier.

- Select the Assign button at the bottom of the dialog.

- You should get a message that licenses were successfully assigned.

Restore or remove a recently deleted user with Microsoft Entra ID

After you delete a user, the account remains in a suspended state for 30 days. During that 30-day window, the user account can be restored, along with all its properties. After that 30-day window passes, the permanent deletion process is automatically started.

You can view your restorable users, restore a deleted user, or permanently delete a user using Microsoft Entra ID user interface.

Important

You can't restore a permanently deleted user.

Required permissions

You must have one of the following roles to restore or permanently delete users.

- Global administrator

- Partner Tier-1 Support

- Partner Tier-2 Support

- User administrator

Unit 2.2.4 - Exercise - restore or remove deleted users

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/4-exercise-restore-remove-deleted-users

Exercise - restore or remove deleted users

Exercise environment needs - this lab assumes you have a basic Microsoft Entra tenant with at least User Administrator rights to complete it. You can get a free trial subscription at Try Microsoft Azure for free .

Remove a user from Microsoft Entra ID

- Browse to the Microsoft Entra admin center .

Browse to the Microsoft Entra admin center .

- In the left navigation, under Identity , select Users .

In the left navigation, under Identity , select Users .

- In the Users list, select the check box for a user to delete. For example, select Chris Green . Tip Selecting users from the list allows you to manage multiple users at the same time. If you select the user, to open that user’s page, you'll only be managing that individual user.

In the Users list, select the check box for a user to delete. For example, select Chris Green .

Tip

Selecting users from the list allows you to manage multiple users at the same time. If you select the user, to open that user’s page, you'll only be managing that individual user.

- With the user account selected, on the menu, select Delete user .

With the user account selected, on the menu, select Delete user .

- Review the dialog box and then select OK .

Review the dialog box and then select OK .

Restore a deleted user

You can see all the users that were deleted less than 30 days ago. These users can be restored.

- In the Users page, in the left navigation, select Deleted users .

In the Users page, in the left navigation, select Deleted users .

- Review the list of deleted users and select the user you deleted. Important By default, deleted user accounts are permanently removed from Microsoft Entra ID automatically after 30 days.

Review the list of deleted users and select the user you deleted.

Important

By default, deleted user accounts are permanently removed from Microsoft Entra ID automatically after 30 days.

- On the menu, select Restore user .

On the menu, select Restore user .

- Review the dialog box and then select OK .

Review the dialog box and then select OK .

- In the left navigation, select All users .

In the left navigation, select All users .

- Verify the user was restored.

Verify the user was restored.

Unit 2.2.5 - Create, configure, and manage groups

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/5-groups

Create, configure, and manage groups

A Microsoft Entra group helps organize users, which makes it easier to manage permissions. Using groups lets the resource owner (or Microsoft Entra directory owner), assign a set of access permissions to all the members of the group, instead of having to provide the rights one-by-one. Groups let you define a security boundary and then add and remove specific users to grant or deny access with a minimum amount of effort. Even better, Microsoft Entra ID supports the ability to define membership based on rules - such as what department a user works in, or the job title they have.

Microsoft Entra ID allows you to define two different types of groups.

- Security groups - the most common type of groups and are used to manage access to shared resources. Members of a security group can include users, devices, and service principals. For example, you can create a security group for a specific security policy. By doing it this way, you can give a set of permissions to all the members at once, instead of having to add permissions to each member individually. This option requires a Microsoft Entra administrator.

- Microsoft 365 groups - provide collaboration opportunities by giving members access to a shared mailbox, calendar, files, SharePoint site, and more. This option also lets you give people outside of your organization access to the group. This option is available to users and admins.

View available groups

You can view all groups through the Groups item under Identity in the Microsoft Entra admin center. A new Microsoft Entra ID deployment has no groups defined.

The second characteristic of a group that you need to be aware of is the Membership Type . This specifies how individual members are added to the group. The three types are:

- Assigned - members are added and maintained manually.

- Dynamic User - users are added and removed automatically based on rules that evaluate user attributes such as department, job title, or location.

- Dynamic Device - devices are added and removed automatically based on rules that evaluate device attributes. Applies to security groups only; Microsoft 365 groups support dynamic users but not dynamic devices.

Dynamic groups

With dynamic membership, Microsoft Entra ID automatically adds or removes users or devices from a group based on rules you define. When a member's attributes change—for example, a user moves to a different department—all dynamic membership rules in the tenant are reevaluated, and the user is added to or removed from groups accordingly.

Dynamic membership requires a Microsoft Entra ID P1 license (or Intune for Education for device-based rules).

For example, you can create a rule that automatically adds all users whose Department attribute equals "Marketing" to a Marketing security group, keeping membership current without manual updates.

Unit 2.2.6 - Exercise - add groups in Microsoft Entra ID

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/6-exercise-add-groups-azure-active-directory

Exercise - add groups in Microsoft Entra ID

Exercise environment needs - this lab assumes you have a basic Microsoft Entra tenant with at least User Administrator rights to complete it. You can get a free trial subscription at Try Microsoft Azure for free .

Create a Microsoft 365 group in Microsoft Entra ID

- Browse to the Microsoft Entra admin center .

Browse to the Microsoft Entra admin center .

- In the left navigation, under Identity , select Groups .

In the left navigation, under Identity , select Groups .

- In the Groups page, on the menu, select New group .

In the Groups page, on the menu, select New group .

- Create a group using the following information: Setting Value Group type Microsoft 365 Group name Northwest Sales Membership type Assigned Owners Assign your own administrator account as the group owner Members Assign a member of this group

Create a group using the following information:

Setting

Value

Group type

Microsoft 365

Group name

Northwest Sales

Membership type

Assigned

Owners

Assign your own administrator account as the group owner

Members

Assign a member of this group

- When complete, verify the group named Northwest sales is shown in the All groups list.

When complete, verify the group named Northwest sales is shown in the All groups list.

- You have to refresh the All groups a couple of times for the new group to show up.

You have to refresh the All groups a couple of times for the new group to show up.

Unit 2.2.7 - Configure and manage device registration

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/7-configure-manage-device-registration

Configure and manage device registration

With the proliferation of devices of all shapes and sizes and the proliferation of bring-your-own-device (BYOD), IT professionals are faced with two somewhat opposing goals:

- Allow end users to be productive wherever and whenever and on any device

- Protect the organization's assets

To protect these assets, IT-staff needs to first manage the device identities. IT-staff can build on the device identity with tools like Microsoft Intune to ensure standards for security and compliance are met. Microsoft Entra ID enables single sign-on to devices, apps, and services from anywhere through these devices.

- Your users get access to your organization's assets they need.

- Your IT-staff gets the controls they need to secure your organization.

Microsoft Entra registered devices

The goal of Microsoft Entra registered devices is to provide your users with support for the BYOD or mobile device scenarios. In these scenarios, a user can access your organization’s Microsoft Entra ID controlled resources using a personal device.

Microsoft Entra registered

Description

Definition

Registered to Microsoft Entra ID without requiring organizational account to sign in to the device

Primary audience

Applicable to Bring your own device (BYOD), and Mobile devices

Device ownership

User or Organization

Operating systems

Windows 10 or newer, macOS 10.15 or newer, iOS 15 or newer, Android, Linux (Ubuntu 20.04/22.04/24.04 LTS, Red Hat Enterprise Linux 8/9 LTS)

Device sign in options

End-user local credentials, Password, Windows Hello, PIN, Biometrics

Device management

Mobile Device Management (example: Microsoft Intune), Mobile Application Management

Key capabilities

SSO to cloud resources, Conditional Access when enrolled in Intune, Conditional Access via App protection policy

Microsoft Entra registered devices are signed in to using a local account like a Microsoft account on a Windows 10 or newer device, but additionally have a Microsoft Entra account attached for access to organizational resources. Access to resources in the organization can be further limited based on that Microsoft Entra account and Conditional Access policies applied to the device identity.

Administrators can secure and further control these Microsoft Entra registered devices using Mobile Device Management (MDM) tools like Microsoft Intune. MDM provides a means to enforce organization-required configurations like requiring storage to be encrypted, password complexity, and security software kept updated.

Microsoft Entra ID registration can be accomplished when accessing a work application for the first time or manually using the Windows 10 or Windows 11 Settings menu.

Scenarios for registered devices

A user in your organization wants to access tools for email, reporting time-off, and benefits enrollment from their home PC. Your organization has these tools behind a Conditional Access policy that requires access from an Intune compliant device. The user adds their organization account and registers their home PC with Microsoft Entra ID and the required Intune policies are enforced giving the user access to their resources.

Another user wants to access their organizational email on their personal Android phone infected by a root-kit. Your company requires a compliant device and created an Intune compliance policy to block any rooted devices. The employee is stopped from accessing organizational resources on this device.

Microsoft Entra joined devices

Microsoft Entra joined is intended for organizations that want to be cloud-first or cloud-only. Any organization can deploy Microsoft Entra joined devices no matter the size or industry. Microsoft Entra joined enables access to both cloud and on-premises apps and resources.

Microsoft Entra joined

Description

Definition

Joined only to Microsoft Entra ID requiring organizational account to sign in to the device

Primary audience

Suitable for both cloud-only and hybrid organizations

Device ownership

Organization

Operating systems

All Windows 10 and Windows 11 devices (except Home editions); Windows Server 2019 and newer VMs in Azure (Server Core not supported); macOS 13 or newer (preview)

Device management

Mobile Device Management (example: Microsoft Intune)

Key capabilities

SSO to both cloud and on-premises resources, Conditional Access, Self-service Password Reset and Windows Hello PIN reset

Microsoft Entra joined devices are signed in to using an organizational Microsoft Entra account. Access to resources in the organization can be further limited based on that Microsoft Entra account and Conditional Access policies applied to the device identity.

Administrators can secure and further control Microsoft Entra joined devices using Mobile Device Management (MDM) tools like Microsoft Intune or in co-management scenarios using Microsoft Endpoint Configuration Manager. These tools provide a means to enforce organization-required configurations like requiring storage to be encrypted, password complexity, software installations, and software updates. Administrators can make organization applications available to Microsoft Entra joined devices using Configuration Manager.

Microsoft Entra joined can be accomplished using self-service options like the Out of Box Experience (OOBE), bulk enrollment, or Windows Autopilot.

Microsoft Entra joined devices can still maintain single sign-on access to on-premises resources when they are on the organization's network. Microsoft Entra joined devices authenticate to on-premises servers like for file, print, and other applications.

Scenarios for joined devices

Although Microsoft Entra joined is primarily intended for organizations that don't have an on-premises Windows Server Active Directory infrastructure, you can certainly use it in scenarios where:

- You want to transition to cloud-based infrastructure using Microsoft Entra ID and MDM like Intune.

- You can’t use an on-premises domain join, for example, if you need to get mobile devices such as tablets and phones under control.

- Your users primarily need to access Microsoft 365 or other SaaS apps integrated with Microsoft Entra ID.

- You want to manage a group of users in Microsoft Entra ID instead of in Active Directory. This scenario can apply, for example, to seasonal workers, contractors, or students.

- You want to provide joining capabilities to workers in remote branch offices with limited on-premises infrastructure.

You can configure Microsoft Entra joined devices for all Windows 10 and Windows 11 devices except for the Home editions.

The goal of Microsoft Entra joined devices is to simplify:

- Windows deployments of work-owned devices

- Access to organizational apps and resources from any Windows device

- Cloud-based management of work-owned devices

- Users to sign in to their devices with their Microsoft Entra ID or synced Active Directory work or school accounts.

Microsoft Entra Joined can be deployed by using many different methods.

Hybrid Microsoft Entra joined devices

For more than a decade, many organizations have used the domain join to their on-premises Active Directory to enable:

- IT departments to manage work-owned devices from a central location.

- Users to sign in to their devices with their Active Directory work or school accounts.

Typically, organizations with an on-premises footprint rely on imaging methods to configure devices, and they often use Configuration Manager or group policy (GP) to manage them.

If your environment has an on-premises AD footprint and you also want benefit from the capabilities provided by Microsoft Entra ID, you can implement hybrid Microsoft Entra joined devices. These devices are devices that are joined to your on-premises Active Directory and registered with your Microsoft Entra directory.

Hybrid Microsoft Entra joined

Description

Definition

Joined to on-premises AD and Microsoft Entra ID requiring organizational account to sign in to the device

Primary audience

Suitable for hybrid organizations with existing on-premises AD infrastructure

Device ownership

Organization

Operating systems

Windows 10, Windows 11 (except Home editions), Windows Server 2016, 2019, and 2022

Device sign in options

Password or Windows Hello for Business

Device management

Group Policy, Configuration Manager standalone, or co-management with Microsoft Intune

Key capabilities

SSO to both cloud and on-premises resources, Conditional Access, Self-service Password Reset and Windows Hello PIN reset

Scenarios for hybrid joined

Use Microsoft Entra hybrid joined devices if:

- You have Win32 apps deployed to these devices that rely on Active Directory machine authentication.

- You want to continue to use Group Policy to manage device configuration.

- You want to continue to use existing imaging solutions to deploy and configure devices.

Device writeback (no longer supported)

Device writeback is no longer supported and is no longer a recommended approach for hybrid identity scenarios. It is replaced by Cloud Kerberos Trust , which allows Microsoft Entra joined and hybrid joined devices to authenticate to on-premises resources without requiring device objects to be written back to on-premises Active Directory.

For organizations planning new hybrid deployments, use Cloud Kerberos Trust to enable on-premises SSO and Windows Hello for Business in hybrid environments. See Configure Microsoft Entra Kerberos for on-premises single sign-on for guidance.

Unit 2.2.8 - Manage licenses

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/8-manage-licenses

Manage licenses

Microsoft paid cloud services, such as Microsoft 365, Enterprise Mobility + Security, Dynamics 365, and other similar products, require licenses. These licenses are assigned to each user who needs access to these services. To manage licenses, administrators use the Microsoft 365 admin center or PowerShell and Microsoft Graph API. Microsoft Entra ID is the underlying infrastructure that supports identity management for all Microsoft cloud services. Microsoft Entra ID stores information about license assignment states for users.

Without group-based licensing, assigning licenses at the individual user level makes large-scale management difficult. For example, to add or remove user licenses based on organizational changes, such as users joining or leaving the organization or a department, an administrator often must write a complex PowerShell script. This script makes individual calls to the cloud service.

To address those challenges, Microsoft Entra ID now includes group-based licensing. You can assign one or more product licenses to a group. Microsoft Entra ID ensures that the licenses are assigned to all members of the group. Any new members who join the group are assigned the appropriate licenses. When they leave the group, those licenses are removed. This licensing management eliminates the need for automating license management via PowerShell to reflect changes in the organization and departmental structure on a per-user basis.

License requirements

You must have one of the following licenses to use group-based licensing:

- Paid or trial subscription for Microsoft Entra ID Premium P1 and greater

- Paid or trial edition Office 365 Enterprise E3 or greater

Required number of licenses

For any groups assigned a license, you must also have a license for each unique member. While you don't have to assign each member of the group a license, you must have at least enough licenses to include all of the members. For example, if you have 1,000 unique members who are part of licensed groups in your tenant, you must have at least 1,000 licenses to meet the licensing agreement.

Features

Here are the main features of group-based licensing:

- Licenses can be assigned to any security group in Microsoft Entra ID. Security groups can be synced from on-premises by using Microsoft Entra Cloud Sync (recommended) or Microsoft Entra Connect Sync. You can also create security groups directly in Microsoft Entra ID (also called cloud-only groups), or automatically via the Microsoft Entra dynamic group feature.

- When a product license is assigned to a group, the administrator can disable one or more service plans in the product. Typically, this assignment is done when the organization isn't yet ready to start using a service included in a product. For example, the administrator might assign Microsoft 365 to a department, but temporarily disable the Viva Engage service.

- All Microsoft cloud services that require user-level licensing are supported. This support includes all Microsoft 365 products, Enterprise Mobility + Security, and Dynamics 365.

- Group-based licensing is currently available only through the Microsoft 365 admin center .

- Microsoft Entra ID automatically manages license modifications that result from group membership changes. Typically, license modifications are effective within minutes of a membership change.

- A user can be a member of multiple groups with license policies specified. A user can also have some licenses that were directly assigned, outside of any groups. The resulting user state is a combination of all assigned product and service licenses. If a user is assigned same license from multiple sources, the license is consumed only once.

- In some cases, licenses can't be assigned to a user. For example, there might not be enough available licenses in the tenant, or conflicting services are assigned at the same time. Administrators have access to information about users for whom Microsoft Entra ID couldn't fully process group licenses. They can then take corrective action based on that information.

Some Microsoft services aren't available in all locations. The administrator, before assigning a license to a user, should specify usage location in the User Profile.

For group license assignment, any users without a usage location specified inherit the location of the directory. If you have users in multiple locations, we recommend that you always set usage location as part of your user creation. Usage location helps ensure the result of license assignment is always correct and users don't receive services in locations that aren't allowed.

Unit 2.2.9 - Exercise - change group license assignments

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/9-exercise-change-group-license-assignments

Exercise - change group license assignments

Exercise environment needs - this lab assumes you have a basic Microsoft Entra tenant with at least User Administrator rights to complete it. You can get a free trial subscription at Try Microsoft Azure for free .

Change group license assignment

- Open https://entra.microsoft.com to get to the Microsoft Entra admin center.

- In the left navigation, open Groups .

- Select All groups , then select one of the available groups.

- In the left navigation, under Manage , select Licenses .

You see a list of any license assignments that are currently made. And you find that you have to use the Microsoft 365 Admin Center to make any updates.

- Review the current assignments and then, on the menu, select + Assignments .

- Open https://admin.microsoft.com to open the Microsoft 365 admin center.

- Select Billing . Then select Licenses .

- Select an available license from the list.

- Select Groups from the menu near the top of the page.

- Select the + Assign licenses option.

- Pick the group you were looking at earlier in Microsoft Entra. Then select the Assign button at the bottom of the page.

- On the group’s Licenses page, review the change. You should be able to see the change in both the Microsoft Entra admin center and the Microsoft 365 admin center.

Identify and resolve license assignment problems for a group in Microsoft Entra ID

Group-based licensing in Microsoft Entra ID introduces the concept of users in a licensing error state. In this section, we explain the reasons why users might end up in this state.

When you assign licenses directly to individual users, without using group-based licensing, the assignment operation might fail. For example, when you execute the PowerShell cmdlet Set-MgUserLicense on a user object, the cmdlet can fail for many reasons that are related to business logic. For example, there might be an insufficient number of licenses or a conflict between two service plans that can't be assigned at the same time. The problem is immediately reported back to you.

Set-MgUserLicense

When you're using group-based licensing the same errors can occur, but they happen in the background while the Microsoft Entra service is assigning licenses. For this reason, the errors can't be communicated to you immediately. Instead, they're recorded on the user object and then reported via the administrative portal. The original intent to license the user is never lost, but it's recorded in an error state for future investigation and resolution.

Not enough licenses

Problem : There aren't enough available licenses for one of the products specified in the group. You need to either purchase more licenses for the product or free up unused licenses from other users or groups.

To see how many licenses are available, go to Microsoft Entra - Identity - Billing , then Licenses , then All products .

To see which users and groups are consuming licenses, select a product. Under Licensed users , you see a list of all users who have licenses assigned directly or via one or more groups. Under Licensed groups , you see all groups with product licenses assigned.

PowerShell : PowerShell cmdlets report this error as CountViolation .

Service plans that conflict

Problem : One of the products specified in the group contains a service plan that conflicts with another service plan that's already assigned to the user via a different product. Some service plans are configured in a way that they can't be assigned to the same user as another, related service plan.

Consider the following example. A user has a license for Office 365 Enterprise E1 assigned directly, with all the plans enabled. The user is added to a group that has the Office 365 Enterprise E3 product assigned to it. The E3 product contains service plans that can't overlap with the plans that are included in E1, so the group license assignment fails with the Conflicting service plans error. In this example, the conflicting service plans are:

- SharePoint Online (Plan 2) conflicts with SharePoint Online (Plan 1).

- Exchange Online (Plan 2) conflicts with Exchange Online (Plan 1).

To solve this conflict, you need to disable two of the plans. You can disable the E1 license directly assigned to the user. Or, you need to modify the entire group license assignment and disable the plans in the E3 license. Alternatively, you might decide to remove the E1 license from the user if it's redundant in the context of the E3 license.

The decision about how to resolve conflicting product licenses always belongs to the administrator. Microsoft Entra ID doesn't automatically resolve license conflicts.

PowerShell : PowerShell cmdlets report this error as MutuallyExclusiveViolation .

Other products depend on this license

Problem : One of the products specified in the group contains a service plan that must be enabled for another service plan, in another product, to function. This error occurs when Microsoft Entra ID attempts to remove the underlying service plan. For example, this can happen when you remove the user from the group.

To solve this problem, you need to make sure that the required plan is still assigned to users through some other method or that the dependent services are disabled for those users. After doing that, you can properly remove the group license from those users.

PowerShell : PowerShell cmdlets report this error as DependencyViolation .

Usage location isn't allowed

Problem : Some Microsoft services aren't available in all locations because of local laws and regulations. Before you can assign a license to a user, you must specify the Usage location property for the user. You can specify the location under the User , then Profile , then Edit the section in the Azure portal.

When Microsoft Entra ID attempts to assign a group license to a user whose usage location isn't supported, it fails and records an error on the user.

To solve this problem, remove users from unsupported locations from the licensed group. Alternatively, if the current usage location values don't represent the actual user location, you can modify them so that the licenses are correctly assigned next time (if the new location is supported). You can specify the usage location under the user's Properties tab in the Microsoft Entra admin center .

PowerShell : PowerShell cmdlets report this error as ProhibitedInUsageLocationViolation .

Note

When Microsoft Entra ID assigns group licenses, any users without a specified usage location inherit the location of the directory. We recommend that administrators set the correct usage location values on users before using group-based licensing to comply with local laws and regulations.

Duplicate proxy addresses

If you use Exchange Online, some users in your organization might be incorrectly configured with the same proxy address value. When group-based licensing tries to assign a license to such a user, it fails and shows “Proxy address is already being used.”

After you resolve any proxy address problems for the affected users, make sure to force license processing on the group to ensure that the licenses can now be applied.

Microsoft Entra Mail and ProxyAddresses attribute change

Problem : While updating license assignment on a user or a group, you might see that the Microsoft Entra Mail and ProxyAddresses attribute of some users are changed.

Updating license assignment on a user causes the proxy address calculation to be triggered, which can change user attributes.

LicenseAssignmentAttributeConcurrencyException in audit logs

Problem : User has LicenseAssignmentAttributeConcurrencyException for license assignment in audit logs. When group-based licensing tries to process concurrent license assignment of the same license to a user, this exception is recorded on the user. This typically happens when a user is a member of more than one group with same assigned license. Microsoft Entra ID retries processing the user license and will resolve the issue. There's no action required from the customer to fix this issue.

More than one product license assigned to a group

You can assign more than one product license to a group. For example, you can assign Office 365 Enterprise E3 and Enterprise Mobility + Security to a group to easily enable all included services for users.

Microsoft Entra ID attempts to assign all licenses that are specified in the group to each user. If Microsoft Entra ID can't assign one of the products because of business logic problems, it won't assign the other licenses in the group either. An example is if there aren't enough licenses for all, or if there are conflicts with other services that are enabled on the user.

You can see the users who failed to get assigned and check which products are affected by this problem.

When a licensed group is deleted

You must remove all licenses assigned to a group before you can delete the group. However, removing licenses from all the users in the group can take time. There can be failures if user has a dependent license assigned. If a user has a license that's dependent on a license, which is being removed due to group deletion, the license assignment to the user is converted from inherited to direct.

For example, consider a group that has Office 365 E3/E5 assigned with a Skype for Business service plan enabled. Also imagine that a few members of the group have Audio Conferencing licenses assigned directly. When the group is deleted, group-based licensing tries to remove Office 365 E3/E5 from all users. Because Audio Conferencing is dependent on Skype for Business, for any users with Audio Conferencing assigned, group-based licensing converts the Office 365 E3/E5 licenses to direct license assignment.

Manage licenses for products with prerequisites

Some Microsoft Online products you might own are add-ons . Add-ons require a prerequisite service plan to be enabled for a user or a group before they can be assigned a license. With group-based licensing, the system requires that both the prerequisite and add-on service plans be present in the same group to ensure that any users who are added to the group can receive the fully working product. Let's consider the following example:

Microsoft Workplace Analytics is an add-on product. It contains a single service plan with the same name. We can only assign this service plan to a user, or group, when one of the following prerequisites is also assigned:

- Exchange Online (Plan 1)

- Exchange Online (Plan 2)

If we try to assign this product on its own to a group, the portal returns a notification message. If we select the item details, it shows the following error message:

License operation failed. Make sure that the group has necessary services before adding or removing a dependent service. The service Microsoft Workplace Analytics requires Exchange Online (Plan 2) to be enabled as well .

To assign this add-on license to a group, we must ensure that the group also contains the prerequisite service plan. For example, we might update an existing group that already contains the full Office 365 E3 product, and then add the add-on product to it.

It's also possible to create a standalone group that contains only the minimum required products to make the add-on work. It can then be used to license only selected users for the add-on product. Based on the previous example, you would assign the following products to the same group:

- Office 365 Enterprise E3 with only the Exchange Online (Plan 2) service plan enabled

- Microsoft Workplace Analytics

From now on, any users added to this group consume one license of the E3 product and one license of the Workplace Analytics product. At the same time, those users can be members of another group that gives them the full E3 product, and they still consume only one license for that product.

Tip

You can create multiple groups for each prerequisite service plan. For example, if you use both Office 365 Enterprise E1 and Office 365 Enterprise E3 for your users, you can create two groups to license Microsoft Workplace Analytics: one that uses E1 as a prerequisite and the other that uses E3. This lets you distribute the add-on to E1 and E3 users without consuming more licenses.

Force the group license process to resolve errors

Depending on what steps taken to resolve the errors, it might be necessary to manually trigger the processing of a group to update the user state.

For example, if you free up some licenses by removing direct license assignments from users, you need to trigger the processing of groups that previously failed to fully license all user members. To reprocess a group, go to the group pane, open Licenses , and then select the Reprocess button on the toolbar.

Force the user license process to resolve errors

Depending on what steps taken to resolve the errors, it might be necessary to manually trigger the processing of a user to update the user's state.

For example, after you resolve duplicate proxy address problem for an affected user, you need to trigger the processing of the user. To reprocess a user, go to the user pane, open Licenses , and then select the Reprocess button on the toolbar.

How to migrate users with individual licenses to group licenses

You can have existing licenses deployed to users in the organizations via direct assignment; that is, using PowerShell scripts or other tools to assign individual user licenses. Before you begin using group-based licensing to manage licenses in your organization, you can use this migration plan to seamlessly replace existing solutions with group-based licensing.

Keep in mind that you should avoid a situation in which migrating to group-based licensing results in users temporarily losing their currently assigned licenses. Any process that result in removal of licenses should be avoided to remove the risk of users losing access to services and their data.

Recommended migration process

- You have existing automation (for example, PowerShell) managing license assignment and removal for users. Leave it running as is.

You have existing automation (for example, PowerShell) managing license assignment and removal for users. Leave it running as is.

- Create a new licensing group (or decide which existing groups to use) and make sure that all required users are added as members.

Create a new licensing group (or decide which existing groups to use) and make sure that all required users are added as members.

- Assign the required licenses to those groups; your goal should be to reflect the same licensing state your existing automation (for example, PowerShell) is applying to those users.

Assign the required licenses to those groups; your goal should be to reflect the same licensing state your existing automation (for example, PowerShell) is applying to those users.

- Verify that licenses are applied to all users in those groups. This application can be done by checking the processing state on each group and by checking Audit Logs. You can perform a random check of a few individual users by looking at their license details. You see that they have the same licenses assigned “directly” and “inherited” from groups. You can run a PowerShell script to verify how licenses are assigned to users . When the same product license is assigned to the user both directly and through a group, only one license is consumed by the user. Hence no more licenses are required to perform migration.

Verify that licenses are applied to all users in those groups. This application can be done by checking the processing state on each group and by checking Audit Logs.

- You can perform a random check of a few individual users by looking at their license details. You see that they have the same licenses assigned “directly” and “inherited” from groups.

- You can run a PowerShell script to verify how licenses are assigned to users .

- When the same product license is assigned to the user both directly and through a group, only one license is consumed by the user. Hence no more licenses are required to perform migration.

- Verify that no license assignments failed by checking each group for users in error state.

Verify that no license assignments failed by checking each group for users in error state.

Consider removing the original direct assignments. We recommend that you do it gradually, and monitor the outcome on a subset of users first. If you leave the original direct assignments on users, when the users leave their licensed groups they retain the directly assigned licenses, which might not be what you want.

An example

An organization has 1,000 users. All users require Office 365 Enterprise E3 licenses. Currently the organization has a PowerShell script running on premises, adding and removing licenses from users as they come and go. However, the organization wants to replace the script with group-based licensing so licenses can be managed automatically by Microsoft Entra ID.

Here is what the migration process could look like:

- Using the Azure portal, assign the Office 365 E3 license to the All users group in Microsoft Entra ID.

Using the Azure portal, assign the Office 365 E3 license to the All users group in Microsoft Entra ID.

- Confirm that license assignment has completed for all users. Go to the overview page for the group, select Licenses , and check the processing status at the top of the Licenses page. Look for “Latest license changes have been applied to all users" to confirm processing has completed. Look for a notification on top about any users for whom licenses were not successfully assigned. Did we run out of licenses for some users? Do some users have conflicting license plans that prevent them from inheriting group licenses?

Confirm that license assignment has completed for all users. Go to the overview page for the group, select Licenses , and check the processing status at the top of the Licenses page.

- Look for “Latest license changes have been applied to all users" to confirm processing has completed.

- Look for a notification on top about any users for whom licenses were not successfully assigned. Did we run out of licenses for some users? Do some users have conflicting license plans that prevent them from inheriting group licenses?

- You need to check a few users to verify that they have both the direct and group licenses applied. Go to the profile page for a user, select Licenses, and examine the state of licenses.

You need to check a few users to verify that they have both the direct and group licenses applied. Go to the profile page for a user, select Licenses, and examine the state of licenses.

- This is the expected user state during migration:

- After confirming that both direct and group licenses are equivalent, you can start removing direct licenses from users. You can test this by removing them for individual users in the portal and then run automation scripts to have them removed in bulk. Here's an example of the same user with the direct licenses removed through the portal. Notice that the license state remains unchanged, but we no longer see direct assignments.

Change license assignments for a user or group in Microsoft Entra ID

This section describes how to move users and groups between service license plans in Microsoft Entra ID. The goal is to ensure that there's no loss of service or data during the license change. Users should switch between services seamlessly. The license plan assignment steps in this section describe changing a user or group on Office 365 E1 to Office 365 E3, but the steps apply to all license plans. When you update license assignments for a user or group, the license assignment removals and new assignments are made simultaneously so that users don't lose access to their services during license changes or see license conflicts between plans.

Before you update the license assignments, verify certain assumptions are true for all of the users or groups to be updated. If the assumptions aren't true for all of the users in a group, the migration might fail for some. As a result, some of the users might lose access to services or data. Ensure that:

- Users have the current license plan that's assigned to a group and inherited by the user and not assigned directly.

- You have enough available licenses for the license plan you're assigning. If you don't have enough licenses, some users might not be assigned the new license plan. You can check the number of available licenses.

- Always confirm users don't have assigned service licenses that can conflict with the desired license or prevent removal of the current license. For example, a license from a service such as Workplace Analytics or Project Online that has a dependency on other services.

- If you manage groups on-premises and sync them into Microsoft Entra ID via Microsoft Entra Connect, then you add or remove users by using your on-premises system. It can take some time for the changes to sync with Microsoft Entra ID to be picked up by group licensing.

- If you're using Microsoft Entra dynamic group memberships, you add or remove users by changing their attributes, but the update process for license assignments remains the same.

Unit 2.2.10 - Exercise - change user license assignments

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/10-exercise-change-user-license-assignments

Exercise - change user license assignments

Exercise environment needs - this lab assumes you have a basic Microsoft Entra tenant with at least User Administrator rights to complete it. You can get a free trial subscription at Try Microsoft Azure for free .

Create a new user in Microsoft Entra ID

- Browse to the Microsoft Entra admin center .

Browse to the Microsoft Entra admin center .

- In the left navigation, under Identity , select Users .

In the left navigation, under Identity , select Users .

- In the Users page, on the menu, select + New user and then Create new user .

In the Users page, on the menu, select + New user and then Create new user .

- Create a user using the following information: Setting Value User name DominiqueK Name Dominique Koch First name Dominique Last name Koch Password Make a unique password for the user Usage location Select your preferred usage location

Create a user using the following information:

Setting

Value

User name

DominiqueK

Name

Dominique Koch

First name

Dominique

Last name

Koch

Password

Make a unique password for the user

Usage location

Select your preferred usage location

- When complete, verify the account for Dominique Koch is shown in the All users list.

When complete, verify the account for Dominique Koch is shown in the All users list.

Update user license assignments

License assignment to individual users is managed through the Microsoft 365 admin center.

- Open the Microsoft 365 admin center .

- Select Billing , then select Licenses .

- Select an available license from the list.

- Select Licensed users from the menu near the top of the page.

- Select + Assign licenses .

- Search for and select Dominique Koch , then select Assign at the bottom of the page.

- When complete, verify the license is listed on Dominique Koch's profile in the Microsoft Entra admin center under Identity > Users > select the user > Licenses .

Unit 2.2.11 - Create custom security attributes

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/11-create-custom-security-attributes

Create custom security attributes

What is a custom security attribute?

Custom security attributes in Microsoft Entra ID are business-specific attributes (key-value pairs) that you can define and assign to Microsoft Entra objects. These attributes can be used to store information, categorize objects, or enforce fine-grained access control over specific Azure resources.

Why use custom security attributes?

- Extend user profiles, such as add Hourly Salary to all my employees.

- Ensure only administrators can see the Hourly Salary attribute in my employees' profiles.

- Categorize hundreds or thousands of applications to easily create a filterable inventory for auditing.

- Grant users access to the Azure Storage blobs belonging to a project.

What can I do with custom security attributes?

- Define business-specific information (attributes) for your tenant.

- Add custom security attributes to Microsoft Entra users and enterprise applications (service principals).

- Manage Microsoft Entra objects using custom security attributes with queries and filters.

- Provide attribute governance so attributes determine who can get access.

Custom security attributes are not supported in Microsoft Entra Domain Services, SAML token claims, or JSON Web Token (JWT) claims.

Features of custom security attributes

- Available tenant-wide

- Include a description

- Support different data types: Boolean, integer, string

- Support single value or multiple values

- Support user-defined free-form values or predefined values

- Assign custom security attributes to directory synced users from an on-premises Active Directory

Unit 2.2.12 - Explore automatic user creation

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/12-explore-automatic-user-creation

Explore automatic user creation

Components of SCIM (System for Cross-Domain Identity Management)

- HCM system - Applications and technologies that enable Human Capital Management process and practices that support and automate HR processes throughout the employee lifecycle.

- Microsoft Entra Provisioning Service - Uses the SCIM 2.0 protocol for automatic provisioning. The service connects to the SCIM endpoint for the application, and uses the SCIM user object schema and REST APIs to automate provisioning and deprovisioning of users and groups.

- Microsoft Entra ID - User repository used to manage the lifecycle of identities and their entitlements.

- Target system - Application or system that has SCIM endpoint and works with the Microsoft Entra provisioning to enable automatic provisioning of users and groups.

Why use SCIM?

System for Cross-Domain Identity Management (SCIM) is an open standard protocol for automating the exchange of user identity information between identity domains and IT systems. SCIM ensures that employees added to the Human Capital Management (HCM) system automatically have accounts created in Microsoft Entra ID or Windows Server Active Directory. User attributes and profiles are synchronized between the two systems, updating, or removing users based on the user status or role change.

The key is keeping your identity systems up to date. If a user can be automatically deprovisioned from Microsoft Entra ID as soon as they're removed from your HR systems, you have less worry about a possible breach.

API-driven inbound provisioning

Not all HR systems expose a SCIM endpoint. For these scenarios, Microsoft Entra ID supports API-driven inbound provisioning , which reached general availability in March 2024. Instead of requiring the source system to push data via SCIM, any automation tool, or script can retrieve workforce data from any system of record and send it to the Microsoft Entra provisioning API. Supported authoritative sources include Workday, SAP SuccessFactors, and any custom HR system integrated via the API. This approach gives organizations flexibility to automate identity lifecycle management regardless of their HR platform's native integration capabilities.

Unit 2.2.13 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/13-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Choose the best response for each of the questions below.

Check your knowledge

Unit 2.2.14 - Summary and resources

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-configure-manage-identities/14-summary-resources

Summary and resources

You completed this module, you are able to:

- Create, configure, and manage users

- Create, configure, and manage groups

- Manage licenses

- Configure and manage device registration

- Explore custom security attributes and automatic account provisioning

Resources

Use these resources to discover more:

- Quickstart: Create and assign a user account

Quickstart: Create and assign a user account

- Bulk create users in Microsoft Entra ID

Bulk create users in Microsoft Entra ID

- Create a basic group and add members using Microsoft Entra ID

Create a basic group and add members using Microsoft Entra ID

- Create or update a dynamic membership group in Microsoft Entra ID

Create or update a dynamic membership group in Microsoft Entra ID

- What is Microsoft Entra Cloud Sync?

What is Microsoft Entra Cloud Sync?

- Manage license requests

Manage license requests

- Assign licenses to users - Microsoft 365 Admin Center

Assign licenses to users - Microsoft 365 Admin Center

- Plan Microsoft Entra device deployment

Plan Microsoft Entra device deployment

- API-driven inbound provisioning concepts

API-driven inbound provisioning concepts

LP 2 M3 - Describe the core architectural components of Azure

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/describe-core-architectural-components-of-azure/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 2.3.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/describe-core-architectural-components-of-azure/1-introduction

Introduction

In this module, you’ll be introduced to the core architectural components of Azure. You’ll learn about Azure's physical layout: datacenters, availability zones, and regions; and you’ll learn about Azure's management structure: resources and resource groups, subscriptions, and management groups.

Learning objectives

After completing this module, you’ll be able to:

- Describe Azure regions, region pairs, and sovereign regions.

- Describe Availability Zones.

- Describe Azure datacenters.

- Describe Azure resources and Resource Groups.

- Describe subscriptions.

- Describe management groups.

- Describe the hierarchy of resource groups, subscriptions, and management groups.

Unit 2.3.2 - What is Microsoft Azure

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/describe-core-architectural-components-of-azure/2-what-microsoft-azure

What is Microsoft Azure

Azure is a continually expanding set of cloud services that help you meet current and future IT challenges. Azure gives you the freedom to build, manage, and deploy applications on a massive global network using your favorite tools and frameworks.

What does Azure offer?

Limitless innovation. Build intelligent apps and solutions with advanced technology, tools, and services to take your operations to the next level. Seamlessly unify your technology to simplify platform management and deliver innovations efficiently and securely on a trusted cloud.

- Bring ideas to life: Build on a trusted platform to advance your team's capabilities with industry-leading AI and cloud services.

- Seamlessly unify: Efficiently manage all your infrastructure, data, analytics, and AI solutions across an integrated platform.

- Innovate on trust: Rely on trusted technology from a partner who's dedicated to security and responsibility.

What can I do with Azure?

Azure provides hundreds of services that enable you to do everything from running your existing applications on virtual machines to exploring new software paradigms, such as intelligent bots and generative AI.

Many teams start exploring the cloud by moving their existing applications to virtual machines (VMs) that run in Azure. Migrating your existing apps to VMs is a good start, but the cloud is much more than a different place to run your VMs.

As your skills grow, you can modernize one workload at a time, such as moving from manually managed servers to managed databases, autoscaling web apps, or event-driven services.

Practical example

Suppose your organization runs an internal app with seasonal demand spikes. In Azure, you can host the app on virtual machines or managed app services, store data in managed databases, and monitor health from a centralized dashboard. As demand increases, you can scale resources up or out and then scale back when demand drops so you're not paying for unused capacity year-round.

For example, Azure provides Azure AI services and Azure OpenAI Service so you can add language, vision, speech, and generative AI capabilities to your applications. It also provides Azure Machine Learning, Internet of Things (IoT) services, and storage solutions that dynamically grow to accommodate massive amounts of data. Azure services enable solutions that aren't feasible without the power of the cloud.

Unit 2.3.3 - Get started with Azure accounts

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/describe-core-architectural-components-of-azure/3-get-started-azure-accounts

Get started with Azure accounts

To create and use Azure services, you need an Azure subscription. When you're working with your own applications and workloads, you create an Azure account, and a subscription is created for you. After you've created an Azure account, you're free to create additional subscriptions. For example, your team might use a single Azure account and separate subscriptions for development, testing, and production workloads. After you've created an Azure subscription, you can start creating Azure resources within each subscription.

If you're new to Azure, you can sign up for a free account on the Azure website to start exploring at no cost to you. When you're ready, you can choose to upgrade your free account. You can also create a new subscription that enables you to start paying for Azure services you need beyond the limits of a free account.

Create an Azure account

You can purchase Azure access directly from Microsoft by signing up on the Azure website or through a Microsoft representative. You can also purchase Azure access through a Microsoft partner. Cloud Solution Provider partners offer a range of complete managed-cloud solutions for Azure.

What is the Azure free account?

The Azure free account includes:

- Free access to popular Azure products for 12 months.

- A credit to use for the first 30 days.

- Access to more than 65 services that are always free.

The Azure free account is an excellent way for new users to get started and explore. To sign up, you need a phone number, a credit card, and a Microsoft or GitHub account. The credit card information is used for identity verification only. You won't be charged for any services until you upgrade to a paid subscription.

What is the Azure free student account?

The Azure free student account offer includes:

- Free access to certain Azure services for 12 months.

- A credit to use in the first 12 months.

- Free access to certain software developer tools.

The Azure free student account is an offer for students that gives $100 credit and free developer tools. Also, you can sign up without a credit card.

If you're practicing by creating resources in Azure, monitor usage and remove resources you no longer need to avoid unexpected costs.

Unit 2.3.4 - Describe Azure physical infrastructure

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/describe-core-architectural-components-of-azure/5-describe-azure-physical-infrastructure

Describe Azure physical infrastructure

Azure's core architectural components can be broken down into two main groupings: the physical infrastructure and the management infrastructure. This unit covers the physical side — how Azure organizes its datacenters, regions, and availability zones to deliver reliable services worldwide.

Physical infrastructure

The physical infrastructure for Azure starts with datacenters. These datacenters are facilities with servers arranged in racks, with dedicated power, cooling, and networking infrastructure — similar to an on-premises datacenter, but at a much larger scale.

As a global cloud provider, Azure has datacenters around the world. However, you don't interact with individual datacenters directly. Instead, datacenters are grouped into Azure Regions and Azure Availability Zones that provide resiliency and reliability for your workloads.

The Global infrastructure site gives you a chance to interactively explore the underlying Azure infrastructure.

Regions

A region is a geographical area on the planet that contains at least one, but potentially multiple datacenters that are nearby and networked together with a low-latency network. Azure intelligently assigns and controls the resources within each region to ensure workloads are appropriately balanced.

When you deploy a resource in Azure, you'll often need to choose the region where you want your resource deployed.

Note

Some services or virtual machine (VM) features are only available in certain regions, such as specific VM sizes or storage types. There are also some global Azure services that don't require you to select a particular region, such as Microsoft Entra ID, Azure Traffic Manager, and Azure DNS.

Availability Zones

Availability zones are physically separate datacenters within an Azure region. Each availability zone is made up of one or more datacenters equipped with independent power, cooling, and networking. An availability zone is set up to be an isolation boundary. If one zone goes down, the other continues working. Availability zones are connected through high-speed, private fiber-optic networks.

Important

To ensure resiliency, a minimum of three separate availability zones are present in all availability zone-enabled regions. However, not all Azure Regions currently support availability zones.

Use availability zones for your workloads

When you run your own on-premises infrastructure, setting up redundancy means buying and maintaining duplicate hardware. With Azure, you can protect your workloads by spreading them across availability zones within a region.

You place your VMs, storage, databases, and other resources in one availability zone and replicate them to other zones within the same region. Keep in mind that there could be a cost to duplicating your services and transferring data between zones.

Azure services that support availability zones fall into three categories:

- Zonal services: You pin the resource to a specific zone (for example, VMs, managed disks, IP addresses).

- Zone-redundant services: The platform replicates automatically across zones (for example, zone-redundant storage, SQL Database).

- Non-regional services: Services are always available from Azure geographies and are resilient to zone-wide outages as well as region-wide outages.

Even with the additional resiliency that availability zones provide, it’s possible that an event could be so large that it impacts multiple availability zones in a single region. To provide even further resilience, Azure has Region Pairs.

Region pairs

Most Azure regions are paired with another region within the same geography (such as US, Europe, or Asia) at least 300 miles away. This approach allows for the replication of resources across a geography that helps reduce the likelihood of interruptions because of events such as natural disasters, civil unrest, power outages, or physical network outages that affect an entire region. For example, if a region in a pair was affected by a natural disaster, services would automatically fail over to the other region in its region pair.

Important

Not all Azure services automatically replicate data or automatically fall back from a failed region to cross-replicate to another enabled region. In these scenarios, recovery and replication must be configured by the customer.

Examples of region pairs in Azure are West US paired with East US and Southeast Asia paired with East Asia. Because the pair of regions is directly connected and far enough apart to be isolated from regional disasters, you can use them to provide reliable services and data redundancy.

Additional advantages of region pairs:

- If an extensive Azure outage occurs, one region out of every pair is prioritized to make sure at least one is restored as quickly as possible for applications hosted in that region pair.

- Planned Azure updates are rolled out to paired regions one region at a time to minimize downtime and risk of application outage.

- Data continues to reside within the same geography as its pair (except for Brazil South) for data-residency and compliance purposes.

Important

Most regions are paired in two directions, meaning they are the backup for the region that provides a backup for them (West US and East US back each other up). However, some regions, such as Brazil South, are paired in only one direction. In a one-direction pairing, the Primary region does not provide backup for its secondary region. Brazil South is unique because it's paired with a region outside of its geography. Brazil South's secondary region is South Central US. The secondary region of South Central US isn't Brazil South. Additionally, some regions (such as Italy North, Poland Central, and Israel Central) don't have a traditional region pair and instead rely on availability zones and geo-redundant storage for resiliency.

Sovereign Regions

In addition to regular regions, Azure also has sovereign regions. Sovereign regions are instances of Azure that are isolated from the main instance of Azure. You may need to use a sovereign region for compliance or legal purposes.

Azure sovereign regions include:

- US DoD Central, US Gov Virginia, US Gov Arizona, and more: These regions are physical and logical network-isolated instances of Azure for U.S. government agencies and partners. These datacenters are operated by screened U.S. personnel and include additional compliance certifications.

- China East, China North, and more: These regions are available through a unique partnership between Microsoft and 21Vianet, whereby Microsoft doesn't directly maintain the datacenters.

Unit 2.3.5 - Describe Azure management infrastructure

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/describe-core-architectural-components-of-azure/6-describe-azure-management-infrastructure

Describe Azure management infrastructure

The management infrastructure includes Azure resources and resource groups, subscriptions, and accounts. Understanding this hierarchy helps you organize resources, control who can access what, and manage costs as your Azure usage grows.

Azure resources and resource groups

A resource is the basic building block of Azure. Anything you create, provision, or deploy is a resource. VMs, virtual networks, databases, and Azure AI services are all examples of resources.

Resource groups are groupings of resources. Every resource must belong to exactly one resource group. You can move some resources between groups, but a resource is only associated with one group at a time. Resource groups can't be nested, and they can't be renamed after creation, so choose a clear naming convention from the start.

Actions you apply to a resource group affect all resources inside it. Deleting a resource group deletes everything in it. Granting or denying access applies to all its resources.

For example, if you're setting up a temporary dev environment, grouping all the resources together lets you delete the entire group when you're done. If you're running multiple projects, create a separate resource group for each so each team only sees and manages its own resources.

There are no hard rules for structuring resource groups — choose the approach that works best for your situation.

Azure subscriptions

In Azure, subscriptions are a unit of management, billing, and scale. Subscriptions let you organize resource groups and control billing separately from access.

Using Azure requires an Azure subscription. A subscription provides access to Azure products and services and serves as a billing unit. An Azure subscription links to an Azure account, which is an identity in Microsoft Entra ID or in a directory that Microsoft Entra ID trusts.

An account can have multiple subscriptions, but only one is required. In a multi-subscription account, you can configure different billing models and access policies. There are two types of subscription boundaries:

- Billing boundary : Determines how an Azure account is billed. You can create multiple subscriptions for different billing requirements. Azure generates separate billing reports and invoices for each subscription.

- Access control boundary : Azure applies access-management policies at the subscription level. For example, you might create one subscription for your development work and another for production, each with different spending limits and access rules.

Create additional Azure subscriptions

You might create additional subscriptions to separate:

- Environments : Subscriptions for lifecycle stages such as sandbox, development, test, and production. Access control occurs at the subscription level, making this a natural boundary.

- Team and workload boundaries : Give each project its own subscription so costs are easy to track, or separate sandbox environments from production.

- Billing : Create subscriptions to track costs separately — for instance, one for production workloads and another for development and testing.

Azure management groups

Resources go into resource groups, and resource groups go into subscriptions. For a small environment, that's enough. But when you have many subscriptions across multiple teams or geographies, you need a way to manage access and policies at a higher level.

Azure management groups sit above subscriptions. You organize subscriptions into management groups and apply governance conditions — like access policies or compliance rules — to the group. All subscriptions in a management group automatically inherit those conditions, just as resources inherit settings from their resource group. Management groups can be nested up to six levels deep (not counting the root level or the subscription level), letting you build a hierarchy that mirrors your organization.

Every Microsoft Entra tenant has a single top-level Tenant Root Group. All other management groups and subscriptions fold up to this root group, which lets you apply governance policies globally.

Management group, subscriptions, and resource group hierarchy

You can build a flexible structure of management groups and subscriptions to organize your resources into a hierarchy for unified policy and access management.

Examples of how you could use management groups:

- Apply a policy across subscriptions . You could limit VM locations to the US West Region in a group called Production. This policy inherits to all subscriptions under that management group and applies to all VMs in those subscriptions. The resource or subscription owner can't override it, which strengthens governance.

- Grant access to multiple subscriptions at once . By placing subscriptions under a management group, you can create one Azure RBAC assignment on the group. All sub-management groups, subscriptions, resource groups, and resources underneath inherit those permissions — no need to script Azure RBAC across individual subscriptions.

Important facts about management groups:

- A single directory supports up to 10,000 management groups.

- Each management group and subscription can have only one parent.

Unit 2.3.6 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/describe-core-architectural-components-of-azure/8-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Choose the best response for each question.

Check your knowledge

Unit 2.3.7 - Summary

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/describe-core-architectural-components-of-azure/9-summary

Summary

In this module, you learned about the physical and management structure of Microsoft Azure. You were introduced to the relationship between datacenters, availability zones, and regions. You explored how the infrastructure supports the benefits of the cloud, such as high availability and reliability. You also learned about the management infrastructure of Azure. You explored how resources and resource groups are related, and how subscriptions and management groups can help manage resources.

Learning objectives

You should now be able to:

- Describe Azure regions, region pairs, and sovereign regions.

- Describe Availability Zones.

- Describe Azure datacenters.

- Describe Azure resources and Resource Groups.

- Describe subscriptions.

- Describe management groups.

- Describe the hierarchy of resource groups, subscriptions, and management groups.

Explore with Copilot

Tip

Try one of these prompts in Copilot Chat:

- "Build a concept map that connects regions, Availability Zones, datacenters, resources, resource groups, subscriptions, and management groups."

- "Design a subscription and management-group structure for an organization with multiple departments and compliance boundaries."

- "Explain region pairs and sovereign regions, then recommend a resiliency approach for a workload with strict data residency requirements."

LP 2 M4 - Azure Policy initiatives

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/sovereignty-policy-initiatives/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 2.4.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/sovereignty-policy-initiatives/overview

Introduction

Azure Policy is a service that allows you to create, assign, and manage governance policies that enforce rules and effects over Azure resources to ensure that they stay compliant with your IT governance standards. These policies enforce various rules and effects on resources, ensuring that they adhere to corporate standards and service-level agreements. These policies are described in JSON format and are known as policy definitions. Azure Policy is crucial for enforcing organizational standards and assessing compliance on a large scale.

Azure Policy initiatives are a collection of Azure Policy definitions that are grouped together toward a specific goal or purpose. By consolidating multiple Azure policies into a single item, Azure Policy initiatives allow centralized control and enforcement of configurations across Azure resources.

Industry-specific organizations in sectors like government, public sector, finance, and others accelerate digital transformation and achieve better business outcomes. They can achieve this objective by adopting specific, sovereignty-focused Azure Policy initiatives to address the complexity of compliance with national and regional regulatory requirements.

Customers can create Azure Policy initiatives that aid in customizing deployments to reduce the time needed to audit environments and help meet established regulatory compliance frameworks and government requirements. The initiatives help public sector partners and customers create cloud guardrails and enforce specific regulations effectively. They can layer policy initiatives to help form a complete solution for their specific needs, and they can use deployment automation to ensure consistency, best practices, and save time.

In this module, you learn how Azure Policy can help do the common tasks related to creating, assigning, and managing policies across your organization, such as:

- Assign a policy to enforce a condition for resources you create in the future

- Create and assign an initiative definition to track compliance for multiple resources

- Resolve a noncompliant or denied resource

- Implement a new policy across an organization

Important

Organizations are wholly responsible for ensuring their own compliance with all applicable laws and regulations. The information provided in this document does not constitute legal advice, and organizations should consult their legal advisors for any questions regarding regulatory compliance.

Unit 2.4.2 - Cloud Adoption Framework for Azure

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/sovereignty-policy-initiatives/cloud-adoption-framework

Cloud Adoption Framework for Azure

The Microsoft Cloud Adoption Framework for Azure offers comprehensive technical guidance for Microsoft Azure. This end-to-end framework helps cloud architects, IT experts, and business leaders reach their cloud adoption objectives. Cloud Adoption Framework includes best practices, documentation, and tools that Microsoft employees, partners, and customers contribute to formulate and implement effective business and technology strategies for the cloud. For more information, see Microsoft Cloud Adoption Framework for Azure documentation - Cloud Adoption Framework | Microsoft Learn .

The following diagram provides high-level information about different methodologies that are included in Microsoft Cloud Adoption Framework for Azure for each phase of your cloud adoption life cycle. Within the framework, Microsoft Azure Policy plays a significant role in the governance framework to help govern your cloud environment and workloads.

Cloud governance refers to the management of cloud usage in your organization. The Cloud Adoption Framework - Govern methodology offers a systematic framework for setting up and improving cloud governance in Azure. This guidance applies to organizations across various industries and it addresses crucial areas, such as regulatory compliance, security, operations, cost management, data, resource management, and AI. It's essential for defining and maintaining efficient cloud use.

Comprehensive cloud governance oversees all aspects of cloud use, minimizes various risks (such as compliance, security, resource management, and data-related concerns), and optimizes cloud operations throughout the organization. It ensures that cloud activities are consistent with the overall cloud strategy, facilitating the achievement of business objectives with reduced obstacles.

Steps for cloud governance

Cloud governance is a continuous process. It requires ongoing monitoring, evaluation, and adjustments to adapt to evolving technologies, risks, and compliance requirements. The Cloud Adoption Framework - Govern methodology divides cloud governance into five steps.

- Build a governance team - Establish a dedicated cloud governance team that's responsible for defining, maintaining, and reporting on the progress of cloud governance policies.

- Assess cloud risks - Conduct a thorough risk assessment that's unique to your organization, addressing all risk categories, including regulatory compliance, security, operations, costs, data management, resource management, and AI-related risks.

- Document cloud governance policies - Clearly document cloud governance policies that dictate acceptable cloud usage and outline the rules and guidelines that mitigate identified risks.

- Enforce cloud governance policies - Implement a systematic approach to ensure compliance with cloud governance policies. Use automated tools alongside manual oversight to enforce compliance. These tools help set guardrails, monitor configurations, and ensure adherence to policies.

- Monitor cloud governance - Regularly monitor cloud usage and the governance teams to ensure ongoing compliance with the established cloud governance policies.

You should complete all five steps to establish cloud governance and regularly iterate on steps 2-5 to maintain cloud governance over time.

Considerations for defining a cloud governance policy

The key considerations when defining a corporate cloud governance policy are as follows:

- Business risk – You must document the evolving business risks and the business's tolerance for risk based on data classification and application criticality.

- Policy and compliance – You must convert risk decisions into policy statements to establish cloud adoption boundaries efficiently.

- Process – You must establish processes to monitor violations and adherence to corporate policies.

The five core disciplines of cloud governance are as follows:

- Cost management – Evaluates and monitors costs, including controlling IT expenditures to establish well-defined cost management. It also includes adjusting resources according to demand. It's crucial to exercise control over cloud expenditure to derive greater value from your investments.

- Security baseline – Ensures compliance with IT security requirements by applying a security baseline to all adoption efforts.

- Resource consistency – Ensures consistency in resource configuration and enforcing practices for onboarding, recovery, and discoverability.

- Identity baseline – Ensures that the baseline for identity and access is enforced by consistently applying role definitions and assignments.

- Deployment acceleration – Accelerates the deployment of policies through centralization, consistency, and standardization across deployment templates.

Adopting these measures simplifies the compliance process and also enhances the security and efficiency of your cloud environment.

Cloud governance with Azure Policy

Azure's primary governance tool is Azure Policy . Azure Policy facilitates the governance of all resources, including current and forthcoming resources. It helps to enforce organizational standards and to assess compliance at scale by establishing guardrails across various resources.

Azure Policy allows for centralized management, allowing you to track compliance status and investigate changes leading to noncompliance. You can consolidate all compliance data into a singular repository, which simplifies auditing processes for effective cloud compliance and resource governance. The compliance dashboard offered by Azure Policy presents an aggregated view of the environment's overall state, with the ability to examine details at each resource and each policy level.

Azure Policy ensures consistent adherence to compliance standards and prevents misconfigurations. It also helps bring your resources to compliance through bulk remediation for existing resources and automatic remediation for new resources. Additionally, embedding Azure Policy directly into the Azure platform can significantly reduce the need for external approval processes, thus boosting developer productivity.

Some useful governance actions that you can enforce with Azure Policy include:

- Ensure that your team deploys Azure resources only to allowed regions.

- Enforce geo-replication rules to comply with your data residency requirements.

- Allow only certain virtual machine sizes for your cloud environment.

- Enforce the consistent application of taxonomic tags across resources.

- Recommend system updates on your servers.

- Allow multifactor authentication for all subscription accounts.

- Require resources to send diagnostic logs to an Azure Monitor Logs workspace.

Azure Policy evaluates your resources and highlights resources that aren't compliant with the policies that you create. Azure Policy can also prevent noncompliant resources from being created. Azure Policy comes with built-in policy and initiative definitions for Storage, Networking, Compute, Security Center, and Monitoring. For example, if you define a policy that only allows a certain size for the virtual machines (VMs) to be used in your environment, that policy is invoked when you create a new VM and whenever you resize existing VMs. Azure Policy also evaluates and monitors all current VMs in your environment, including VMs that were created before the policy was created.

In some cases, Azure Policy can automatically remediate noncompliant resources and configurations to ensure the integrity of the state of the resources. For example, if all resources in a specific resource group need to have the AppName tag with a value of SpecialOrders , Azure Policy can automatically apply that tag if it's missing. However, you maintain full control over your environment. If there's a particular resource that you don't want Azure Policy to automatically update, you can mark that resource as an exception, and the policy won't automatically update it.

Azure Policy also integrates with Azure DevOps by applying any continuous integration and delivery pipeline policies that pertain to the predeployment and post-deployment phases of your applications.

The objective when designing an Azure Policy should be to strike a balance between control and stability in one area with speed and results in the other. The main reason to maintain balance is to ensure that the environment remains highly manageable so that you can implement necessary levels of control to ensure governance without hindering operational efficiency or productivity. In establishing and enforcing these controls, you must take care that your speed to achieve efficiency isn't affected. Hence, achieving this balance between control and stability with speed and results, often requires thoughtful compromise, and it's necessary to carefully evaluate the potential impact before introducing new policies.

For more information, see Microsoft Cloud Adoption Framework for Azure - Cloud Adoption Framework | Microsoft Learn .

Unit 2.4.3 - Azure Policy design principles

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/sovereignty-policy-initiatives/azure-policy-design-principles

Azure Policy design principles

Governance provides mechanisms and processes to maintain control over your applications and resources in Azure. It involves planning your policy in Azure Policy and setting strategic priorities. While designing your policy, you must organize your cloud-based resources to secure, manage, and track costs that are related to your workloads.

Hierarchy for governance

Azure provides four levels of management to establish proper governance: Management groups, Subscriptions, Resource groups, and Resources. You can build a flexible structure of management groups and subscriptions to organize your resources into a hierarchy for unified policy and access management. The following diagram shows an example of creating a hierarchy for governance by using management groups.

The Azure structure starts with the tenant root group at the top, followed by a hierarchy of management groups, which can extend to six levels beneath the root. The definition of each level in the management hierarchy and relationship between these levels is as follows:

Concept

Description

Resource

A resource is the basic building block of Azure, and it includes instances of services that you create, provision, deploy, and so on. Virtual machines (VMs), virtual networks, databases, AI services, and so on, are considered resources in Azure.

Resource groups

Resource groups are groupings of resources. When you create a resource, you must place it into a resource group. While a resource group can contain many resources, a single resource can only be in one resource group at a time. When you apply an action to a resource group, that action applies to all resources in the resource group. If you delete a resource group, all resources are deleted. If you grant or deny access to a resource group, all resources in the resource group are also granted or denied access.

Subscriptions

In Azure, subscriptions are a unit of management, billing, and scale. Similar to how resource groups are a way of logically organizing resources, subscriptions allow you to logically organize your resource groups and facilitate billing. Each subscription has limits or quotas on the number of resources that you can create and use. Organizations can use subscriptions to manage costs and the resources that users, teams, and projects create. Using Azure requires an Azure subscription. An Azure subscription provides you with authenticated and authorized access to Azure products and services. It also allows you to provision resources. An Azure subscription links to an Azure account, which is an identity in Microsoft Entra ID or in a directory that Microsoft Entra ID trusts.

Management groups

Azure management groups provide a level of scope above subscriptions. If you have many subscriptions, you might need a way to efficiently manage access, policies, and compliance for those subscriptions. You organize subscriptions into containers called management groups and then apply governance conditions to the management groups. Management groups give you enterprise-grade management at a large scale, no matter what type of subscriptions you might have. Management groups can be nested.

You can apply management settings at any of these levels of scope. The level that you select determines how widely the setting is applied. Lower levels inherit settings from higher levels. For example, when you apply a policy to the subscription, the policy is applied to all resource groups and resources in that subscription. When you apply a policy on the resource group, that policy is applied to that resource group and all its resources. However, another resource group won't have that policy assignment. All subscriptions within a management group automatically inherit the conditions that are applied to the management group.

Introduction to Azure Resource Manager

Azure Resource Manager is the deployment and management service for Azure. It provides a management layer that allows you to create, update, and delete resources in your Azure account.

Azure operations are classified into two main types: control plane and data plane. The control plane helps you manage resources in your subscription, while the data plane allows you to access the capabilities provided by instances of specific resource types.

Control plane

Azure Policy operates in the control plane to enforce rules and compliance on your resources. Azure Resource Manager manages all control plane operations in Azure and includes the different components that are centralized between the different services. Azure Policy is integrated with Azure Resource Manager.

Azure Resource Manager manages essential functions, such as template-based deployments, role-based access control (RBAC), auditing, monitoring, and tagging, which provides a unified management experience for Azure resources after deployment. For example, consider a scenario where you have a storage account. With Azure Resource Manager, you can create the storage account and enforce a policy that mandates encryption for all storage accounts.

When you send a control plane request through any of the Azure APIs, tools, or SDKs, Azure Resource Manager receives the request. All capabilities that are available in the portal are also available through PowerShell, Azure CLI, REST APIs, and client SDKs. These tools use the same API to process requests, ensuring uniform results and capabilities. The Resource Manager authenticates and authorizes the request before forwarding it to the appropriate Azure resource provider that completes the operation.

Data plane

The data plane is where the actual data operations occur, and Azure Policy ensures that the resources you interact with in the data plane are compliant with your policies. Data plane operations involve direct interaction with the data stored in a resource. Continuing with the previous example, you engage with the storage account to upload or download files. This interaction is handled directly by the data plane of the storage account rather than being managed by Azure Resource Manager.

Data plane operations aren't limited to REST API. Requests are made directly to the data endpoints of services (for example, accessing data in Microsoft Azure Storage, querying an SQL database, or reading secrets from Microsoft Azure Key Vault). Each Azure service handles these requests internally, bypassing Azure Resource Manager, and directly managing the data through its resource provider. Service-specific access controls, such as RBAC or access control lists (ACLs), often manage data plane permissions. The service responds with the data or result of the data operation, ensuring that the requester has the correct permissions.

Azure Policy allows individual Azure services to implement an Azure Policy extension, enhancing policy behavior and integration with specific resource providers. Azure Policy currently supports data plane operations through the following resource provider modes:

- Microsoft.Kubernetes.Data - Used for managing Kubernetes clusters and components such as pods, containers, and ingresses.

- Microsoft.KeyVault.Data - Used for managing vaults and certificates in Azure Key Vault.

- Microsoft.Network.Data - Used for managing Microsoft Azure Virtual Network Manager custom membership policies by using Azure Policy.

- Microsoft.ManagedHSM.Data - Used for managing Azure Key Vault Managed HSM keys by using Azure Policy.

- Microsoft.DataFactory.Data - Used for using Azure Policy to deny Microsoft Azure Data Factory outbound traffic domain names.

- Microsoft.MachineLearningServices.v2.Data - Used for managing Microsoft Azure Machine Learning model deployments. This Resource Provider mode reports compliance for newly created and updated components.

For more information, see Resource Provider Modes .

Operation flows of Azure Resource Manager

Azure Resource Manager includes two scenarios for handling Azure requests: Greenfield and Brownfield . As you deploy resources, Azure Resource Manager understands when to create new resources and when to update existing resources.

Greenfield refers to a scenario where an Azure Policy (policy-first) exists, and when you're creating or updating an Azure resource.

For example, you're creating a new resource by calling an HTTPS REST API into Azure Resource Manager, that is, targeting a specific resource provider. In Azure Resource Manager, the request goes through different layers, including role-based access control (RBAC) and Azure Policy. These layers are only two of the many other layers, but it's important to understand that Azure Policy comes after RBAC. If you don't have permissions to run a given operation, then Azure Policy isn't considered or called because it would fail on the RBAC stage. If you have permissions, the request goes through Azure Policy and is evaluated against any policy. For resource updates, you send only the changes (delta) in the request payload in the existing resource. Azure Policy requires full visibility of the current state of the resource. Azure Policy merges the delta that you're sending by reading the current state. Then, the target state is obtained as a result of the merger, and that's what gets evaluated against your policies.

Brownfield is the scenario where the resources exist already (resource-first), and you're assigning a new Azure Policy to those resources.

In this case, policy evaluation happens through a compliance scan, which runs automatically every 24 hours, or it can be manually triggered. The duration of the scan is unpredictable, but after it's completed, the compliance state of existing resources is updated. To perform this evaluation, Azure Policy reads all existing resources in the scope. You can create an Azure policy that prohibits resources from being created outside of a certain region, such as West Europe. Existing resources outside this region aren't deleted but are flagged as noncompliant after the policy is applied, and future attempts to create resources outside West Europe fail.

Unit 2.4.4 - Azure Policy resources

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/sovereignty-policy-initiatives/azure-policy-resources

Azure Policy resources

Azure Policy enforces organizational standards and assesses compliance at scale. It evaluates Azure resources and actions by comparing their properties to business rules, providing an aggregated view of the environment's overall state. This policy allows for detailed analysis down to each resource and policy level with granularity. Six policy resources are available in Azure, and multiple different concepts apply to these Azure policy resources.

Definitions

Azure Policy definitions describe resource compliance conditions and the effect to take if a condition is met. Several settings determine which resources are evaluated by any Azure Policy. You explore these settings in the next unit, Azure Policy definitions . The primary concept to which these settings can be applied is scope.

Scope in Azure Policy is the same as the levels of hierarchy for governance in Azure. Four levels of management scope are under the root tenant: the management groups, subscriptions, resource groups, and resources. The definition might be saved in a management group or a subscription. The definition location determines the scope to which the initiative or policy can be assigned. An assignment also has several properties that set a scope. The use of these properties determines which resource for Azure Policy to evaluate and which resources count toward compliance

You can apply management settings at any of these levels of scope. The level that you select determines how widely the setting is applied. Lower levels inherit settings from higher levels. For more information, see Scope in Azure Policy .

Initiatives

Azure Policy initiatives, also known as a policy set, allow you to group several policy definitions to simplify assignments and management because you work with the initiatives as a single item. Initiatives offer a streamlined and automated approach to governance, allowing organizations to manage and monitor compliance at scale. The initiative definition contains all policy definitions to help track your compliance state for a larger goal, such as organizational compliance goals or compliance with regulatory frameworks. For example, multiple tagging policy definitions can be grouped into a single initiative, and rather than assigning each policy individually, you can apply the initiative to Azure resources. A JSON can be used to create a policy initiative definition. For more information, see Azure Policy initiative definition structure .

For more information about Azure Policy built-ins and patterns, see Azure Policy samples .

Built-in policy is a type of policy definition that's generated by Azure Resource Providers and is available by default. A group of such policy definitions is known as a built-in initiative . Azure built-in policy initiatives are a powerful tool set that enables centralized control across Azure resources and enforcement of specific configurations. These initiatives comprise a collection of policy definitions and support compliance with various regulatory frameworks, industry standards, and security best practices.

For a list of built-in policies and initiatives, see Policies and Initiatives .

Custom policy is a type of policy definition that's written by a policy user when no built-in policy maps to your requirements. A group of such policy definitions is known as a custom initiative . Azure Policy custom initiatives help you to tailor a set of policies specifically to your organization's unique requirements, giving you control to enforce the standards and rules that best fit your environment. Microsoft for Sovereignty makes several custom policy initiatives and compliance mappings accessible through the industry-policy-portfolio repository on GitHub.

Microsoft for Sovereignty initiatives and compliance mappings, which expand on the Azure built-in initiatives, help you automate policy enforcement and foster a robust governance framework that reduces the risk of noncompliance. Further, the initiatives also strengthen data protection measures. Organizations can use the large suite of available regulatory compliance built-in initiatives while we continue to expand on other frameworks. These initiatives are available as Azure built-in and custom policy initiatives.

For more information, see Microsoft for Sovereignty policy portfolio .

Assignments

Policy assignments define which resources are evaluated by a policy definition or initiative. Policy assignments can be done in the portal, an API call, or through the command line interface.

Policy and initiative definitions are deployed to a definition location (management group or subscription). This location determines the scope to which the initiative or policy can be assigned. The location should be the resource container shared by all resources that you want to use the policy definition on. For more information, see Definition location .

Policies and initiatives are assigned to a specific scope (management group, subscription, or resource group). While doing so, you can define several optional aspects, including the resource scope and policy definition.

- Optional resource selectors to allow gradual rollout based on resource location or type.

- Optional overrides to change the effect of a policy definition without modifying the underlying definition.

- enforcementMode can be disabled to support "what-if" scenarios without changing the definition, which is equivalent to changing the definition to an audit effect mode, but a way to do it at assignment level. For example, if the policy has Deny effects, that denial isn't effective, but you can still view the result of the compliance evaluation of that policy.

- Optional excluded scopes to exclude inner containers or resources from the assignment scope.

- Noncompliance messages can be defined.

- Parameters can be assigned values.

- If you have a policy with the deployIfNotExists effect type, a managed identity can be assigned (system-assigned or user-assigned) to turn on remediation actions. An assignment has several properties that set a scope. The use of these properties determines which resource for Azure Policy to evaluate and which resources count toward compliance. These properties map to the following concepts: Inclusion - For more information, see Azure Policy assignment structure . Exclusion - For more information, see Azure Policy assignment structure excluded scopes .

- Inclusion - For more information, see Azure Policy assignment structure .

- Exclusion - For more information, see Azure Policy assignment structure excluded scopes .

Exemptions

Use the Policy exemptions feature to exempt a resource hierarchy or an individual resource from evaluation of initiatives or definitions. Resources that are exempt count toward overall compliance but can't be evaluated or have a temporary waiver. They're created as a child object on the resource hierarchy, or the individual resource granted the exemption.

Policy exemptions aren't created during assignment time, but after, and the effect is still the same as an excluded scope. Two exemption categories exist and are used to group exemptions:

- Mitigated - The exemption is granted because the policy intent is met through another method.

- Waiver - The exemption is granted because the noncompliance state of the resource is temporarily accepted.

For more information about policy exemption, see Azure Policy exemption structure .

Attestations

Policy attestations are used by Azure Policy to set compliance states of resources or scopes targeted by manual policies . Each applicable resource requires one attestation for each manual policy assignment. For ease of management, manual policies should be designed to target the scope that defines the boundary of resources whose compliance state needs to be attested.

For more information, see Azure Policy attestation structure .

Remediations

The policy remediation task feature is used to bring resources into compliance based on a definition and assignment. Resources that are noncompliant to a modify or deployIfNotExists definition assignment can be brought into compliance by using a remediation task. Resources that are newly created or updated that are applicable to a deployIfNotExists or modify definition assignment are automatically remediated.

For more information, see Azure Policy remediation task structure .

Unit 2.4.5 - Azure Policy definitions

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/sovereignty-policy-initiatives/azure-policy-definitions

Azure Policy definitions

Azure Policy definition describes resource compliance conditions and the action or effects that take place if those conditions are met. The policy consists of two parts:

- A condition that compares a resource property field or a value, accessed by using aliases, to a required value.

- The effect determines what happens when the policy rule is evaluated to match the condition. For each new resource, an updated resource, or an existing resource, the effects behave differently.

Anatomy of a policy definition

You use JSON to create a policy definition that contains the elements shown in the following table.

Element

Description

Properties or values

displayName (string, max 128 characters)

Used to identify the policy definition.

description (string, max 512 characters)

Provides context for when the definition is used.

policyType (read-only string)

Indicates the origin of the policy definition. This property can't be set, but SDK returns three values which are visible in the portal.

● Built in: Provided and maintained by Microsoft. ● Custom: Custom definitions created by the customer. ● Static: Regulatory Compliance policy with Microsoft ownership.

mode (string)

Configured depending on the target of the policy: an Azure Resource Manager property or a Resource Provider property.

● Resource Manager Modes: o On All: Evaluates resource groups, subscriptions, and all resource types. o Indexed: Evaluates resource groups, subscriptions, and all resource types. ● Resource Provider Modes (limited to Built in policies and fully supported): o Microsoft.Kubernetes.Data o Microsoft.KeyVault.Data o Microsoft.Network.Data ● Resource Provider Modes (limited to Built in policies and in preview mode): o Microsoft.ManagedHSM.Data o Microsoft.DataFactory.Data

version (string, optional)

Built-in policy definitions can host multiple versions with the same definitionID. If no version number is specified, all experiences show the latest version of the definition.

metadata (object, optional, max 1,024 characters)

Stores information about the policy definition.

Common properties (for Built-in policies): ● version (string) : Tracks details about the version of the contents of a policy definition. ● category (string) : Determines under which category in the Azure portal the policy definition is displayed. ● preview (Boolean) : True or false flag that indicates if the policy definition is in preview. ● deprecated (Boolean) : True or false flag that indicates if the policy definition is deprecated. ● portalReview (string) : Determines if parameters require review in the portal.

parameters (object, optional)

Help simplify your policy management by reducing the number of policy definitions. By including parameters in a policy definition, you can reuse that policy for different scenarios by using different values.

Properties: ● name ● type (String, Array, Object, Boolean, Integer, Float, DateTime) ● metadata (description, displayName, strongType, assignPermissions) ● defaultValue ● allowedValues ● schema

policyRule (object)

The effect of a policy is defined in the policyRule . The policy rule consists of the if and then blocks. ● In the if block, you define one or more conditions that specify when the policy applies. ● In the then block, you define the effect that happens when the if conditions result true.

{

"displayName": "Allowed locations",

"description": "This policy enables you to restrict the locations your organization can specify when deploying resources. Use to enforce your geo-compliance requirements. Excludes resource groups, Microsoft.AzureActiveDirectory/b2cDirectories, and resources that use the 'global' region.",

"policyType": "BuiltIn",

"mode": "Indexed",

"metadata": {

"version": "1.0.0",

"category": "General"

},

"parameters": {

"listOfAllowedLocations": {

"type": "Array",

"metadata": {

"description": "The list of locations that can be specified when deploying resources.",

"strongType": "location",

"displayName": "Allowed locations"

}

},

"policyRule": {

"if": {

"allOf": [

{

"field": "location",

"notIn": "[parameters('listOfAllowedLocations')]"

},

{

"field": "location",

"notEquals": "global"

},

{

"field": "type",

"notEquals": "Microsoft.AzureActiveDirectory/b2cDirectories"

}

]

},

"then": {

"effect": "deny"

}

{

"displayName": "Allowed locations",

"description": "This policy enables you to restrict the locations your organization can specify when deploying resources. Use to enforce your geo-compliance requirements. Excludes resource groups, Microsoft.AzureActiveDirectory/b2cDirectories, and resources that use the 'global' region.",

"policyType": "BuiltIn",

"mode": "Indexed",

"metadata": {

"version": "1.0.0",

"category": "General"

},

"parameters": {

"listOfAllowedLocations": {

"type": "Array",

"metadata": {

"description": "The list of locations that can be specified when deploying resources.",

"strongType": "location",

"displayName": "Allowed locations"

}

},

"policyRule": {

"if": {

"allOf": [

{

"field": "location",

"notIn": "[parameters('listOfAllowedLocations')]"

},

{

"field": "location",

"notEquals": "global"

},

{

"field": "type",

"notEquals": "Microsoft.AzureActiveDirectory/b2cDirectories"

}

]

},

"then": {

"effect": "deny"

}

In the given example, b2cDirectories is excluded from the policy logic because its location field isn't a region (it can be "United States," "Europe," "Asia Pacific," or "Australia"). This logic can be enforced with a separate policy.

Logical operators and conditions ( if blocks)

The first part of the policyRule in an Azure Policy definition is the if block. This block defines the conditions for which the policy evaluates the resources. A policy definition can contain several conditional statements. Depending on your evaluation requirements, you might or might not need each statement to be true, and you might only need some of them to be true.

Logical operators supported in the if block

In the if condition, you can put different logical operators.

Operator

Type

Description

not

{condition or operator}

The not syntax inverts the result of the condition.

allOf

[{condition or operator}, {condition or operator}]

The allOf syntax (like the logical and operation) requires all conditions to be true.

anyOf

[{condition or operator}, {condition or operator}]

The anyOf syntax (like the logical or operation) requires one or more conditions to be true.

The following example shows use of the allOf logical operator:

{

"if": {

"allOf": [

{

"field": "location",

"notIn": "[parameters('listOfAllowedLocations')]"

},

{

"field": "location",

"notEquals": "global"

},

{

"field": "type",

"notEquals": "Microsoft.AzureActiveDirectory/b2cDirectories"

}

]

},

"then": {

"effect": "deny"

}

{

"if": {

"allOf": [

{

"field": "location",

"notIn": "[parameters('listOfAllowedLocations')]"

},

{

"field": "location",

"notEquals": "global"

},

{

"field": "type",

"notEquals": "Microsoft.AzureActiveDirectory/b2cDirectories"

}

]

},

"then": {

"effect": "deny"

}

Nested logical operations

Logical operations are optional and can be nested to create complex scenarios.

The following example shows a not operation nested in an allOf operation:

"if": {

"allOf": [

{

"not": {

"field": "tags",

"containsKey": "application"

}

},

{

"field": "type",

"equals": "Microsoft.Storage/storageAccounts"

}

]

},

"if": {

"allOf": [

{

"not": {

"field": "tags",

"containsKey": "application"

}

},

{

"field": "type",

"equals": "Microsoft.Storage/storageAccounts"

}

]

},

Conditions

Properties like fields, values, or counts can be evaluated within a condition.

Fields

Conditions that evaluate whether the values of properties in the resource request payload meet certain criteria can be formed by using a field expression.

Name, fullName, kind, type, location, ID, identity.type, tags, tags['tagName'], property aliases

Value

Conditions that evaluate whether a value meets certain criteria can be formed by using a value expression.

Count

Conditions that count how many members of an array meet certain criteria can be formed by using a count expression.

● Field count, value count ● The current () function returns the value of the array member that's being evaluated

The condition in an Azure Policy assesses whether the evaluated values for the properties, such as Fields, Value, or Count, meets certain criteria. If the result of a function is an error, the policy results in a deny effect. This result can be avoided while testing by disabling enforcementMode in the assignment. For more information, see Enforcement Mode .

Evaluation criteria

Value type

equals

stringValue

notEquals

stringValue

like

stringValue

notLike

stringValue

match

stringValue

notMatch

stringValue

matchInsensitively

stringValue

notMatchInsensitively

stringValue

contains

stringValue

notContains

stringValue

In

["stringValue1", "stringValue2"]

notIn

["stringValue1", "stringValue2"]

containsKey

keyName

notContainsKey

keyName

less

dateValue

less

stringValue

less

intValue

lessOrEquals

dateValue

lessOrEquals

stringValue

lessOrEquals

intValue

greater

dateValue

greater

stringValue

greater

intValue

greaterOrEquals

dateValue

greaterOrEquals

stringValue

greaterOrEquals

intValue

exists

bool

The following JSON is an example of using conditions:

{

"if": {

"allOf": [

{

"value": "[resourceGroup().name]",

"like": "*netrq"

},

{

"field": "type",

"notLike": "Network/*"

}

]

},

"then": {

"effect": "deny",

"details": {

"count": {

"field": "Microsoft.Network/virtualNetworks/addressSpace.addressPrefixes[*]",

"where": {

"value": "[ipRangeContains('10.0.0.0/24', current('Microsoft.Network/virtualNetworks/addressSpace.addressPrefixes[*]'))]",

"equals": "greater"

}

{

"if": {

"allOf": [

{

"value": "[resourceGroup().name]",

"like": "*netrq"

},

{

"field": "type",

"notLike": "Network/*"

}

]

},

"then": {

"effect": "deny",

"details": {

"count": {

"field": "Microsoft.Network/virtualNetworks/addressSpace.addressPrefixes[*]",

"where": {

"value": "[ipRangeContains('10.0.0.0/24', current('Microsoft.Network/virtualNetworks/addressSpace.addressPrefixes[*]'))]",

"equals": "greater"

}

Policy functions

Functions can be used to introduce extra logic into a policy rule. They're resolved in the policy rule of a policy definition and in the parameter values that are assigned to the policy definitions in an initiative.

The Resource Manager template functions are available to use in a policy rule except a few policy functions and user-defined functions .

The utcNow() function is available to use in a policy rule but differs from use in an Azure Resource Manager template (ARM template). Unlike an ARM template, this function can be used outside defaultValue . It returns a string set to the current date and time in Universal ISO 8601 DateTime format yyyy-MM-ddTHH:mm:ss.fffffffZ .

yyyy-MM-ddTHH:mm:ss.fffffffZ

The following table describes the functions that are only available in policy rules.

Function

Description

addDays(dateTime, numberOfDaysToAdd)

● dateTime : [Required] string - String in the Universal ISO 8601 DateTime format 'yyyy-MM-ddTHH:mm:ss.FFFFFFFZ'. ● numberOfDaysToAdd : [Required] integer - Number of days to add.

dateTime

numberOfDaysToAdd

Field(fieldName)

● fieldName : [Required] string - Name of the field to retrieve. ● Returns the value of that field from the resource evaluated by the If condition. ● field is primarily used with auditIfNotExists and deployIfNotExists to reference fields on the resource that are being evaluated.

fieldName

field

auditIfNotExists

deployIfNotExists

requestContext().apiVersion

Returns the API version of the request that triggered policy evaluation. This value is the API version that was used in the PUT/PATCH request for evaluations on resource creation/update. The latest API version is always used during compliance evaluation on existing resources.

policy()

Returns the following information about the policy that's being evaluated. Properties can be accessed from the returned object. "assignmentId": "" , "definitionId": "" , "setDefinitionId": "" , "definitionReferenceId": ""

"assignmentId": ""

"definitionId": ""

"setDefinitionId": ""

"definitionReferenceId": ""

ipRangeContains(range, targetRange)

● range : [Required] string - String specifying a range of IP addresses to check if the targetRange is within range. ● targetRange : [Required] string - String specifying a range of IP addresses to validate as included within the range . Returns a boolean for whether the range IP address range contains the targetRange IP address range. Empty ranges or mixing between IP families isn't allowed and results in evaluation failure.

range

targetRange

current(indexName)

Special function that can only be used inside count expressions.

Effect types ( then blocks)

The second part of the policyRule in an Azure Policy definition is the then block. This block defines the effect that takes place when the policy rule is evaluated to match the condition resources. More than one effect can be valid for a given policy definition. Parameters are often used to specify allowed effect values ( allowedValues ) in such cases so that a single definition can be more versatile during assignment. Resource properties and logic in the policy rule can determine whether a certain effect is considered valid to the policy definition.

Effect

Description

Type

disabled

The disabled effect is a way to deactivate the policy. If a policy definition has Disabled as its effect, any assignments of that policy aren't active. This effect is checked first to determine if the policy rule should be evaluated. This flexibility makes it possible to deactivate a single assignment instead of deactivating all of that policy's assignments.

Synchronous evaluation

append

The append effect is used to add more fields to the requested resource during creation or update. It's mostly obsolete because Modify can also be used to add fields to the request.

Synchronous evaluation

modify

The modify effect is used to add, update, or remove properties or tags on a subscription or resource during creation or update. It allows Azure Policy to modify requests to Azure Resource Manager by altering fields to ensure compliance.

Synchronous evaluation

deny

The deny effect is used to prevent a resource request that doesn't match defined standards through a policy definition and fails the request.

Synchronous evaluation

denyAction

The denyAction effect is used to block requests based on intended action to resources at scale. Currently, the only supported action is DELETE.

Synchronous evaluation

audit

The audit effect is used to create a warning event in the activity log when you're evaluating a noncompliant resource, but it doesn't stop the request.

Asynchronous evaluation

auditIfNotExists

The auditIfNotExists effect allows the auditing of resources that are related to the resource that matches the if condition but doesn't have the properties specified in the details of the then condition.

Asynchronous evaluation

deployIfNotExists

The deployIfNotExists policy definition runs a template deployment when the condition is met. It can trigger deployment of a related resource based on the compliance state of the currently evaluated resource.

Asynchronous evaluation

manual

The manual effect allows you to self-attest the compliance of resources or scopes. When a policy definition with Manual effect is assigned, you can set the compliance states of targeted resources or scopes through custom attestations.

Manual attestation

The following list provides general guidance around interchangeable effects:

- audit , deny , and either modify or append are often interchangeable.

- auditIfNotExists and deployIfNotExists are often interchangeable.

- manual isn't interchangeable.

- disabled is interchangeable with any effect.

Multiple policies can be assigned to a single resource at the same scope or at different scopes. Each policy mostly has a different effect defined. The condition and effect for each policy is independently evaluated. The net result of layering policy definitions is considered cumulative most restrictive .

Unit 2.4.6 - Evaluation of resources through Azure Policy

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/sovereignty-policy-initiatives/azure-policies-evaluation-resources

Evaluation of resources through Azure Policy

A significant benefit of Azure Policy is the insight and controls that it provides over resources in a subscription or management group of subscriptions. This control can be used to prevent resources from being created in the wrong location, enforce common and consistent tag usage, or audit existing resources for appropriate configurations and settings. Before you review compliance data and react to it, you need to understand the evaluation triggers, timings, and the resource compliance states.

Evaluation triggers

Evaluations of assigned policies and initiatives happen as the result of various events:

- A policy or initiative is newly assigned to a scope

- A policy or initiative already assigned to a scope is updated

- A resource is deployed to or updated in a scope with an assignment through Azure Resource Manager, REST API, or a supported SDK

- A subscription (resource type Microsoft.Resources/subscriptions) is created or moved in a management group hierarchy with an assigned policy definition that targets the subscription resource type

- A policy exemption is created, updated, or deleted

- Standard compliance evaluation cycle

- The machine configuration resource provider is updated with compliance details by a managed resource

- On-demand scan

For more information, see Evaluation triggers .

Evaluation timing

When you're working with policy assignments in Azure, you need to understand the behavior and timing of compliance scans, especially in Brownfield scenarios, where new policies are applied to existing resources. Compliance scans through Azure policies are triggered by various methods:

- Automatic full scan - A full compliance scan is triggered automatically every 24 hours.

- Manual scan for Brownfield scenarios - In cases where a new policy is applied to existing resources (Brownfield scenarios), you can manually trigger a compliance scan by running az policy state trigger-scan .

When you assign a new policy, a delay can occur in the policy taking effect, which can be up to 30 minutes. The Azure Resource Manager cache holds session data, and it can take time for the policy to propagate in the same session. To bypass the caching delay, you can sign out and sign back in to refresh the Azure Resource Manager cache, which ensures that the new policy is applied immediately to the defined scope.

After the scan starts, several factors influence how long it takes for a compliance scan to complete:

- Policy definitions - The size and complexity of the policy definitions can increase scan time.

- Number of policies - The more policies applied, the longer the scan might take.

- Scope size - The size of the resource scope assigned to the policy also plays a role.

- System load - Compliance scans are a low-priority operation, meaning that if the system is busy with more critical tasks, the scan might take longer. The system prioritizes interactive and high-importance operations, so scans might take several minutes, or tens of minutes, even in smaller environments.

- Synchronous scan (Low-Priority Execution) - Because compliance scans are synchronous and assigned a low priority in Azure's system, they're delayed if the system is busy. This scan can significantly extend the time it takes for the scan to complete, even for smaller scopes or policies.

This understanding of the compliance scan process and potential delays allows you to better manage the application and avoid unnecessary waiting, especially in environments with complex or extensive policy definitions.

Resource compliance states

When initiative or policy definitions are assigned, Azure Policy determines which resources are applicable. Then, it evaluates those resources that aren't excluded or exempted. Evaluation provides one of the compliance states to each resource based on conditions in the policy rule and each resource's adherence to those requirements.

- Non-compliant

- Compliant

- Error (for template or evaluation error)

- Conflicting (two or more policy assignments in the same scope with contradicting rules, such as two policies appending the same tag with different values)

- Protected (resource covered under an assignment with a denyAction effect)

- Exempted Unknown (default state for definitions with a manual effect)

When multiple resources or policies have varying compliance states, the overall compliance state is assessed individually for each resource and for each policy assignment. Azure Policy ranks each compliance state so that one wins over another in this situation. The rank order of the states is as given in the previous list of compliance states.

The compliance percentage is determined by dividing Compliant , Exempt , and Unknown resources by total resources. Total resources include resources with Compliant , Non-compliant , Unknown , Exempt , Conflicting , and Error states.

For more information on when the policies return these states for any particular resource, see Azure Policy compliance states .

Enforcement Mode

enforcementMode is a property of a policy assignment that lets you deactivate the enforcement of certain policy effects. This mode allows you to test the policy's outcome on existing resources without initiating the policy effect or triggering entries in the Azure Activity log . The enforcementMode can be changed to Enabled after the policy is thoroughly tested.

This scenario is commonly referred to as What If and aligns to safe deployment practices. The enforcementMode is different from the disabled effect. The disabled effect prevents resource evaluation from happening at all while enforcementMode lets the evaluation happen without the effect taking place.

The following table describes this property's values.

Mode

JSON value

Type

Remediate manually

Activity log entry

Description

Enabled

Default

string

Yes

The policy effect is enforced during resource creation or update.

Disabled

DoNotEnforce

string

Yes

No

The policy effect isn't enforced during resource creation or update.

If enforcementMode isn't specified in a policy or initiative definition, the value Default is used. Remediation tasks can be started for deployIfNotExists policies, even when enforcementMode is set to DoNotEnforce .

Policy enforcement and safe deployment best practices

Without the appropriate knowledge of best practices and proper testing, applying a set of policy to an existing environment that's running production workloads can result in unintended behaviors of policy resources. Treating policy as code (keeping your policy definitions in source control, and whenever a change is made, testing and validating that change) allows you to automate testing and make sure that no manual error factor happens. The best practices framework focuses on minimizing the impact of policy changes while ensuring compliance, and it includes two aspects:

- First aspect - Start from Assignments of new policies with enforcementMode Disabled. When assigning policies that include deny or modify actions, beginning with enforcementMode Disabled allows you to view the compliance state and evaluate policy outcomes without triggering actions or denying operations. This "what-if" scenario minimizes impact and helps identify issues in the new policies or changes without disrupting the environment.

First aspect - Start from Assignments of new policies with enforcementMode Disabled. When assigning policies that include deny or modify actions, beginning with enforcementMode Disabled allows you to view the compliance state and evaluate policy outcomes without triggering actions or denying operations. This "what-if" scenario minimizes impact and helps identify issues in the new policies or changes without disrupting the environment.

- Second aspect - Deploy policies in deployment rings. To control potential negative impacts, policies should be deployed gradually in smaller subsets and then in bigger sets. You can start with test and development environments and then move to production by applying the policy to a small subset first. This strategy helps in testing the policy thoroughly. Gradually expanding the scope (through deployment rings) can cover the full production environment.

Second aspect - Deploy policies in deployment rings. To control potential negative impacts, policies should be deployed gradually in smaller subsets and then in bigger sets. You can start with test and development environments and then move to production by applying the policy to a small subset first. This strategy helps in testing the policy thoroughly. Gradually expanding the scope (through deployment rings) can cover the full production environment.

The following diagram shows how to apply the safe deployment best practices framework for Azure Policy assignments.

The following steps correspond with the outlined steps in the preceding screenshot:

- Create definition - Begin by defining the policy definition with the scope as root (tenant).

Create definition - Begin by defining the policy definition with the scope as root (tenant).

- Create assignment - Define deployment rings (1 to 5) by using resource selectors. Assign the policy to a specific scope (such as a resource group, subscription, or management group) in Ring 5. Assign with enforcementMode Disabled to evaluate compliance without enforcing changes.

Create assignment - Define deployment rings (1 to 5) by using resource selectors. Assign the policy to a specific scope (such as a resource group, subscription, or management group) in Ring 5. Assign with enforcementMode Disabled to evaluate compliance without enforcing changes.

- a) Compliance check - Verify that the policy is being applied correctly and that the desired compliance state is achieved for the resources in Ring 5. b) Application health check - Assess the impact of the policy for the resources in Ring 5. Ensure that no unexpected side effects exist.

a) Compliance check - Verify that the policy is being applied correctly and that the desired compliance state is achieved for the resources in Ring 5.

b) Application health check - Assess the impact of the policy for the resources in Ring 5. Ensure that no unexpected side effects exist.

- Repeat for each ring (Non-production) - Repeat step 3 for all nonproduction environment rings.

Repeat for each ring (Non-production) - Repeat step 3 for all nonproduction environment rings.

- Update assignment (Optional) - If necessary, adjust the policy definition or assignment based on the evaluation of resources of the nonproduction environment and then reassign it to the resources in Ring 5 with the enforcementMode Enabled.

Update assignment (Optional) - If necessary, adjust the policy definition or assignment based on the evaluation of resources of the nonproduction environment and then reassign it to the resources in Ring 5 with the enforcementMode Enabled.

- a) Compliance check - Reevaluate compliance after making changes (same as step 3a). b) Application health check - Again, verify that the policy isn't causing issues (same as step 3b).

a) Compliance check - Reevaluate compliance after making changes (same as step 3a).

b) Application health check - Again, verify that the policy isn't causing issues (same as step 3b).

- Repeat for each ring (Non-production) - Repeat step 6 for all nonproduction environment rings.

Repeat for each ring (Non-production) - Repeat step 6 for all nonproduction environment rings.

- Repeat for production rings - After the policy is validated in a nonproduction environment, gradually deploy it to production environments, starting with a smaller subset (ring) and expanding the scope over time.

Repeat for production rings - After the policy is validated in a nonproduction environment, gradually deploy it to production environments, starting with a smaller subset (ring) and expanding the scope over time.

For more detailed steps on the safe deployment of Azure Policy assignments with different effects, see Safe deployment of Azure Policy assignments .

Reacting to policy state changes

Azure Policy events allow applications to react to state changes. This integration is done without the need for complicated code or expensive and inefficient polling services. Events from Azure Policy (Event Source) are pushed through Microsoft Azure Event Grid to Event Handlers.

Azure Event Grid provides reliable delivery services to your applications through rich retry policies and dead-letter delivery. Event Grid takes care of the proper routing, filtering, and multicasting of the events to destinations through Event Grid subscriptions. For more information, see Azure Event Grid .

An Event Handler is the place where the event is sent. Several services, such as Microsoft Azure Functions, Microsoft Azure Logic Apps, or your own custom HTTP listener, can be configured to handle events. You can also use any webhook for handling events.

For more information, see Event handlers in Azure Event Grid , Reacting to Azure Policy state change events , and the Route policy state change events to Event Grid with Azure CLI tutorial.

Unit 2.4.7 - Check your knowledge

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/sovereignty-policy-initiatives/check

Check your knowledge

Answer the following questions to see what you learned

Unit 2.4.8 - Summary

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/sovereignty-policy-initiatives/summary

Summary

Azure Policy is a crucial component of the governance model in the Cloud Adoption Framework for Azure, which is designed to balance control and stability with speed and results. It helps you enforce organizational and regulatory standards and assess compliance at scale through built-in and custom policies and policy initiatives.

The module covered the hierarchical organization of Azure resources, policy operations in Greenfield and Brownfield scenarios, and the various components of policy definitions. You also delved into the evaluation and effects of policies, safe deployment practices, and integration with Event Grid for automated actions based on policy state changes. Key points included:

- Importance of careful policy design

- Testing to ensure effective governance without disrupting operations

- Logical operators and conditions in policy evaluation

- Supported effect types such as disabled , modify , deny , audit , deployIfNotExists , and manual

Additionally, the module emphasized starting with enforcementMode deactivated for new policies to test their impact and then deploying policies in rings to gradually expand to production environments.

For more information, see the Azure Policy documentation.

LP 2 M5 - Secure your Azure resources with Azure role-based access control (Azure RBAC)

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/secure-azure-resources-with-rbac/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 2.5.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/secure-azure-resources-with-rbac/1-introduction

Introduction

For any organization using the cloud, securing your Azure resources such as virtual machines, websites, networks, and storage is a critical function. You want to ensure that your data and assets are protected, but still grant your employees and partners the access they need to perform their jobs. Azure RBAC is an authorization system in Azure that helps you manage who has access to Azure resources, what they can do with those resources, and where they have access.

Suppose you work for First Up Consultants, which is an engineering firm that specializes in circuit and electrical design. They've moved their workloads and assets to Azure to make collaboration easier across several offices and other companies. You work in the IT department at First Up Consultants. You're responsible for keeping the company's assets secure, but still allowing users to access the resources they need. You've heard that Azure RBAC can help you manage resources in Azure.

In this module, you'll learn how to use Azure RBAC to manage access to resources in Azure.

Learning objectives

In this module, you'll:

- Verify access to resources for yourself and others.

- Grant access to resources.

- View activity logs of Azure RBAC changes.

Unit 2.5.2 - What is Azure RBAC?

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/secure-azure-resources-with-rbac/2-rbac-overview

What is Azure RBAC?

When it comes to identity and access, most organizations that are considering using the public cloud are concerned about two things:

- Ensuring that when people leave the organization, they lose access to resources in the cloud.

- Striking the right balance between autonomy and central governance. For example, giving project teams the ability to create and manage virtual machines in the cloud, while centrally controlling the networks those VMs use to communicate with other resources.

Microsoft Entra ID and Azure RBAC work together to make it simple to carry out these goals.

Azure subscriptions

First, remember that each Azure subscription is associated with a single Microsoft Entra directory. Users, groups, and applications in that directory can manage resources in the Azure subscription. The subscriptions use Microsoft Entra ID for single sign-on (SSO) and access management. You can extend your on-premises Active Directory to the cloud by using Microsoft Entra Connect . This feature allows your employees to manage their Azure subscriptions by using their existing work identities. When you disable an on-premises Active Directory account, it automatically loses access to all Azure subscriptions connected with Microsoft Entra ID.

What's Azure RBAC?

Azure RBAC is an authorization system built on Azure Resource Manager that provides fine-grained access management for resources in Azure. With Azure RBAC, you can grant the exact access that users need to do their jobs. For example, you can use Azure RBAC to let one employee manage virtual machines in a subscription, while another manages SQL databases within the same subscription.

The following video describes Azure RBAC in detail:

You can grant access by assigning the appropriate Azure role to users, groups, and applications at a certain scope. The scope of a role assignment can be a management group, subscription, a resource group, or a single resource. A role assigned at a parent scope also grants access to the child scopes contained within it. For example, a user with access to a resource group can manage all the resources it contains like websites, virtual machines, and subnets. The Azure role that you assign dictates what resources the user, group, or application can manage within that scope.

The following diagram depicts how the classic subscription administrator roles, Azure roles, and Microsoft Entra roles are related at a high level. Child scopes, such as service instances, inherit roles assigned at a higher scope, like an entire subscription.

In the preceding diagram, a subscription is associated with only one Microsoft Entra tenant. Also note that a resource group can have multiple resources, but it's associated with only one subscription. Although it's not obvious from the diagram, a resource can be bound to only one resource group.

What can I do with Azure RBAC?

Azure RBAC allows you to grant access to Azure resources that you control. Suppose you need to manage access to resources in Azure for the development, engineering, and marketing teams. You’ve started to receive access requests, and you need to quickly learn how access management works for Azure resources.

Here are some scenarios you can implement with Azure RBAC:

- Allow one user to manage virtual machines in a subscription and another user to manage virtual networks.

- Allow a database administrator group to manage SQL databases in a subscription.

- Allow a user to manage all resources in a resource group, such as virtual machines, websites, and subnets.

- Allow an application to access all resources in a resource group.

Azure RBAC in the Azure portal

In several areas in the Azure portal, you'll see a pane named Access control (IAM) , also known as identity and access management . On this pane, you can see who has access to that area and their role. Using this same pane, you can grant or remove access.

The following shows an example of the Access control (IAM) pane for a resource group. In this example, Alain has been assigned the Backup Operator role for this resource group.

How does Azure RBAC work?

You can control access to resources using Azure RBAC by creating role assignments, which control how permissions are enforced. To create a role assignment, you need three elements: a security principal, a role definition, and a scope. You can think of these elements as who , what , and where .

1. Security principal (who)

A security principal is just a fancy name for a user, group, or application to which you want to grant access.

2. Role definition (what)

A role definition is a collection of permissions. It's sometimes just called a role. A role definition lists the permissions the role can perform such as read, write, and delete. Roles can be high-level, like Owner, or specific, like Virtual Machine Contributor.

Azure includes several built-in roles that you can use. The following lists four fundamental built-in roles:

- Owner : Has full access to all resources, including the right to delegate access to others.

- Contributor : Can create and manage all types of Azure resources, but can’t grant access to others.

- Reader : Can view existing Azure resources.

- User Access Administrator : Lets you manage user access to Azure resources.

If the built-in roles don't meet the specific needs of your organization, you can create your own custom roles.

3. Scope (where)

Scope is the level where the access applies. This is helpful if you want to make someone a Website Contributor but only for one resource group.

In Azure, you can specify a scope at multiple levels: management group, subscription, resource group, or resource. Scopes are structured in a parent-child relationship. When you grant access at a parent scope, the child scopes automatically inherit those permissions. For example, if a group is assigned the Contributor role at the subscription scope, it will inherit the role for all resource groups and resources within the subscription.

Role assignment

Once you have determined the who, what, and where, you can combine those elements to grant access. A role assignment is the process of binding a role to a security principal at a particular scope for the purpose of granting access. To grant access, you'll create a role assignment. To revoke access, you'll remove a role assignment.

The following example shows how the Marketing group has been assigned the Contributor role at the sales resource group scope.

Azure RBAC is an allow model

Azure RBAC is an allow model. This means that when you're assigned a role, Azure RBAC allows you to perform certain actions such as read, write, or delete. If one role assignment grants you read permissions to a resource group, and a different role assignment grants you write permissions to the same resource group, then you'll have read and write permissions on that resource group.

Azure RBAC has something called NotActions permissions. You can use NotActions to create a set of not allowed permissions. The access a role grants—the effective permissions —is computed by subtracting the NotActions operations from the Actions operations. For example, the Contributor role has both Actions and NotActions . The wildcard (*) in Actions indicates that it can perform all operations on the control plane. You'd then subtract the following operations in NotActions to compute the effective permissions:

NotActions

Actions

NotActions

Actions

NotActions

- Delete roles and role assignments

- Create roles and role assignments

- Grant the caller User Access Administrator access at the tenant scope

- Create or update any blueprint artifacts

- Delete any blueprint artifacts

Unit 2.5.3 - Knowledge check - What is Azure RBAC?

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/secure-azure-resources-with-rbac/3-knowledge-check-rbac-overview

Knowledge check - What is Azure RBAC?

Check your knowledge

Unit 2.5.4 - Exercise - List access using Azure RBAC and the Azure portal

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/secure-azure-resources-with-rbac/4-list-access

Exercise - List access using Azure RBAC and the Azure portal

At First Up Consultants, you've been granted access to a resource group for the marketing team. You want to familiarize yourself with the Azure portal and see what roles are currently assigned.

You need an Azure subscription to complete the exercises. If you don't have an Azure subscription, create a free account and add a subscription before you begin. If you're a student, you can take advantage of the Azure for students offer.

List role assignments for yourself

Follow these steps to see what roles are currently assigned to you.

- Sign in to the Azure portal .

Sign in to the Azure portal .

- On the Profile menu, select the ellipsis ( ... ) to see more links.

On the Profile menu, select the ellipsis ( ... ) to see more links.

- Select My permissions to open the My permissions pane. You'll find the roles that you've been assigned and the scope. Your list will look different.

Select My permissions to open the My permissions pane.

You'll find the roles that you've been assigned and the scope. Your list will look different.

List role assignments for a resource group

Follow these steps to see what roles are assigned at the resource group scope.

- In the Search box at the top, search for and select Resource groups .

In the Search box at the top, search for and select Resource groups .

- In the list of resource groups, select a resource group. These steps use a resource group named example-group , but your resource group's name will be different.

In the list of resource groups, select a resource group.

These steps use a resource group named example-group , but your resource group's name will be different.

- On the left menu pane, select Access control (IAM) .

On the left menu pane, select Access control (IAM) .

- Select the Role assignments tab. This tab shows who has access to the resource group. Notice that some roles are scoped to This resource , while others are (Inherited) from a parent scope.

Select the Role assignments tab.

This tab shows who has access to the resource group. Notice that some roles are scoped to This resource , while others are (Inherited) from a parent scope.

List roles

As you learned in the previous unit, a role is a collection of permissions. Azure has more than 70 built-in roles that you can use in your role assignments. To list the roles:

- In the menu bar at the top of the pane, select the Roles tab to list of all the built-in and custom roles. Select a role's View link in the Details column, then select the Assignments tab to display the number of users and groups assigned to that role.

In the menu bar at the top of the pane, select the Roles tab to list of all the built-in and custom roles.

Select a role's View link in the Details column, then select the Assignments tab to display the number of users and groups assigned to that role.

In this unit, you learned how to list the role assignments for yourself in the Azure portal. You also learned how to list the role assignments for a resource group.

Unit 2.5.5 - Exercise - Grant access using Azure RBAC and the Azure portal

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/secure-azure-resources-with-rbac/5-grant-access

Exercise - Grant access using Azure RBAC and the Azure portal

A coworker named Alain at First Up Consultants needs permission to create and manage virtual machines for a project on which they're working. Your manager has asked that you handle this request. Using the best practice to grant users the least privileges to get their work done, you decide to assign Alain the Virtual Machine Contributor role for a resource group.

Grant access

Follow this procedure to assign the Virtual Machine Contributor role to a user at the resource group scope.

- Sign in to the Azure portal as an administrator that has permissions to assign roles, such as User Access Administrator or Owner .

Sign in to the Azure portal as an administrator that has permissions to assign roles, such as User Access Administrator or Owner .

- In the Search box at the top, search for Resource groups .

In the Search box at the top, search for Resource groups .

- In the list of resource groups, select a resource group. These steps use a resource group named example-group , but your resource group's name will be different.

In the list of resource groups, select a resource group.

These steps use a resource group named example-group , but your resource group's name will be different.

- On the left menu pane, select Access control (IAM) .

On the left menu pane, select Access control (IAM) .

- Select the Role assignments tab to display the current list of role assignments at this scope.

Select the Role assignments tab to display the current list of role assignments at this scope.

- Select Add > Add role assignment . If you don't have permissions to assign roles, the Add role assignment option will be disabled. The Add role assignment page opens.

Select Add > Add role assignment .

If you don't have permissions to assign roles, the Add role assignment option will be disabled.

The Add role assignment page opens.

- On the Role tab, search for and select Virtual Machine Contributor .

On the Role tab, search for and select Virtual Machine Contributor .

- Select Next .

Select Next .

- On the Members tab, select Select members .

On the Members tab, select Select members .

- Search for and select a user.

Search for and select a user.

- Select Select to add the user to the Members list.

Select Select to add the user to the Members list.

- Select Next .

Select Next .

- On the Review + assign tab, review the role assignment settings.

On the Review + assign tab, review the role assignment settings.

- Select Review + assign to assign the role. After a few moments, the user is assigned the Virtual Machine Contributor role at the resource group scope. The user can now create and manage virtual machines just within this resource group.

Select Review + assign to assign the role.

After a few moments, the user is assigned the Virtual Machine Contributor role at the resource group scope. The user can now create and manage virtual machines just within this resource group.

Remove access

In Azure RBAC, you can remove a role assignment to remove access.

- In the list of role assignments, select View Assignments .

In the list of role assignments, select View Assignments .

- Search for and check the box for the user with the Virtual Machine Contributor role.

Search for and check the box for the user with the Virtual Machine Contributor role.

- Select Delete .

Select Delete .

- In the Remove role assignments message that appears, select Yes .

In the Remove role assignments message that appears, select Yes .

In this unit, you learned how to grant a user access to create and manage virtual machines in a resource group using the Azure portal.

Unit 2.5.6 - Exercise - View activity logs for Azure RBAC changes

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/secure-azure-resources-with-rbac/6-view-activity-logs

Exercise - View activity logs for Azure RBAC changes

First Up Consultants reviews Azure RBAC changes quarterly for auditing and troubleshooting purposes. You know that changes get logged in the Azure Activity Log . Your manager has asked if you can generate a report of the role assignment and custom role changes for the last month.

View activity logs

The easiest way to get started is to view the activity logs with the Azure portal.

- Select All services , then search for Activity log .

Select All services , then search for Activity log .

- Select Activity log to open the activity log.

Select Activity log to open the activity log.

- Set the Timespan filter to Last month .

Set the Timespan filter to Last month .

- Add an Operation filter and type role to filter the list.

Add an Operation filter and type role to filter the list.

- Select the following Azure RBAC operations: Create role assignment (roleAssignments) Delete role assignment (roleAssignments) Create or update custom role definition (roleDefinitions) Delete custom role definition (roleDefinitions) After a moment, you'll get a list of all the role assignment and role definition operations for the last month. There's also a button at the top of the screen to download the activity log as a CSV file.

Select the following Azure RBAC operations:

- Create role assignment (roleAssignments)

- Delete role assignment (roleAssignments)

- Create or update custom role definition (roleDefinitions)

- Delete custom role definition (roleDefinitions)

After a moment, you'll get a list of all the role assignment and role definition operations for the last month. There's also a button at the top of the screen to download the activity log as a CSV file.

- Select one of the operations to get the activity log details.

Select one of the operations to get the activity log details.

In this unit, you learned how to use Azure Activity Log to list Azure RBAC changes in the portal and generate a simple report.

Unit 2.5.7 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/secure-azure-resources-with-rbac/7-knowledge-check-rbac

Module assessment

Check your knowledge

Unit 2.5.8 - Summary

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/secure-azure-resources-with-rbac/8-summary

Summary

In this module, you learned about Azure RBAC, and how you can use it to secure your Azure resources. To grant access, you assign users a role at a particular scope. Using Azure RBAC, you can grant only the amount of access to users that they need to perform their jobs.

Azure RBAC has more than 200 built-in roles. However, if your organization needs specific permissions, you can create your own custom roles. Azure keeps track of your Azure RBAC changes in case you need to see what changes were made in the past.

Further reading

To continue learning about Azure RBAC, check out What is Azure role-based access control (Azure RBAC)? .

LP 2 M6 - Allow users to reset their password with Microsoft Entra self-service password reset

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/allow-users-reset-their-password/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 2.6.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/allow-users-reset-their-password/1-introduction

Introduction

Suppose you're an IT administrator for a large retail organization. Your organization starts using Microsoft Entra ID to allow employees to securely sign in and use software as a service (SaaS) apps. It also allows access to the organization's resources in Microsoft 365. You're overwhelmed with password-reset requests because you currently reset employees' passwords manually. To get these employees back to being productive quickly and reduce your workload, you decide to evaluate and set up self-service password reset in Microsoft Entra ID.

In this module, you learn how Azure supports this feature and how to set it up. Only paid subscriptions can leverage this, while free and pay-as-you-go can't.

By the end of this module, you'll be able to configure self-service password reset in Microsoft Entra ID.

Learning objectives

In this module, you:

- Decide whether to implement self-service password reset.

- Implement self-service password reset to meet your requirements.

- Configure self-service password reset to customize the experience.

Prerequisites

- Basic understanding of Microsoft Entra ID

- A working Microsoft Entra tenant with a subscription package that includes Microsoft Entra ID P1

- An account with at least the Authentication Policy Administrator role

Unit 2.6.2 - What is self-service password reset in Microsoft Entra ID?

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/allow-users-reset-their-password/2-self-service-password-reset

What is self-service password reset in Microsoft Entra ID?

You've been asked to assess ways to reduce help-desk costs in your retail organization. You've noticed that the support staff spends a lot of their time resetting passwords for users. Users often complain about delays with this process, and these delays impact their productivity. You want to understand how you can configure Azure to allow users to manage their own passwords.

In this unit, you'll learn how self-service password reset (SSPR) works in Microsoft Entra ID.

Why use SSPR?

In Microsoft Entra ID, any user can change their password if they're already signed in. But if they're not signed in, forgot their password, or it's expired, they'll need to reset their password. With SSPR, users can reset their passwords in a web browser or from a Windows sign-in screen to regain access to Azure, Microsoft 365, and any other application that uses Microsoft Entra ID for authentication.

SSPR reduces the load on administrators because users can fix password problems themselves without having to call the help desk. Also, it minimizes the productivity impact of a forgotten or expired password. Users don't have to wait until an administrator is available to reset their password.

How SSPR works

The user initiates a password reset either by going directly to the password-reset portal, or by selecting the Can't access your account link on a sign-in page. The reset portal takes these steps:

- Localization : The portal checks the browser's locale setting and renders the SSPR page in the appropriate language.

- Verification : The user enters their username and passes a CAPTCHA to ensure that it's a user and not a bot.

- Authentication : The user enters the required data to authenticate their identity. They might enter a code or answer security questions.

- Password reset : If the user passes the authentication tests, they can enter a new password and confirm it.

- Notification : A message is sent to the user to confirm the reset.

There are several ways you can customize the SSPR user experience. For example, you can add your company logo to the sign-in page so users know they're in the right place to reset their password.

Authenticate a password reset

It's critical to verify a user's identity before you allow a password reset. Malicious users might exploit any weakness in the system to impersonate that user. Azure supports six different ways to authenticate reset requests.

As an administrator, you can choose the methods to use when you configure SSPR. Enable two or more of these methods so that users can choose the ones they can easily use. The methods are:

Authentication method

How to register

How to authenticate for a password reset

Mobile app notification

Install the Microsoft Authenticator app on your mobile device, then register it on the multifactor authentication setup page.

Azure sends a notification to the app, which you can either verify or deny.

Mobile app code

This method also uses the Authenticator app, and you install and register it in the same way.

Enter the code from the app.

Email

Provide an email address that's external to Azure and Microsoft 365.

Azure sends a code to the address, which you enter in the reset wizard.

Mobile phone

Provide a mobile phone number.

Azure sends a code to the phone in an SMS message, which you enter in the reset wizard. You can also choose to get an automated call.

Office phone

Provide a nonmobile phone number.

You receive an automated call to this number and press #.

Security questions

Select questions such as "In what city was your mother born?" and save their responses.

Answer the questions.

In trial Microsoft Entra organizations, phone call options aren't supported.

Require the minimum number of authentication methods

You can specify the minimum number of methods that the user must set up, either one or two. For example, you might enable the mobile app code, email, office phone, and security questions methods and specify a minimum of two methods. Users can then choose the two methods they prefer, like mobile app code and email.

For the security-question method, you can specify a minimum number of questions the user must set up to register for this method. You also can specify a minimum number of questions they must answer correctly to reset their password.

After your users register the required information for the minimum number of methods you've specified, they're considered registered for SSPR.

Recommendations

- Enable two or more of the authentication reset request methods.

- Use the mobile app notification or code as the primary method. But also enable the email or office phone methods to support users without mobile devices.

- The mobile phone method isn't a recommended method, because it's possible to send fraudulent SMS messages.

- The security-question option is the least recommended method, because the answers to the security questions might be known to other people. Only use the security-question method in combination with at least one other method.

Accounts associated with administrator roles

- A strong, two-method authentication policy is always applied to accounts with an administrator role, regardless of your configuration for other users.

- The security-question method isn't available to accounts associated with an administrator role.

Configure notifications

Administrators can choose how users are notified of password changes. There are two options you can enable:

- Notify users on password resets : The user who resets their own password is notified to their primary and secondary email addresses. If the reset was done by a malicious user, this notification alerts the user, who can take mitigation steps.

- Notify all admins when other admins reset their password : All administrators are notified when another administrator resets their password.

License requirements

There are two editions of Microsoft Entra ID, Premium P1 and Premium P2. The password-reset functionality you can use depends on your edition.

Any user who is signed in can change their password, regardless of the edition of Microsoft Entra ID.

What if you're not signed in, and you've forgotten your password or your password has expired? In this case, you can use SSPR in Microsoft Entra ID P1 or P2. It's also available with Microsoft 365 Apps for business or Microsoft 365.

In a hybrid situation, where you have Active Directory on-premises and Microsoft Entra ID in the cloud, any password change in the cloud must be written back to the on-premises directory. This writeback support is available in Microsoft Entra ID P1 or P2. It's also available with Microsoft 365 Apps for business.

SSPR deployment options

You can deploy SSPR with password writeback by using Microsoft Entra Connect or cloud sync , depending on user needs. You can deploy each option side-by-side in different domains to target different sets of users. This helps existing users on-premises to write back password changes, while adding an option for users in disconnected domains because of a company merger or split. Users from an existing on-premises domain can use Microsoft Entra Connect, while new users from a merger can use cloud sync in another domain.

Cloud sync can also provide higher availability, because it doesn't rely on a single instance of Microsoft Entra Connect. For a feature comparison between the two deployment options, see Comparison between Microsoft Entra Connect and cloud sync .

Check your knowledge

Unit 2.6.3 - Implement Microsoft Entra self-service password reset

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/allow-users-reset-their-password/3-implement-azure-ad-self-service-password-reset

Implement Microsoft Entra self-service password reset

You've decided to implement self-service password reset (SSPR) in Microsoft Entra ID for your organization. You want to start using SSPR for a group of 20 users in the marketing department as a trial deployment. If everything works well, you'll enable SSPR for your whole organization.

In this unit, you'll learn how to enable SSPR in Microsoft Entra ID.

Prerequisites

Before you start to configure SSPR, you need a:

- Microsoft Entra organization : This organization must have at least a P1 or P2 trial license enabled.

- Microsoft Entra account with Authentication Policy Administrator role : You'll use this account to set up SSPR.

- Non-administrative user account : You'll use this account to test SSPR. It's important that this account isn't an administrator, because Microsoft Entra imposes extra requirements on administrative accounts for SSPR. This user, and all user accounts, must have a valid license to use SSPR.

- Security group with which to test the configuration : The non-administrative user account must be a member of this group. You'll use this security group to limit who you roll SSPR out to.

Scope of SSPR rollout

There are three settings for the Self-service password reset enabled property:

- None : No users in the Microsoft Entra organization can use SSPR. This value is the default.

- Selected : Only the members of the specified security group can use SSPR. You can use this option to enable SSPR for a targeted group of users who can test it and verify that it works as expected. When you're ready to roll it out broadly, set the property to Enabled so that all users have access to SSPR.

- All : All users in the Microsoft Entra organization can use SSPR.

Configure SSPR

Here are the high-level steps to configure SSPR:

- Go to the Azure portal , then to Microsoft Entra ID > Manage > Password reset .

Go to the Azure portal , then to Microsoft Entra ID > Manage > Password reset .

- Properties : Enable SSPR. You can enable it for all users in the Microsoft Entra organization or for selected users. To enable for selected users, you must specify the security group. Members of this group can use SSPR.

Properties :

- Enable SSPR.

- You can enable it for all users in the Microsoft Entra organization or for selected users.

- To enable for selected users, you must specify the security group. Members of this group can use SSPR.

- Authentication methods : Choose whether to require one or two authentication methods. Choose the authentication methods that the users can use.

Authentication methods :

- Choose whether to require one or two authentication methods.

- Choose the authentication methods that the users can use.

- Registration : Specify whether users are required to register for SSPR when they next sign in. Specify how often users are asked to reconfirm their authentication information.

Registration :

- Specify whether users are required to register for SSPR when they next sign in.

- Specify how often users are asked to reconfirm their authentication information.

- Notifications : Choose whether to notify users and administrators of password resets.

Notifications : Choose whether to notify users and administrators of password resets.

- Customization : Provide an email address or web page URL where your users can get help.

Customization : Provide an email address or web page URL where your users can get help.

Unit 2.6.4 - Exercise - Set up self-service password reset

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/allow-users-reset-their-password/4-exercise-set-up-self-service-password-reset

Exercise - Set up self-service password reset

In this unit, you'll configure and test self-service password reset (SSPR) by using your email. You'll need to use your email to complete the password-reset process in this exercise.

Create a group

You want to roll out SSPR to a limited set of users first to make sure your SSPR configuration works as expected. Let's begin by creating a security group for the limited rollout.

- In the Microsoft Entra organization you created, under Manage , select Groups .

In the Microsoft Entra organization you created, under Manage , select Groups .

- Select New Group .

Select New Group .

- Enter the following values: Setting Value Group type Security Group name SSPRTesters Group description Members are testing the rollout of SSPR Membership type Assigned

Enter the following values:

Setting

Value

Group type

Security

Group name

SSPRTesters

Group description

Members are testing the rollout of SSPR

Membership type

Assigned

- Select Create .

Select Create .

Create a user account

To test your configuration, create an account that's not associated with an administrator role. You'll also assign the account to the group you created.

- In your Microsoft Entra organization, under Manage , select Users .

In your Microsoft Entra organization, under Manage , select Users .

- Select + New user , select Create new user in the drop-down, and use the following values: Setting Value User principal name balas Display name Bala Sandhu Password Select the Copy icon next to the autogenerated password, then paste the password to a text editor like Notepad.

Select + New user , select Create new user in the drop-down, and use the following values:

Setting

Value

User principal name

balas

Display name

Bala Sandhu

Password

Select the Copy icon next to the autogenerated password, then paste the password to a text editor like Notepad.

- Select the Assignments tab.

Select the Assignments tab.

- Select Add group , check the box for the SSPRTesters group, and then the Select button.

Select Add group , check the box for the SSPRTesters group, and then the Select button.

- Select Review + create and then select Create .

Select Review + create and then select Create .

Enable SSPR

Now, you're ready to enable SSPR for the group.

- In your Microsoft Entra organization, under Manage , select Password reset .

In your Microsoft Entra organization, under Manage , select Password reset .

- On the Properties page, select Selected . Select the link under Select Group , select the box next to the SSPRTesters group, and then the Select button.

On the Properties page, select Selected . Select the link under Select Group , select the box next to the SSPRTesters group, and then the Select button.

- Select Save .

Select Save .

- Under Manage , select the Authentication methods , Registration , and Notifications pages to review the default values. Ensure Authentication methods has Email selected.

Under Manage , select the Authentication methods , Registration , and Notifications pages to review the default values. Ensure Authentication methods has Email selected.

- Select Customization .

Select Customization .

- Select Yes , and then in the Custom helpdesk email or URL text box, enter admin@organization-domain-name.onmicrosoft.com . Replace "organization-domain-name" with the domain name of the Microsoft Entra organization you created. If you've forgotten the domain name, hover over your profile in the Azure portal.

Select Yes , and then in the Custom helpdesk email or URL text box, enter admin@organization-domain-name.onmicrosoft.com . Replace "organization-domain-name" with the domain name of the Microsoft Entra organization you created. If you've forgotten the domain name, hover over your profile in the Azure portal.

- Select Save .

Select Save .

Register for SSPR

Now that the SSPR configuration is complete, register an email for the user you created.

Note

If you get a message that says "The administrator has not enabled this feature," use private/incognito mode in your web browser.

- In a new browser window, go to https://aka.ms/ssprsetup .

In a new browser window, go to https://aka.ms/ssprsetup .

- Sign in with the user name balas@organization-domain-name.onmicrosoft.com and the password that you noted earlier. Remember to replace "organization-domain-name" with the domain name of the Microsoft Entra organization you created.

Sign in with the user name balas@organization-domain-name.onmicrosoft.com and the password that you noted earlier. Remember to replace "organization-domain-name" with the domain name of the Microsoft Entra organization you created.

- If you're asked to update your password, enter a new password of your choice. Make sure you note the new password.

If you're asked to update your password, enter a new password of your choice. Make sure you note the new password.

- Select the Security info tab, and then select + Add sign-in method .

Select the Security info tab, and then select + Add sign-in method .

- In the Add a method box, select Email .

In the Add a method box, select Email .

- Enter your email details.

Enter your email details.

- When you receive the code in your email, enter the code in the text box and select Next .

When you receive the code in your email, enter the code in the text box and select Next .

Test SSPR

Now, let's test whether the user can reset their password.

- In a new browser window, go to https://aka.ms/sspr .

In a new browser window, go to https://aka.ms/sspr .

- For User ID , type balas@organization-domain-name.onmicrosoft.com . Replace "organization-domain-name" with the domain you used for your Microsoft Entra organization.

For User ID , type balas@organization-domain-name.onmicrosoft.com . Replace "organization-domain-name" with the domain you used for your Microsoft Entra organization.

- Complete the CAPTCHA and select Next .

Complete the CAPTCHA and select Next .

- The Email my alternate email radio button is selected. Select Email .

The Email my alternate email radio button is selected. Select Email .

- When the email arrives, in the Enter your verification code text box, enter the code you were sent. Select Next .

When the email arrives, in the Enter your verification code text box, enter the code you were sent. Select Next .

- Enter a new password, and then select Finish . Make sure you note the new password.

Enter a new password, and then select Finish . Make sure you note the new password.

- Close the browser window.

Close the browser window.

Unit 2.6.5 - Exercise - Customize directory branding

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/allow-users-reset-their-password/5-exercise-customize-directory-branding

Exercise - Customize directory branding

Suppose you've been asked to display your retail organization's branding on the Azure sign-in page to reassure users that they're passing credentials to a legitimate system. Here, you'll learn how to configure this custom branding.

To complete this exercise, you must have two image files:

- A page background image. This must be a PNG or JPG file, 1920 x 1080 pixels, and smaller than 300 KB.

- A company logo image. This must be a PNG or JPG file, 32 x 32 pixels, and smaller than 5 KB.

Customize Microsoft Entra organization branding

Let's use Microsoft Entra ID to set up the custom branding.

- Sign in to the Azure portal .

Sign in to the Azure portal .

- Go to your Microsoft Entra organization by selecting Microsoft Entra ID . If you're not in the right Microsoft Entra organization, go to your Azure profile, and select Switch directory to find your organization.

Go to your Microsoft Entra organization by selecting Microsoft Entra ID . If you're not in the right Microsoft Entra organization, go to your Azure profile, and select Switch directory to find your organization.

- Under Manage , select Company branding . Then select the Customize button in the center of the screen.

Under Manage , select Company branding . Then select the Customize button in the center of the screen.

- Next to Favicon , select Browse . Select your logo image.

Next to Favicon , select Browse . Select your logo image.

- Next to Background image , select Browse . Select your page background image.

Next to Background image , select Browse . Select your page background image.

- Select a Page background color or accept the default.

Select a Page background color or accept the default.

- Select Review + Create , and then select Create .

Select Review + Create , and then select Create .

Test the organization's branding

Now, let's use the account that we created in the last exercise to test the branding.

- In a new browser window, go to https://login.microsoft.com .

In a new browser window, go to https://login.microsoft.com .

- Select the account for Bala Sandhu . Your custom branding is displayed.

Select the account for Bala Sandhu . Your custom branding is displayed.

- Select Forgot my password .

Select Forgot my password .

Unit 2.6.6 - Summary

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/allow-users-reset-their-password/6-summary

Summary

In this module, you've learned how you can use SSPR in Microsoft Entra ID to allow users to reset their forgotten or expired passwords. An administrator doesn't have to do the password reset. SSPR is secured by authentication methods of your choice. These methods can include a mobile authentication app, a code sent to you by an SMS text message, or security questions.

SSPR helps reduce the amount of work required from administrators. It also minimizes the productivity impact for users when they forget their password.

Clean up

Remember to clean up after you've finished.

- Delete the user you created in Microsoft Entra ID : Go to Microsoft Entra ID > Manage > Users . Check the box next to the user and select Delete . Select OK .

- Delete the group you created in Microsoft Entra ID : Go to Microsoft Entra ID > Manage > Groups . Check the box next to the group and select Delete . Select OK .

- Turn off self-service password reset : Go to Microsoft Entra ID > Manage > Password reset . Under Self service password reset enabled , select None . Select Save .

If you created a Premium trial Microsoft Entra tenant for this module, you can delete the tenant 30 days after the trial has expired.

Learn more

- Tutorial: Enable users to unlock their account or reset passwords using Microsoft Entra self-service password reset

- How it works: Microsoft Entra self-service password reset

- Enable self-service password reset

LP 3 M1 - Configure virtual networks

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-networks/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 3.1.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-networks/1-introduction

Introduction

Azure virtual networks are an essential component for creating private networks in Azure. They allow different Azure resources to securely communicate with each other, the internet, and on-premises networks.

Suppose you work for a company in the healthcare industry. Your company is looking to migrate their on-premises infrastructure to Azure. They want to ensure secure communication between their resources in Azure and their on-premises network. The company is also concerned about scalability and availability. By using Azure virtual networks, they can create a private network in Azure and securely connect their resources.

The topics covered in this module include subnetting, creating virtual networks, and using private and public IP addresses. You also learn about the different scenarios where virtual networks can be used. These scenarios include creating a dedicated private cloud-only network or extending a data center securely. The module provides a detailed explanation of subnets and their benefits, and how to plan IP addressing for Azure resources.

By the end of this module, you have a clear understanding of how to create and configure AI-ready virtual networks in Azure. You're able to effectively use subnets, assign IP addresses, and ensure secure communication between your Azure resources and on-premises network.

Learning objectives

In this module, you learn how to:

- Describe Azure virtual network features and components.

- Identify features and usage cases for subnets and subnetting.

- Identify usage cases for private and public IP addresses.

- Create a virtual network and assign an IP address.

Skills measured

The content in the module helps you prepare for Exam AZ-104: Microsoft Azure Administrator .

Prerequisites

- Basic knowledge of virtual networking in cloud environments.

- Familiarity with IP address formats and subnetting.

Unit 3.1.2 - Plan virtual networks

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-networks/2-plan-virtual-networks

Plan virtual networks

A major incentive for adopting cloud solutions like Azure is to enable information technology departments to transition server resources to the cloud. Moving resources to the cloud can save money and simplify administrative operations. Relocating resources removes the need to maintain expensive datacenters with uninterruptible power supplies, generators, multiple fail-safes, or clustered database servers. For small and medium-sized companies, which might not have the expertise to maintain their own robust infrastructure, moving to the cloud is particularly appealing.

Things to know about Azure virtual networks

You can implement Azure Virtual Network to create a virtual representation of your network in the cloud. With some planning , you can deploy virtual networks and connect the resources you need more effectively. Let's examine some characteristics of virtual networks in Azure.

- An Azure virtual network is a logical isolation of the Azure cloud resources.

An Azure virtual network is a logical isolation of the Azure cloud resources.

- You can use virtual networks to provision and manage virtual private networks (VPNs) in Azure.

You can use virtual networks to provision and manage virtual private networks (VPNs) in Azure.

- Each virtual network has its own Classless Inter-Domain Routing (CIDR) block and can be linked to other virtual networks and on-premises networks.

Each virtual network has its own Classless Inter-Domain Routing (CIDR) block and can be linked to other virtual networks and on-premises networks.

- You can link virtual networks with an on-premises IT infrastructure to create hybrid or cross-premises solutions, when the CIDR blocks of the connecting networks don't overlap.

You can link virtual networks with an on-premises IT infrastructure to create hybrid or cross-premises solutions, when the CIDR blocks of the connecting networks don't overlap.

- You control the DNS server settings for virtual networks, and segmentation of the virtual network into subnets.

You control the DNS server settings for virtual networks, and segmentation of the virtual network into subnets.

The next illustration depicts a virtual network that has a subnet containing two virtual machines. The virtual network has connections to an on-premises infrastructure and a separate virtual network.

Things to consider when using virtual networks

Virtual networks can be used in many ways. As you think about the configuration plan for your virtual networks and subnets, consider the following scenarios.

Scenario

Description

Create a dedicated private cloud-only virtual network

Sometimes you don't require a cross-premises configuration for your solution. When you create a virtual network, your services and virtual machines within your virtual network can communicate directly and securely with each other in the cloud. You can still configure endpoint connections for the virtual machines and services that require internet communication, as part of your solution.

Securely extend your data center with virtual networks

You can build traditional site-to-site VPNs to securely scale your datacenter capacity. Site-to-site VPNs use IPSEC to provide a secure connection between your corporate VPN gateway and Azure.

Enable hybrid cloud scenarios

Virtual networks give you the flexibility to support a range of hybrid cloud scenarios. You can securely connect cloud-based applications to any type of on-premises system, such as mainframes and Unix systems.

Unit 3.1.3 - Create subnets

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-networks/3-create-subnets

Create subnets

Azure Subnets provide a way for you to implement logical divisions within your virtual network. Your network can be segmented into subnets to help improve security, increase performance, and make it easier to manage.

Things to know about subnets

There are certain conditions for the IP addresses in a virtual network when you apply segmentation with subnets.

- Each subnet contains a range of IP addresses that fall within the virtual network address space.

Each subnet contains a range of IP addresses that fall within the virtual network address space.

- The address range for a subnet must be unique within the address space for the virtual network.

The address range for a subnet must be unique within the address space for the virtual network.

- The range for one subnet can't overlap with other subnet IP address ranges in the same virtual network.

The range for one subnet can't overlap with other subnet IP address ranges in the same virtual network.

- The IP address space for a subnet must be specified by using CIDR notation.

The IP address space for a subnet must be specified by using CIDR notation.

- You can segment a virtual network into one or more subnets in the Azure portal. Characteristics about the IP addresses for the subnets are listed.

You can segment a virtual network into one or more subnets in the Azure portal. Characteristics about the IP addresses for the subnets are listed.

Reserved addresses

For each subnet, Azure reserves five IP addresses. The first four addresses and the last address are reserved.

Let's examine the reserved addresses in an IP address range of 192.168.1.0/24 .

192.168.1.0/24

Reserved address

Reason

192.168.1.0

This value identifies the virtual network address.

192.168.1.1

Azure configures this address as the default gateway.

192.168.1.2 and 192.168.1.3

192.168.1.2

192.168.1.3

Azure maps these Azure DNS IP addresses to the virtual network space.

192.168.1.255

This value supplies the virtual network broadcast address.

Things to consider when using subnets

When you plan for adding subnet segments within your virtual network, there are several factors to consider.

- Consider service requirements . Each service directly deployed into a virtual network has specific requirements for routing and the types of traffic that must be allowed into and out of associated subnets. A service might require or create their own subnet. There must be enough unallocated space to meet the service requirements. Suppose you connect a virtual network to an on-premises network by using Azure VPN Gateway. The virtual network must have a dedicated subnet for the gateway.

Consider service requirements . Each service directly deployed into a virtual network has specific requirements for routing and the types of traffic that must be allowed into and out of associated subnets. A service might require or create their own subnet. There must be enough unallocated space to meet the service requirements. Suppose you connect a virtual network to an on-premises network by using Azure VPN Gateway. The virtual network must have a dedicated subnet for the gateway.

- Consider network virtual appliances . Azure routes network traffic between all subnets in a virtual network, by default. You can override Azure's default routing to prevent Azure routing between subnets. You can also override the default to route traffic between subnets through a network virtual appliance. If you require traffic between resources in the same virtual network to flow through a network virtual appliance, deploy the resources to different subnets.

Consider network virtual appliances . Azure routes network traffic between all subnets in a virtual network, by default. You can override Azure's default routing to prevent Azure routing between subnets. You can also override the default to route traffic between subnets through a network virtual appliance. If you require traffic between resources in the same virtual network to flow through a network virtual appliance, deploy the resources to different subnets.

- Consider network security groups . You can associate zero or one network security group to each subnet in a virtual network. You can associate the same or a different network security group to each subnet. Each network security group contains rules that allow or deny traffic to and from sources and destinations.

Consider network security groups . You can associate zero or one network security group to each subnet in a virtual network. You can associate the same or a different network security group to each subnet. Each network security group contains rules that allow or deny traffic to and from sources and destinations.

- Consider private links . Azure Private Link provides private connectivity from a virtual network to Azure platform as a service (PaaS), customer-owned, or Microsoft partner services. Private Link simplifies the network architecture and secures the connection between endpoints in Azure. The service eliminates data exposure to the public internet.

Consider private links . Azure Private Link provides private connectivity from a virtual network to Azure platform as a service (PaaS), customer-owned, or Microsoft partner services. Private Link simplifies the network architecture and secures the connection between endpoints in Azure. The service eliminates data exposure to the public internet.

Unit 3.1.4 - Create virtual networks

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-networks/4-create-virtual-networks

Create virtual networks

You can create new virtual networks at any time. You can also add virtual networks when you create a virtual machine.

Things to know about creating virtual networks

Review these requirements for creating a virtual network.

- When you create a virtual network, you need to define the IP address space for the network.

When you create a virtual network, you need to define the IP address space for the network.

- Plan to use an IP address space that's not already in use in your organization.

Plan to use an IP address space that's not already in use in your organization.

- The address space for the virtual network can be either on-premises or in the cloud, but not both.

The address space for the virtual network can be either on-premises or in the cloud, but not both.

- To create a virtual network, you need to define at least one subnet. Each subnet contains a range of IP addresses that fall within the virtual network address space. The address range for each subnet must be unique within the address space for the virtual network. The range for one subnet can't overlap with other subnet IP address ranges in the same virtual network.

To create a virtual network, you need to define at least one subnet.

- Each subnet contains a range of IP addresses that fall within the virtual network address space.

Each subnet contains a range of IP addresses that fall within the virtual network address space.

- The address range for each subnet must be unique within the address space for the virtual network.

The address range for each subnet must be unique within the address space for the virtual network.

- The range for one subnet can't overlap with other subnet IP address ranges in the same virtual network.

The range for one subnet can't overlap with other subnet IP address ranges in the same virtual network.

- You can create a virtual network in the Azure portal. Provide the Azure subscription, resource group, virtual network name, and service region for the network.

You can create a virtual network in the Azure portal. Provide the Azure subscription, resource group, virtual network name, and service region for the network.

Note

Default limits on Azure networking resources can change periodically. Be sure to consult the Azure networking documentation for the latest information.

Unit 3.1.5 - Plan IP addressing

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-networks/5-plan-addressing

Plan IP addressing

Let's begin with an overview of IP addressing.

You can assign IP addresses to Azure resources to communicate with other Azure resources, your on-premises network, and the internet. There are two types of Azure IP addresses: private and public .

Private IP addresses enable communication within an Azure virtual network and your on-premises network. You create a private IP address for your resource when you use a VPN gateway or Azure ExpressRoute circuit to extend your network to Azure.

Public IP addresses allow your resource to communicate with the internet. You can create a public IP address to connect with Azure public-facing services.

The next illustration shows a virtual machine resource that has a private IP address and a public IP address.

Things to know about IP addresses

Let's take a closer look at the characteristics of IP addresses.

- IP addresses can be statically assigned or dynamically assigned.

IP addresses can be statically assigned or dynamically assigned.

- You can separate dynamically and statically assigned IP resources into different subnets.

You can separate dynamically and statically assigned IP resources into different subnets.

- Static IP addresses don't change and are best for certain situations, such as: DNS name resolution, where a change in the IP address requires updating host records. IP address-based security models that require apps or services to have a static IP address. TLS/SSL certificates linked to an IP address. Firewall rules that allow or deny traffic by using IP address ranges. Role-based virtual machines such as Domain Controllers and DNS servers.

Static IP addresses don't change and are best for certain situations, such as:

- DNS name resolution, where a change in the IP address requires updating host records.

- IP address-based security models that require apps or services to have a static IP address.

- TLS/SSL certificates linked to an IP address.

- Firewall rules that allow or deny traffic by using IP address ranges.

Unit 3.1.6 - Create public IP addressing

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-networks/6-create-public-ip-addressing

Create public IP addressing

You can create a public IP address for your resource in the Azure portal. For example, you could create a public IP address for a virtual machine.

Things to consider when creating a public IP address

To create a public IP address, configure these settings. Notice that public IP addresses are often used with load balancers.

- IP Version : Public IP addresses can be attached to a load balancer or to a network interface. IPv4 and IPv6 addresses are charged at the same rate.

IP Version : Public IP addresses can be attached to a load balancer or to a network interface. IPv4 and IPv6 addresses are charged at the same rate.

- SKU : Select the SKU for the public IP address. A Public IP's SKU must match the SKU of the Load Balancer with which it is used.

SKU : Select the SKU for the public IP address. A Public IP's SKU must match the SKU of the Load Balancer with which it is used.

- Tier : Must match the load balancer tier. A cross-region load balancer distributes traffic across regional backends. Regional distributes traffic within a virtual network.

Tier : Must match the load balancer tier. A cross-region load balancer distributes traffic across regional backends. Regional distributes traffic within a virtual network.

- IP address assignment : Static addresses are assigned when a public IP address is created. Static addresses aren't released until a public IP address resource is deleted.

IP address assignment : Static addresses are assigned when a public IP address is created. Static addresses aren't released until a public IP address resource is deleted.

Unit 3.1.7 - Associate public IP addresses

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-networks/7-associate-public-ip-addresses

Associate public IP addresses

A public IP address resource can be associated with virtual machine network interfaces, internet-facing load balancers, VPN gateways, and application gateways. You can associate your resource with both dynamic and static public IP addresses.

Things to consider when associating public IP addresses

The next table summarizes how you can associate public IP addresses for different types of resources.

Top-level resource

IP address configuration

Virtual machine

Network interface configuration

Virtual Network Gateway (VPN), Virtual Network Gateway (ER), NAT Gateway

Gateway IP configuration

Public Load Balancer, Application Gateway, Azure Firewall, Route Server, API Management

Front-end configuration

Bastion host

Public IP configuration

Public IP address SKU features

The next table summarizes the standard SKU features.

Public IP address

Standard SKU

Allocation method

Static

Security

Secure by default model

Available zones

Supported. Standard IPs can be nonzonal, zonal, or zone-redundant.

Unit 3.1.8 - Allocate or assign private IP addresses

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-networks/8-associate-private-ip-addresses

Allocate or assign private IP addresses

A private IP address resource can be associated with virtual machine network interfaces, internal load balancers, and application gateways. Azure can provide an IP address (dynamic assignment) or you can assign the IP address (static assignment).

Things to consider when associating private IP addresses

The next table summarizes how you can associate private IP addresses for different types of resources.

Resource

Private IP address association

Dynamic IP address

Static IP address

Virtual machine

NIC

Yes

Internal load balancer

Front-end configuration

Yes

Application gateway

Front-end configuration

Yes

Private IP address assignment

A private IP address is allocated from the address range of the virtual network subnet that a resource is deployed in. There are two options: dynamic and static.

- Dynamic : Azure assigns the next available unassigned or unreserved IP address in the subnet's address range. Dynamic assignment is the default allocation method. Suppose addresses 10.0.0.4 through 10.0.0.9 are already assigned to other resources. In this case, Azure assigns the address 10.0.0.10 to a new resource.

Dynamic : Azure assigns the next available unassigned or unreserved IP address in the subnet's address range. Dynamic assignment is the default allocation method.

Suppose addresses 10.0.0.4 through 10.0.0.9 are already assigned to other resources. In this case, Azure assigns the address 10.0.0.10 to a new resource.

- Static : You select and assign any unassigned or unreserved IP address in the subnet's address range. Suppose a subnet's address range is 10.0.0.0/16, and addresses 10.0.0.4 through 10.0.0.9 are already assigned to other resources. In this scenario, you can assign any address between 10.0.0.10 and 10.0.255.254.

Static : You select and assign any unassigned or unreserved IP address in the subnet's address range.

Suppose a subnet's address range is 10.0.0.0/16, and addresses 10.0.0.4 through 10.0.0.9 are already assigned to other resources. In this scenario, you can assign any address between 10.0.0.10 and 10.0.255.254.

Tip

For a more complete review of virtual networks, consider the Introduction to Virtual Networks training module.

Unit 3.1.9 - Exercise: Create and configure virtual networks

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-networks/9-simulation-create-networks

Exercise: Create and configure virtual networks

Exercise scenario

Your organization is migrating a web-based application to Azure. Your first task is to put in place the virtual networks and subnets. You also need to securely peer the virtual networks. You identify these requirements.

- Two virtual networks are required, app-vnet and hub-vnet. The virtual networks simulate a hub and spoke network architecture.

- The app-vnet hosts the application. The app-vnet virtual network requires two subnets. The frontend subnet hosts the web servers. The backend subnet hosts the database servers.

- The hub-vnet only requires a subnet for the firewall.

- The two virtual networks must be able to communicate with each other securely and privately through virtual network peering.

- Both virtual networks should be in the same region.

Architecture diagram

Job skills

- Create a virtual network.

- Create a subnet.

- Configure virtual network peering (optional).

Note

Estimated time: 30 minutes.

To complete this exercise, you need an Azure subscription .

Launch the exercise, and follow the instructions. When finished, be sure to return to this page so you can continue learning.

Unit 3.1.10 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-networks/10-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Your company is migrating to Azure and replicating their on-premises network in the cloud. They're developing a plan to use Azure Virtual Network to organize company resources into virtual networks and subnets. You're working on the design for the company IP address schema, mapping out which ranges can be assigned, and which ranges can be denied traffic.

Answer these questions

Choose the best response for each question.

Unit 3.1.11 - Summary and resources

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-networks/11-summary-resources

Summary and resources

In this module, you learned about Azure virtual networks and their importance in creating private networks in Azure. You explored the benefits of using virtual networks, such as scalability, availability, and isolation. You learned how to create virtual networks with subnetting and how to determine which resources require public or private IP addresses.

The main takeaways from this module are:

- Azure virtual networks allow different Azure resources to securely communicate with each other, the internet, and on-premises networks.

Azure virtual networks allow different Azure resources to securely communicate with each other, the internet, and on-premises networks.

- Subnets within virtual networks provide logical divisions, improving security, performance, and management.

Subnets within virtual networks provide logical divisions, improving security, performance, and management.

- When creating virtual networks, ensure that the IP address space is unique and doesn't overlap with other subnets.

When creating virtual networks, ensure that the IP address space is unique and doesn't overlap with other subnets.

- IP addresses can provide public or private access to resources.

IP addresses can provide public or private access to resources.

Learn more with Copilot

Copilot can assist you in designing Azure infrastructure solutions. Copilot can compare, recommend, explain, and research products and services where you need more information. Open a Microsoft Edge browser and choose Copilot (top right) or navigate to copilot.microsoft.com. Take a few minutes to try these prompts and extend your learning with Copilot.

- Explain CIDR for a nontechnical audience. Provide examples.

Explain CIDR for a nontechnical audience. Provide examples.

- What are the basic steps and considerations for creating a virtual network in Azure?

What are the basic steps and considerations for creating a virtual network in Azure?

- What types of Azure resources should be assigned a static IP address?

What types of Azure resources should be assigned a static IP address?

Learn more with documentation

- What is Azure Virtual Network? . This article is your starting point to learn about virtual networks.

What is Azure Virtual Network? . This article is your starting point to learn about virtual networks.

- Public IP addresses . This article reviews the basics of when to use public IP addresses.

Public IP addresses . This article reviews the basics of when to use public IP addresses.

- Private IP addresses . This article reviews the basics of when to use private IP addresses.

Private IP addresses . This article reviews the basics of when to use private IP addresses.

Learn more with self-paced training

- Introduction to Azure Virtual Networks . Learn how to design and implement core Azure Networking infrastructure.

Introduction to Azure Virtual Networks . Learn how to design and implement core Azure Networking infrastructure.

- Implement Windows Server IaaS virtual machine IP addressing and routing . Learn about IP addressing and virtual networks for virtual machines.

Implement Windows Server IaaS virtual machine IP addressing and routing . Learn about IP addressing and virtual networks for virtual machines.

LP 3 M2 - Configure network security groups

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-network-security-groups/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 3.2.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-network-security-groups/1-introduction

Introduction

Network security groups are a way to limit network traffic to resources in your virtual network. Network security groups contain a list of security rules that allow or deny inbound or outbound network traffic.

Suppose your company has several locations and wants to migrate to a cloud based solution. The company only considers moving key systems onto the cloud platform if stringent security requirements can be met. These requirements include tight control over which computers have network access to the app servers. You need to secure both virtual machine networking and Azure services networking. Your goal is to prevent unwanted or unsecured network traffic from being able to reach key systems.

In this module, you learn how to create an AI-ready network security group, configure inbound and outbound port rules, and verify secure connectivity. The goal of this module is to teach you how to control network traffic with network security groups.

Learning objectives

In this module, you learn how to:

- Determine when to use network security groups.

- Create network security groups.

- Implement and evaluate network security group rules.

- Describe the function of application security groups.

Skills measured

The content in the module helps you prepare for Exam AZ-104: Microsoft Azure Administrator .

Prerequisites

- Familiarity with Azure virtual networks and resources such as virtual machines.

- Working knowledge of the Azure portal so you can configure the network security groups.

- Basic understanding of traffic routing and traffic control strategies.

Unit 3.2.2 - Implement network security groups

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-network-security-groups/2-implement-network-security-groups

Implement network security groups

You can limit network traffic to resources in your virtual network by using a network security group . You can assign a network security group to a subnet or a network interface, and define security rules in the group to control network traffic.

Things to know about network security groups

Let's look at the characteristics of network security groups.

- A network security group contains a list of security rules that allow or deny inbound or outbound network traffic.

A network security group contains a list of security rules that allow or deny inbound or outbound network traffic.

- A network security group can be associated to a subnet or a network interface.

A network security group can be associated to a subnet or a network interface.

- A network security group can be associated multiple times.

A network security group can be associated multiple times.

- You create a network security group and define security rules in the Azure portal.

You create a network security group and define security rules in the Azure portal.

- The Overview page for a virtual machine provides information about the associated network security groups. You can see details such as the assigned subnets, assigned network interfaces, and the defined security rules.

The Overview page for a virtual machine provides information about the associated network security groups. You can see details such as the assigned subnets, assigned network interfaces, and the defined security rules.

Network security groups and subnets

You can assign network security groups to a subnet and create a protected screened subnet (also referred to as a demilitarized zone or DMZ ). A DMZ acts as a buffer between resources within your virtual network and the internet.

- Use the network security group to restrict traffic flow to all machines that reside within the subnet.

Use the network security group to restrict traffic flow to all machines that reside within the subnet.

- Each subnet can have a maximum of one associated network security group.

Each subnet can have a maximum of one associated network security group.

Network security groups and network interfaces

You can assign network security groups to a network interface card (NIC).

- Define network security group rules to control all traffic that flows through a network interface.

Define network security group rules to control all traffic that flows through a network interface.

- Each network interface that exists in a subnet can have zero, or one, associated network security groups.

Each network interface that exists in a subnet can have zero, or one, associated network security groups.

Unit 3.2.3 - Determine network security group rules

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-network-security-groups/3-determine-network-security-groups-rules

Determine network security group rules

Security rules in network security groups enable you to filter network traffic. You can define rules to control the traffic flow in and out of virtual network subnets and network interfaces.

Things to know about security rules

Let's review the characteristics of security rules in network security groups.

- Azure creates several default security rules within each network security group, including inbound traffic and outbound traffic. Examples of default rules include DenyAllInbound traffic and AllowInternetOutbound traffic.

Azure creates several default security rules within each network security group, including inbound traffic and outbound traffic. Examples of default rules include DenyAllInbound traffic and AllowInternetOutbound traffic.

DenyAllInbound

AllowInternetOutbound

- Azure creates the default security rules in each network security group that you create.

Azure creates the default security rules in each network security group that you create.

- You can add more security rules to a network security group by specifying conditions . Here's a list of the most common conditions. Setting Value Source Any, IP Addresses, My IP address, Service Tag, or Application security group Source port ranges Specify the ports on which the rule allows or denies traffic Destination Any, IP Addresses, Service Tag, or Application security group Protocol Restrict the rule to Transmission Control Protocol (TCP), User Datagram Protocol (UDP), Internet Control Message Protocol (ICMP), Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP), or Authentication Header (AH). ESP and AH protocols are only available via JSON templates and PowerShell. The default is for the rule to apply to all protocols (Any). Action Allow or Deny Priority A value between 100 and 4,096 that's unique for all security rules within the NSG

You can add more security rules to a network security group by specifying conditions . Here's a list of the most common conditions.

Setting

Value

Source

Any, IP Addresses, My IP address, Service Tag, or Application security group

Source port ranges

Specify the ports on which the rule allows or denies traffic

Destination

Any, IP Addresses, Service Tag, or Application security group

Protocol

Restrict the rule to Transmission Control Protocol (TCP), User Datagram Protocol (UDP), Internet Control Message Protocol (ICMP), Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP), or Authentication Header (AH). ESP and AH protocols are only available via JSON templates and PowerShell. The default is for the rule to apply to all protocols (Any).

Action

Allow or Deny

Priority

A value between 100 and 4,096 that's unique for all security rules within the NSG

- Each security rule is assigned a Priority value. All security rules for a network security group are processed in priority order. When a rule has a low Priority value, the rule has a higher priority or precedence in terms of order processing.

Each security rule is assigned a Priority value. All security rules for a network security group are processed in priority order. When a rule has a low Priority value, the rule has a higher priority or precedence in terms of order processing.

- You can't remove the default security rules.

You can't remove the default security rules.

- You can override a default security rule by creating another security rule that has a higher Priority setting for your network security group.

You can override a default security rule by creating another security rule that has a higher Priority setting for your network security group.

Inbound traffic rules

Azure defines three default inbound security rules for your network security group. These rules deny all inbound traffic except traffic from your virtual network and Azure load balancers. The next image shows the default inbound security rules for a network security group in the Azure portal.

Outbound traffic rules

Azure defines three default outbound security rules for your network security group. These rules only allow outbound traffic to the internet and your virtual network. The next image shows the default outbound security rules for a network security group in the Azure portal.

Unit 3.2.4 - Determine network security group effective rules

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-network-security-groups/4-determine-network-security-groups-effective-rules

Determine network security group effective rules

Each network security group and its defined security rules are evaluated independently. Azure processes the conditions in each rule defined for each virtual machine in your configuration.

- For inbound traffic, Azure first processes network security group security rules for any associated subnets and then any associated network interfaces.

- For outbound traffic, the process is reversed. Azure first evaluates network security group security rules for any associated network interfaces followed by any associated subnets.

- For both the inbound and outbound evaluation process, Azure also checks how to apply the rules for intra-subnet traffic. Intra-subnet traffic refers to virtual machines in the same subnet.

How Azure ends up applying your defined security rules for a virtual machine determines the overall effectiveness of your rules.

Network security group evaluation

When you apply network security groups to both a subnet and a network interface, each network security group is evaluated independently. Both inbound and outbound rules are considered based on the priority and processing order.

Things to consider when creating effective rules

Review the following considerations regarding creating effective security rules for machines in your virtual network.

- Consider allowing all traffic . If you place your virtual machine within a subnet or utilize a network interface, you don't have to associate the subnet or NIC with a network security group. This approach allows all network traffic through the subnet or NIC according to the default Azure security rules. If you're not concerned about controlling traffic to your resource at a specific level, then don't associate your resource at that level to a network security group.

Consider allowing all traffic . If you place your virtual machine within a subnet or utilize a network interface, you don't have to associate the subnet or NIC with a network security group. This approach allows all network traffic through the subnet or NIC according to the default Azure security rules. If you're not concerned about controlling traffic to your resource at a specific level, then don't associate your resource at that level to a network security group.

- Consider importance of allow rules . When you create a network security group, you must define an allow rule for both the subnet and network interface in the group to ensure traffic can get through. If you have a subnet or NIC in your network security group, you must define an allow rule at each level. Otherwise, the traffic is denied for any level that doesn't provide an allow rule definition.

Consider importance of allow rules . When you create a network security group, you must define an allow rule for both the subnet and network interface in the group to ensure traffic can get through. If you have a subnet or NIC in your network security group, you must define an allow rule at each level. Otherwise, the traffic is denied for any level that doesn't provide an allow rule definition.

- Consider intra-subnet traffic . The security rules for a network security group associated to a subnet can affect traffic between all virtual machines in the subnet. You can prohibit intra-subnet traffic by defining a rule in the network security group to deny all inbound and outbound traffic. This rule prevents all virtual machines in your subnet from communicating with each other.

Consider intra-subnet traffic . The security rules for a network security group associated to a subnet can affect traffic between all virtual machines in the subnet. You can prohibit intra-subnet traffic by defining a rule in the network security group to deny all inbound and outbound traffic. This rule prevents all virtual machines in your subnet from communicating with each other.

- Consider rule priority . The security rules for a network security group are processed in priority order. To ensure a particular security rule is always processed, assign the lowest possible priority value to the rule. It's a good practice to leave gaps in your priority numbering, such as 100, 200, 300, and so. The gaps in the numbering allow you to add new rules without having to edit existing rules.

Consider rule priority . The security rules for a network security group are processed in priority order. To ensure a particular security rule is always processed, assign the lowest possible priority value to the rule. It's a good practice to leave gaps in your priority numbering, such as 100, 200, 300, and so. The gaps in the numbering allow you to add new rules without having to edit existing rules.

View effective security rules

If you have several network security groups and aren't sure which security rules are being applied, you can use the Effective security rules link in the Azure portal. You can use the link to verify which security rules are applied to your machines, subnets, and network interfaces.

Note

Network Watcher provides a consolidated view of your infrastructure rules, including both NSG rules and Azure Virtual Network Manager security admin rules. The IP flow verify feature evaluates traffic against both NSG rules and any security admin rules that may be in effect.

Unit 3.2.5 - Create network security group rules

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-network-security-groups/5-create-network-security-groups-rules

Create network security group rules

It's easy to add security rules to control inbound and outbound traffic in the Azure portal. You can configure your virtual network security group rule settings, and select from a large variety of communication services, including HTTPS, RDP, FTP, and DNS.

Things to know about configuring security rules

Let's look at some of the properties you need to specify to create your security rules. As you review these settings, think about the traffic rules you need to create and what services can fulfill your network requirements.

- Source : Identifies how the security rule controls inbound traffic. The value specifies a specific source IP address range to allow or deny. The source filter can be any resource, an IP address range, an application security group, or a default tag.

Source : Identifies how the security rule controls inbound traffic. The value specifies a specific source IP address range to allow or deny. The source filter can be any resource, an IP address range, an application security group, or a default tag.

- Destination : Identifies how the security rule controls outbound traffic. The value specifies a specific destination IP address range to allow or deny. The destination filter value is similar to the source filter. The value can be any resource, an IP address range, an application security group, or a default tag.

Destination : Identifies how the security rule controls outbound traffic. The value specifies a specific destination IP address range to allow or deny. The destination filter value is similar to the source filter. The value can be any resource, an IP address range, an application security group, or a default tag.

- Service : Specifies the destination protocol and port range for the security rule. You can choose a predefined service like RDP or SSH or provide a custom port range. There are a large number of services to select from.

Service : Specifies the destination protocol and port range for the security rule. You can choose a predefined service like RDP or SSH or provide a custom port range. There are a large number of services to select from.

- Priority : Assigns the priority order value for the security rule. Rules are processed according to the priority order of all rules for a network security group, including a subnet and network interface. The lower the priority value, the higher priority for the rule.

Priority : Assigns the priority order value for the security rule. Rules are processed according to the priority order of all rules for a network security group, including a subnet and network interface. The lower the priority value, the higher priority for the rule.

When to use augmented security rules

A single network security group rule can contain multiple values in the Source, Destination, and Service fields. This approach, called augmented security rules, reduces the total number of rules needed and simplifies NSG management.

Things to know about augments security rules

- Multiple IP addresses : Combine multiple IP addresses into one rule.

Multiple IP addresses : Combine multiple IP addresses into one rule.

- Multiple port ranges : Specify multiple ports and ranges in the Service field.

Multiple port ranges : Specify multiple ports and ranges in the Service field.

- Service tags and ASGs : Mix service tags, application security groups, and IP addresses within the same rule.

Service tags and ASGs : Mix service tags, application security groups, and IP addresses within the same rule.

- Reduced rule count : Instead of creating separate rules for each IP range or port, combine them into fewer, more manageable rules.

Reduced rule count : Instead of creating separate rules for each IP range or port, combine them into fewer, more manageable rules.

In enterprise environments with many IP ranges or services, augmented rules prevent NSG rule sprawl. For example, instead of creating four separate rules for ports 80, 443, 8080, and 8090, create one rule with all the ports.

Tip

Expand your learning with the Secure and isolate access to Azure resources by using network security groups and service endpoints training module. This module includes a sandbox where you can practice.

Unit 3.2.6 - Implement application security groups

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-network-security-groups/6-implement-asgs

Implement application security groups

You can implement application security groups (ASGs) in your Azure virtual network to logically group your virtual machines by workload. You can then define your network security group rules based on your application security groups.

Things to know about using application security groups

Application security groups provide an application-centric way of looking at your infrastructure. You join your virtual machines to an application security group. Then you use the application security group as a source or destination in the network security group rules.

Let's examine how to implement application security groups by creating a configuration for an online retailer. In our example scenario, we need to control network traffic to virtual machines in application security groups.

Note

In the diagram, the application servers are handing SQL Server requests.

Scenario requirements

Here are the scenario requirements for our example configuration:

- In this scenario, there are two tiers: web servers and application servers.

- The web servers handle HTTP and HTTPS internet traffic.

- The application servers process SQL requests from the web servers.

Solution

For our scenario, we need to build the following configuration:

- Create application security groups for each tier.

Create application security groups for each tier.

- For each virtual machine server, assign its network interface to the appropriate application security group.

For each virtual machine server, assign its network interface to the appropriate application security group.

- Create the network security group and security rules. Rule 1 : Set Priority to 100. Allow access from the internet to the web servers machines from HTTP port 80 and HTTPS port 443. Rule 1 has the lowest priority value, so it has precedence over the other rules in the group. Customer access to our online catalog is paramount in our design. Rule 2 : Set Priority to 110. Allow access from the web servers to application servers over SQL port 1433. Rule 3 : Set Priority to 120. Deny access from anywhere to application server machines on the HTTP and HTTPS ports. The combination of Rule 2 and Rule 3 ensures that only our web servers can access our database servers. This security configuration protects our inventory databases from outside attack.

Create the network security group and security rules.

- Rule 1 : Set Priority to 100. Allow access from the internet to the web servers machines from HTTP port 80 and HTTPS port 443. Rule 1 has the lowest priority value, so it has precedence over the other rules in the group. Customer access to our online catalog is paramount in our design.

Rule 1 : Set Priority to 100. Allow access from the internet to the web servers machines from HTTP port 80 and HTTPS port 443.

Rule 1 has the lowest priority value, so it has precedence over the other rules in the group. Customer access to our online catalog is paramount in our design.

- Rule 2 : Set Priority to 110. Allow access from the web servers to application servers over SQL port 1433.

Rule 2 : Set Priority to 110. Allow access from the web servers to application servers over SQL port 1433.

- Rule 3 : Set Priority to 120. Deny access from anywhere to application server machines on the HTTP and HTTPS ports. The combination of Rule 2 and Rule 3 ensures that only our web servers can access our database servers. This security configuration protects our inventory databases from outside attack.

Rule 3 : Set Priority to 120. Deny access from anywhere to application server machines on the HTTP and HTTPS ports.

The combination of Rule 2 and Rule 3 ensures that only our web servers can access our database servers. This security configuration protects our inventory databases from outside attack.

Things to consider when using application security groups

There are several advantages to implementing application security groups in your virtual networks.

- Consider IP address maintenance . When you control network traffic by using application security groups, you don't need to configure inbound and outbound traffic for specific IP addresses. If you have many virtual machines in your configuration, it can be difficult to specify all of the affected IP addresses. As you maintain your configuration, the number of your servers can change. These changes can require you to modify how you support different IP addresses in your security rules.

Consider IP address maintenance . When you control network traffic by using application security groups, you don't need to configure inbound and outbound traffic for specific IP addresses. If you have many virtual machines in your configuration, it can be difficult to specify all of the affected IP addresses. As you maintain your configuration, the number of your servers can change. These changes can require you to modify how you support different IP addresses in your security rules.

- Consider no subnets . By organizing your virtual machines into application security groups, you don't need to also distribute your servers across specific subnets. You can arrange your servers by application and purpose to achieve logical groupings.

Consider no subnets . By organizing your virtual machines into application security groups, you don't need to also distribute your servers across specific subnets. You can arrange your servers by application and purpose to achieve logical groupings.

- Consider simplified rules . Application security groups help to eliminate the need for multiple rule sets. You don't need to create a separate rule for each virtual machine. You can dynamically apply new rules to designated application security groups. New security rules are automatically applied to all the virtual machines in the specified application security group.

Consider simplified rules . Application security groups help to eliminate the need for multiple rule sets. You don't need to create a separate rule for each virtual machine. You can dynamically apply new rules to designated application security groups. New security rules are automatically applied to all the virtual machines in the specified application security group.

- Consider workload support . A configuration that implements application security groups is easy to maintain and understand because the organization is based on workload usage. Application security groups provide logical arrangements for your applications, services, data storage, and workloads.

Consider workload support . A configuration that implements application security groups is easy to maintain and understand because the organization is based on workload usage. Application security groups provide logical arrangements for your applications, services, data storage, and workloads.

- Consider service tags . Service Tags represent a group of IP address prefixes from a specific Azure service. They help minimize the complexity of frequent updates on network security rules. While service tags are used to simplify the management of IP addresses for Azure services, ASGs are used to group VMs and manage network security policies based on those groups.

Consider service tags . Service Tags represent a group of IP address prefixes from a specific Azure service. They help minimize the complexity of frequent updates on network security rules. While service tags are used to simplify the management of IP addresses for Azure services, ASGs are used to group VMs and manage network security policies based on those groups.

Unit 3.2.7 - Exercise - Implement virtual networking

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-network-security-groups/7-simulation-create-network-groups

Exercise - Implement virtual networking

Lab scenario

Your organization wants to ensure that access to virtual machines is restricted. As the Azure Administrator, you need to:

- Create and configure network security groups.

- Associate network security groups to virtual machines.

- Deny and allow access to the virtual machines by using network security groups.

Architecture diagram

Job skills

- Create a virtual network with subnets using the portal.

- Create a virtual network and subnets using a template.

- Create and configure communication between an Application Security Group and a Network Security Group.

- Configure public and private Azure DNS zones. (optional)

Important

Estimated time: 50 minutes.

To complete this exercise, you need an Azure subscription .

Launch the exercise, and follow the instructions. When finished, be sure to return to this page so you can continue learning.

Unit 3.2.8 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-network-security-groups/8-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Your company is migrating several sites to Azure. You're responsible for implementing network security groups and designing effective security rules to control network traffic. You need to ensure that virtual machine networking and Azure services networking are both secure.

- The infrastructure team has two network security group security rules for inbound traffic to the back-end web servers. There's an allow rule with a priority of 200, and a deny rule with a priority of 150.

The infrastructure team has two network security group security rules for inbound traffic to the back-end web servers. There's an allow rule with a priority of 200, and a deny rule with a priority of 150.

- The IT team wants to apply service tags for the virtual machine IP addresses.

The IT team wants to apply service tags for the virtual machine IP addresses.

- You're exploring how to use default rules to apply security to inbound traffic from virtual machines within your virtual network.

You're exploring how to use default rules to apply security to inbound traffic from virtual machines within your virtual network.

Answer the following questions

Choose the best response for each question.

Unit 3.2.9 - Summary and resources

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-network-security-groups/9-summary-resources

Summary and resources

In this module, you learned about network security groups (NSGs) in Azure. NSGs are used to limit network traffic to resources in your virtual network by containing a list of security rules. You can associate NSGs with subnets or network interfaces and define rules to control inbound and outbound traffic.

You also learned how NSG rules are evaluated and processed. Lastly, you learned how application security groups, allow for grouping virtual machines based on workload.

The main takeaways from this module are:

- Network security groups are essential for controlling network traffic in Azure virtual networks.

Network security groups are essential for controlling network traffic in Azure virtual networks.

- NSG rules are evaluated and processed based on priority and can be created for subnets and network interfaces.

NSG rules are evaluated and processed based on priority and can be created for subnets and network interfaces.

- Effective NSG rules can be achieved by considering rule precedence, intra-subnet traffic, and managing rule priority.

Effective NSG rules can be achieved by considering rule precedence, intra-subnet traffic, and managing rule priority.

- Application security groups provide an application-centric view of infrastructure and simplify rule management.

Application security groups provide an application-centric view of infrastructure and simplify rule management.

Learn more with Copilot

Copilot can assist you in designing Azure infrastructure solutions. Copilot can compare, recommend, explain, and research products and services where you need more information. Open a Microsoft Edge browser and choose Copilot (top right) or navigate to copilot.microsoft.com. Take a few minutes to try these prompts and extend your learning with Copilot.

- What is the difference between an Azure network security group and an application security group? Provide usage examples.

What is the difference between an Azure network security group and an application security group? Provide usage examples.

- Can you explain NSG rules in detail?

Can you explain NSG rules in detail?

- How can I troubleshoot network security group rules?

How can I troubleshoot network security group rules?

Learn more with documentation

- Read about network security groups . This article describes the properties of a network security group rule, the default security rules that are applied, and the rule properties that you can modify.

Read about network security groups . This article describes the properties of a network security group rule, the default security rules that are applied, and the rule properties that you can modify.

- Filter network traffic with network security groups in the Azure portal . Learn how to create a network security group and an application security group.

Filter network traffic with network security groups in the Azure portal . Learn how to create a network security group and an application security group.

- Create, change, or delete a network security group . Learn how to work with network and application security groups.

Create, change, or delete a network security group . Learn how to work with network and application security groups.

- Application security groups . Learn about application security groups and traffic control with rules.

Application security groups . Learn about application security groups and traffic control with rules.

Learn more with self-paced training

- Secure and isolate access to Azure resources with network security groups and service endpoints (sandbox) . Learn how to secure your virtual machines and Azure services from unauthorized network access.

Secure and isolate access to Azure resources with network security groups and service endpoints (sandbox) . Learn how to secure your virtual machines and Azure services from unauthorized network access.

- Filter network traffic with a network security group using the Azure portal . Learn how to create, configure, and apply NSGs for improved network security.

Filter network traffic with a network security group using the Azure portal . Learn how to create, configure, and apply NSGs for improved network security.

LP 3 M3 - Host your domain on Azure DNS

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/host-domain-azure-dns/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 3.3.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/host-domain-azure-dns/1-introduction

Introduction

Azure DNS lets you host your Domain Name System (DNS) records for your domains on Azure infrastructure. With Azure DNS, you can use the same credentials, APIs, tools, and billing as your other Azure services.

Let's say that your company recently bought the custom domain name wideworldimporters.com from a third-party domain-name registrar. The domain name is for a new website that your organization plans to launch. You need a hosting service for DNS domains. This hosting service would resolve the wideworldimporters.com domain to your web server's IP address.

You're already using Azure to build your website, so you decide to use Azure DNS to manage your domain.

This module shows you how to configure Azure DNS to host your domain. You also see how to add an alias and other DNS records to resolve your domain name to a website.

Learning objectives

In this module, you will:

- Configure Azure DNS to host your domain.

Prerequisites

- Knowledge of networking concepts like name resolution and IP addresses.

Unit 3.3.2 - What is Azure DNS?

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/host-domain-azure-dns/2-what-is-azure-dns

What is Azure DNS?

Azure DNS is a hosting service for Domain Name System (DNS) domains that provides name resolution by using Microsoft Azure infrastructure.

In this unit, you learn what DNS is and how it works. You also learn about Azure DNS and why you'd use it.

What is DNS?

DNS, or the Domain Name System, is a protocol within the TCP/IP standard. DNS serves an essential role of translating the human-readable domain names—for example: www.wideworldimports.com —into a known IP address. IP addresses enable computers and network devices to identify and route requests among themselves.

www.wideworldimports.com

DNS uses a global directory hosted on servers around the world. Microsoft is part of the network that provides a DNS service through Azure DNS.

A DNS server is also known as a DNS name server, or just a name server.

How does DNS work?

A DNS server carries out one of two primary functions:

- Maintains a local cache of recently accessed or used domain names and their IP addresses. This cache provides a faster response to a local domain lookup request. If the DNS server can't find the requested domain, it passes the request to another DNS server. This process repeats at each DNS server until either a match is made or the search times out.

- Maintains the key-value pair database of IP addresses and any host or subdomain over which the DNS server has authority. This function is often associated with mail, web, and other internet domain services.

DNS server assignment

In order for a computer, server, or other network-enabled device to access web-based resources, it must reference a DNS server.

When you connect by using your on-premises network, the DNS settings come from your server. When you connect by using an external location like a hotel, the DNS settings come from the internet service provider (ISP).

Domain lookup requests

Here's a simplified overview of the process a DNS server uses when it resolves a domain-name lookup request:

- If the domain name is stored in the short-term cache, the DNS server resolves the domain request.

- If the domain isn't in the cache, it contacts one or more DNS servers on the web to see if they have a match. When a match is found, the DNS server updates the local cache and resolves the request.

- If the domain isn't found after a reasonable number of DNS checks, the DNS server responds with a domain cannot be found error.

IPv4 and IPv6

Every computer, server, or network-enabled device on your network has an IP address. An IP address is unique within your domain. There are two standards of IP address: IPv4 and IPv6.

- IPv4 is composed of four sets of numbers, in the range 0 to 255, each separated by a dot; for example: 127.0.0.1. Today, IPv4 is the most commonly used standard. Yet, with the increase in IoT devices, the IPv4 standard will eventually be unable to keep up.

IPv4 is composed of four sets of numbers, in the range 0 to 255, each separated by a dot; for example: 127.0.0.1. Today, IPv4 is the most commonly used standard. Yet, with the increase in IoT devices, the IPv4 standard will eventually be unable to keep up.

- IPv6 is a relatively new standard and is intended to eventually replace IPv4. It consists of eight groups of hexadecimal numbers, each separated by a colon; for example: fe80:11a1:ac15:e9gf:e884:edb0:ddee:fea3.

IPv6 is a relatively new standard and is intended to eventually replace IPv4. It consists of eight groups of hexadecimal numbers, each separated by a colon; for example: fe80:11a1:ac15:e9gf:e884:edb0:ddee:fea3.

Many network devices are now provisioned with both an IPv4 and an IPv6 address. The DNS name server can resolve domain names to both IPv4 and IPv6 addresses.

DNS settings for your domain

Whether a third-party host your DNS server or you manage it in-house, you need to configure it for each host type you're using. Host types include web, email, or other services you're using.

As the administrator for your company, you want to set up a DNS server by using Azure DNS. In this instance, the DNS server acts as a start of authority (SOA) for your domain.

DNS record types

Configuration information for your DNS server is stored as a file within a zone on your DNS server. Each file is called a record. The following record types are the most commonly created and used:

- A is the host record, and is the most common type of DNS record. It maps the domain or host name to the IP address.

- CNAME is a Canonical Name record that's used to create an alias from one domain name to another domain name. If you had different domain names that all accessed the same website, you'd use CNAME.

- MX is the mail exchange record. It maps mail requests to your mail server, whether hosted on-premises or in the cloud.

- TXT is the text record. It's used to associate text strings with a domain name. Azure and Microsoft 365 use TXT records to verify domain ownership.

Additionally, there are the following record types:

- Wildcards

- CAA (certificate authority)

- NS (name server)

- SOA (start of authority)

- SPF (sender policy framework)

- SRV (server locations)

The SOA and NS records are created automatically when you create a DNS zone by using Azure DNS.

Record sets

Some record types support the concept of record sets, or resource record sets. A record set allows for multiple resources to be defined in a single record. For example, here's an A record that has one domain with two IP addresses:

www.wideworldimports.com. 3600 IN A 127.0.0.1

www.wideworldimports.com. 3600 IN A 127.0.0.2

www.wideworldimports.com. 3600 IN A 127.0.0.1

www.wideworldimports.com. 3600 IN A 127.0.0.2

SOA and CNAME records can't contain record sets.

What is Azure DNS?

Azure DNS allows you to host and manage your domains by using a globally distributed name-server infrastructure. It allows you to manage all of your domains by using your existing Azure credentials.

Azure DNS acts as the SOA for the domain.

You can't use Azure DNS to register a domain name; you need to register it by using a third-party domain registrar.

Why use Azure DNS to host your domain?

Azure DNS is built on the Azure Resource Manager service, which offers the following benefits:

- Improved security

- Ease of use

- Private DNS domains

- Alias record sets

At this time, Azure DNS doesn't support Domain Name System Security Extensions. If you require this security extension, you should host those portions of your domain with a third-party provider.

Security features

Azure DNS provides the following security features:

- Activity logs, which let you track changes to a resource and pinpoint where faults occurred.

- Resource locking, which gives you a greater level of control to restrict or remove access to resource groups, subscriptions, or any Azure resources.

Ease of use

Azure DNS can manage DNS records for your Azure services and provide DNS for your external resources. Azure DNS uses the same Azure credentials, support contract, and billing as your other Azure services.

You can manage your domains and records by using the Azure portal, Azure PowerShell cmdlets, or the Azure CLI. Applications that require automated DNS management can integrate with the service by using the REST API and software development kit (SDKs).

Private domains

Azure DNS handles translating external domain names to IP addresses. Azure DNS lets you create private zones. These zones provide name resolution for virtual machines (VMs) within a virtual network and between virtual networks without having to create a custom DNS solution. Private zones allow you to use your own custom domain names rather than the Azure-provided names.

To publish a private DNS zone to your virtual network, you specify the list of virtual networks that are allowed to resolve records within the zone.

Private DNS zones have the following benefits:

- DNS zones are supported as part of the Azure infrastructure, so there's no need to invest in a DNS solution.

- All DNS record types are supported: A, CNAME, TXT, MX, SOA, AAAA, PTR, and SRV.

- Host names for VMs in your virtual network are automatically maintained.

- Split-horizon DNS support allows the same domain name to exist in both private and public zones. It resolves to the correct one based on the originating request location.

Alias record sets

Alias records sets can point to an Azure resource. For example, you can set up an alias record to direct traffic to an Azure public IP address, an Azure Traffic Manager profile, or an Azure Content Delivery Network endpoint.

The alias record set is supported in the following DNS record types:

- A

- AAAA

- CNAME

Check your knowledge

Unit 3.3.3 - Configure Azure DNS to host your domain

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/host-domain-azure-dns/3-configure-azure-dns-host-domain

Configure Azure DNS to host your domain

The new company website is in final testing. You're working on the plan to deploy the wideworldimports.com domain by using Azure DNS. You need to understand what steps are involved.

In this unit, you learn how to:

- Create and configure a DNS zone for your domain by using Azure DNS.

- Understand how to link your domain to an Azure DNS zone.

- Create and configure a private DNS zone.

Configure a public DNS zone

You use a DNS zone to host the DNS records for a domain, such as wideworldimports.com.

Step 1: Create a DNS zone in Azure

You used a third-party domain-name registrar to register the wideworldimports.com domain. The domain doesn't point to your organization's website yet.

To host the domain name with Azure DNS, you first need to create a DNS zone for that domain. A DNS zone holds all the DNS entries for your domain.

When creating a DNS zone, you need to supply the following details:

- Subscription : The subscription to be used.

Subscription : The subscription to be used.

- Resource group : The name of the resource group to hold your domains. If one doesn't exist, create one to allow for better control and management.

Resource group : The name of the resource group to hold your domains. If one doesn't exist, create one to allow for better control and management.

- Name : Your domain name, which in this case is wideworldimports.com.

Name : Your domain name, which in this case is wideworldimports.com.

- Resource group location : The location defaults to the location of the resource group.

Resource group location : The location defaults to the location of the resource group.

Step 2: Get your Azure DNS name servers

After you create a DNS zone for the domain, you need to get the name server details from the name servers (NS) record. You use these details to update your domain registrar's information and point to the Azure DNS zone.

Step 3: Update the domain registrar setting

As the domain owner, you need to sign in to the domain-management application provided by your domain registrar. In the management application, edit the NS record and change the NS details to match your Azure DNS name server details.

Changing the NS details is called domain delegation . When you delegate the domain, you must use all four name servers provided by Azure DNS.

Step 4: Verify delegation of domain name services

The next step is to verify that the delegated domain now points to the Azure DNS zone you created for the domain. This process can take as few as 10 minutes, but might take longer.

To verify the success of the domain delegation, query the start of authority (SOA) record. The SOA record is automatically created when the Azure DNS zone is set up. You can verify the SOA record using a tool like nslookup.

The SOA record represents your domain and becomes the reference point when other DNS servers are searching for your domain on the internet.

To verify the delegation, use nslookup like this:

nslookup -type=SOA wideworldimports.com

Step 5: Configure your custom DNS settings

The domain name is wideworldimports.com. When it's used in a browser, the domain resolves to your website. But what if you want to add in web servers or load balancers? These resources need to have their own custom settings in the DNS zone, either as an A record or a CNAME.

A record

Each A record requires the following details:

- Name : The name of the custom domain, for example webserver1 .

- Type : In this instance, it's A.

- TTL : Represents the "time-to-live" as a whole unit, where 1 is one second. This value indicates how long the A record lives in a DNS cache before it expires.

- IP address : The IP address of the server to which this A record should resolve.

CNAME record

The CNAME is the canonical name, or the alias for an A record. Use CNAME when you have different domain names that all access the same website. For example, you might need a CNAME in the wideworldimports zone if you want both www.wideworldimports.com and wideworldimports.com to resolve to the same IP address.

You'd create the CNAME record in the wideworldimports zone with the following information:

- NAME: www

- TTL: 600 seconds

- Record type: CNAME

If you exposed a web function, you'd create a CNAME record that resolves to the Azure function.

Configure a private DNS zone

Another type of DNS zone that you can configure and host in Azure is a private DNS zone. Private DNS zones aren't visible on the Internet, and don't require that you use a domain registrar. You can use private DNS zones to assign DNS names to virtual machines (VMs) in your Azure virtual networks.

Step 1: Create a private DNS zone

In the Azure portal, search for private DNS zones . To create the private zone, you need enter a resource group and the name of the zone. For example, the name might be something like private.wideworldimports.com.

Step 2: Identify virtual networks

Let's assume that your organization already created your VMs and virtual networks in a production environment. Identify the virtual networks associated with VMs that need name-resolution support. To link the virtual networks to the private zone, you need the virtual network names.

Step 3: Link your virtual network to a private DNS zone

To link the private DNS zone to a virtual network, you create a virtual network link. In the Azure portal, go to the private zone, and select Virtual network links .

Select Add to pick the virtual network you want to link to the private zone.

You add a virtual network link record for each virtual network that needs private name-resolution support.

In the next unit, you learn how to create a public DNS zone.

Unit 3.3.4 - Exercise - Create a DNS zone and an A record by using Azure DNS

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/host-domain-azure-dns/4-exercise-create-dns-zone-a-record

Exercise - Create a DNS zone and an A record by using Azure DNS

In the previous unit, we described setting up and configuring the wideworldimports.com domain to point to your Azure hosting on Azure DNS.

In this unit, you'll:

- Set up an Azure DNS and create a public DNS zone.

- Create an A record.

- Verify that the A record resolves to an IP address.

Note

This exercise is optional. If you want to complete this exercise, you'll need to create an Azure subscription before you begin. If you don't have an Azure account or you don't want to create one at this time, you can read through the instructions so you understand the information that's being presented.

Note

You need to use a resource group to complete the steps in this exercise. You can use a resource group that you already created, or you can create a new resource group specifically for this exercise. If you choose to create a new resource group, that will make it easier to clean up any resources that you create as you complete the exercise. If you don't have an existing resource group or you want to create a new one specifically for this exercise, you can follow the steps in Use the Azure portal and Azure Resource Manager to manage resource groups to create a resource group by using the Azure portal, or you can follow the steps in Manage Azure resource groups by using Azure CLI to create a resource group by using the the Azure CLI.

Create a DNS zone in Azure DNS

Before you can host the wideworldimports.com domain on your servers, you need to create a DNS zone. The DNS zone holds all the configuration records associated with your domain.

To create your DNS zone:

- Sign in to the Azure portal with the account you used to activate the sandbox.

Sign in to the Azure portal with the account you used to activate the sandbox.

- On the Azure home page, under Azure services , select Create a resource . The Create a resource pane appears.

On the Azure home page, under Azure services , select Create a resource . The Create a resource pane appears.

- In the Search services and marketplace search box, search for and select DNS zone by Microsoft. The DNS zone pane appears.

In the Search services and marketplace search box, search for and select DNS zone by Microsoft. The DNS zone pane appears.

- Select Create > DNS zone . The Create DNS zone pane appears.

Select Create > DNS zone .

The Create DNS zone pane appears.

- On the Basics tab, enter the following values for each setting. Setting Value Project details Subscription Choose your subscription Resource group From the dropdown list, select the resource group you want to use for this exercise. Instance details Name The name needs to be unique in the sandbox. Use wideworldimportsXXXX.com , and replace the "Xs" with letters or numbers.

On the Basics tab, enter the following values for each setting.

Setting

Value

Project details

Subscription

Choose your subscription

Resource group

From the dropdown list, select the resource group you want to use for this exercise.

Instance details

Name

The name needs to be unique in the sandbox. Use wideworldimportsXXXX.com , and replace the "Xs" with letters or numbers.

wideworldimportsXXXX.com

- Select Review + create .

Select Review + create .

- After validation passes, select Create . It takes a few minutes to create the DNS zone.

After validation passes, select Create . It takes a few minutes to create the DNS zone.

- When deployment is complete, select Go to resource . The Overview pane for your DNS zone appears.

When deployment is complete, select Go to resource . The Overview pane for your DNS zone appears.

- Select Record Sets from the top menu bar. By default, the NS and SOA record sets are automatically created whenever a DNS zone is created, and automatically deleted whenever a DNS zone deleted. The NS record set defines the Azure DNS namespaces and contains the four Azure DNS records. You use all four records when you update the registrar. The SOA record represents your domain, and is used when other DNS servers are searching for your domain.

Select Record Sets from the top menu bar.

By default, the NS and SOA record sets are automatically created whenever a DNS zone is created, and automatically deleted whenever a DNS zone deleted. The NS record set defines the Azure DNS namespaces and contains the four Azure DNS records. You use all four records when you update the registrar.

The SOA record represents your domain, and is used when other DNS servers are searching for your domain.

- Make a note of the NS record values. You need them in the next section.

Make a note of the NS record values. You need them in the next section.

Create a DNS record

Now that the DNS zone exists, you need to create the necessary records to support the domain.

The primary record set to create is the A record. The A record set is used to point traffic from a logical domain name to the hosting server's IP address. An A record set can have multiple records. In a record set, the domain name remains constant, while the IP addresses differ.

- If you're not already on the Record Sets screen, then open the DNS zone pane for wideworldimportsXXXX.com . In the top menu bar, select Record sets .

If you're not already on the Record Sets screen, then open the DNS zone pane for wideworldimportsXXXX.com . In the top menu bar, select Record sets .

- On the Record Sets pane, select + Add in the top menu bar.

On the Record Sets pane, select + Add in the top menu bar.

- Select Add at the top of the Record sets page. The Add record set pane appears.

Select Add at the top of the Record sets page.

The Add record set pane appears.

- Enter the following values for each setting. Setting Value Description Name www The host name that you want to resolve to an IP address. Type A The A record is the most commonly used. If you're using IPv6, select the AAAA type. Alias record set No This setting can only be applied to A, AAAA, and CNAME record types. TTL 1 The time to live, which specifies the period of time each DNS server caches the resolution before being purged. TTL unit Hours This value can be seconds, minutes, hours, days, or weeks. Here, you're selecting hours. IP Address 10.10.10.10 The IP address the record name resolves to. In a real-world scenario, you'd enter the public IP address for your web server.

Enter the following values for each setting.

Setting

Value

Description

Name

www

The host name that you want to resolve to an IP address.

Type

A

The A record is the most commonly used. If you're using IPv6, select the AAAA type.

Alias record set

No

This setting can only be applied to A, AAAA, and CNAME record types.

TTL

1

The time to live, which specifies the period of time each DNS server caches the resolution before being purged.

TTL unit

Hours

This value can be seconds, minutes, hours, days, or weeks. Here, you're selecting hours.

IP Address

10.10.10.10

The IP address the record name resolves to. In a real-world scenario, you'd enter the public IP address for your web server.

- Select Add to add the record to your zone.

Select Add to add the record to your zone.

It's possible to have more than one IP address set up for your web server. In that case, you add all the associated IP addresses as records in the A record set. After the record set is created, you can update it with more IP addresses.

Verify your global Azure DNS

In a real-world scenario, after you create the public DNS zone, you update the NS records of the domain-name registrar to delegate the domain to Azure.

Even though we don't have a registered domain, it's still possible to verify that the DNS zone works as expected by using the nslookup tool.

nslookup

Use nslookup to verify the configuration

Here's how to use nslookup to verify the DNS zone configuration.

nslookup

- Use Cloud Shell to run the following command. Replace the DNS zone name with the zone you created, and replace <name server address> with one of the NS values you copied after you created the DNS zone. nslookup www.wideworldimportsXXXX.com <name server address> The command should look something like the following example: nslookup www.wideworldimportsXXXX.com ns1-04.azure-dns.com

Use Cloud Shell to run the following command. Replace the DNS zone name with the zone you created, and replace <name server address> with one of the NS values you copied after you created the DNS zone.

<name server address>

nslookup www.wideworldimportsXXXX.com <name server address>

The command should look something like the following example:

nslookup www.wideworldimportsXXXX.com ns1-04.azure-dns.com

- You should see that your host name www.wideworldimportsXXXX.com resolves to 10.10.10.10.

You should see that your host name www.wideworldimportsXXXX.com resolves to 10.10.10.10.

www.wideworldimportsXXXX.com

Congratulations! You successfully set up a DNS zone and created an A record.

Unit 3.3.5 - Dynamically resolve resource name by using alias record

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/host-domain-azure-dns/5-resolve-name-alias-record

Dynamically resolve resource name by using alias record

In the previous exercise, you successfully delegated the domain from the domain registrar to your Azure DNS and configured an A record to link the domain to your web server.

The next phase of the deployment is to improve resiliency by using a load balancer. Load balancers distribute inbound data requests and traffic across one or more servers. They reduce the load on any one server and improve performance. This technology is well established. You can use it throughout your on-premises network.

You know that the A record and CNAME record don't support direct connection to Azure resources like your load balancers. You're tasked with finding out how to link the apex domain with a load balancer.

What is an apex domain?

The apex domain is your domain's highest level. In our case, that's wideworldimports.com. The apex domain is also sometimes referred to as the zone apex or root apex .

The @ symbol often represents the apex domain in your DNS zone records.

If you check the DNS zone for wideworldimports.com, you see that there are two apex domain records: NS and SOA. The NS and SOA records are automatically created when you created the DNS zone.

CNAME records that you might need for an Azure Traffic Manager profile or Azure Content Delivery Network endpoints aren't supported at the zone apex level. However, other alias records are supported at the zone apex level.

What are alias records?

Azure alias records enable a zone apex domain to reference other Azure resources from the DNS zone. You don't need to create complex redirection policies. You can also use an Azure alias to route all traffic through Traffic Manager.

The Azure alias record can point to the following Azure resources:

- A Traffic Manager profile

- Azure Content Delivery Network endpoints

- A public IP resource

- A front-door profile

Alias records provide lifecycle tracking of target resources, ensuring that changes to any target resource are automatically applied to the DNS zone. Alias records also provide support for load-balanced applications in the zone apex.

The alias record set supports the following DNS zone record types:

- A : The IPv4 domain name-mapping record.

- AAAA : The IPv6 domain name-mapping record.

- CNAME : The alias for your domain, which links to the A record.

Uses for alias records

The following are some of the advantages of using alias records:

- Prevents dangling DNS records : A dangling DNS record occurs when the DNS zone records aren't up to date with changes to IP addresses. Alias records prevent dangling references by tightly coupling the lifecycle of a DNS record with an Azure resource.

- Updates DNS record set automatically when IP addresses change : When the underlying IP address of a resource, service, or application is changed, the alias record ensures that any associated DNS records are automatically refreshed.

- Hosts load-balanced applications at the zone apex : Alias records allow for zone apex resource routing to Traffic Manager.

- Points zone apex to Azure Content Delivery Network endpoints : With alias records, you can now directly reference your Azure Content Delivery Network instance.

An alias record allows you to link the zone apex (wideworldimports.com) to a load balancer. It creates a link to the Azure resource rather than a direct IP-based connection. So, if the IP address of your load balancer changes, the zone apex record continues to work.

Unit 3.3.6 - Exercise - Create alias records for Azure DNS

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/host-domain-azure-dns/6-exercise-create-alias-records

Exercise - Create alias records for Azure DNS

Your new website's deployment was a huge success. Usage volumes are higher than anticipated. The single web server on which the website runs is showing signs of strain. Your organization wants to increase the number of servers and distribute the load using a load balancer.

You now know you can use an Azure alias record to provide a dynamic, automatically refreshing link between the zone apex and the load balancer.

In this unit, you'll:

- Set up a virtual network with two VMs and a load balancer.

- Learn how to configure an Azure alias at the zone apex to direct to the load balancer.

- Verify that the domain name resolves to one or either of the VMs on your virtual network.

Note

This exercise is optional. If you want to complete this exercise, you'll need to create an Azure subscription before you begin. If you don't have an Azure account or you don't want to create one at this time, you can read through the instructions so you understand the information that's being presented.

Set up a virtual network, load balancer, and VMs in Azure

When you manually create a virtual network, load balancer, and two VMs, it takes some time. To reduce this time, you can use a Bash setup script that's available on GitHub. Follow these instructions to create a test environment for your alias record.

- In Azure Cloud Shell, run the following setup script: git clone https://github.com/MicrosoftDocs/mslearn-host-domain-azure-dns.git

In Azure Cloud Shell, run the following setup script:

git clone https://github.com/MicrosoftDocs/mslearn-host-domain-azure-dns.git

- To run the setup script, run the following commands: cd mslearn-host-domain-azure-dns

chmod +x setup.sh

./setup.sh The setup script takes a few minutes to run. The script: Creates a network security group. Creates two network interface controllers (NICs) and two VMs. Creates a virtual network and assigns the VMs. Creates a public IP address and updates the configuration of the VMs. Creates a load balancer that references the VMs, including rules for the load balancer. Links the NICs to the load balancer. After the script completes, it shows you the public IP address for the load balancer. Copy the IP address to use it later.

To run the setup script, run the following commands:

cd mslearn-host-domain-azure-dns

chmod +x setup.sh

./setup.sh

cd mslearn-host-domain-azure-dns

chmod +x setup.sh

./setup.sh

The setup script takes a few minutes to run. The script:

- Creates a network security group.

- Creates two network interface controllers (NICs) and two VMs.

- Creates a virtual network and assigns the VMs.

- Creates a public IP address and updates the configuration of the VMs.

- Creates a load balancer that references the VMs, including rules for the load balancer.

- Links the NICs to the load balancer.

After the script completes, it shows you the public IP address for the load balancer. Copy the IP address to use it later.

Create an alias record in your zone apex

Now that you created a test environment, you're ready to set up the Azure alias record in your zone apex.

- In the Azure portal , select Resource groups . The Resource groups pane appears.

In the Azure portal , select Resource groups . The Resource groups pane appears.

- Select your resource group. The Resource group pane appears.

Select your resource group. The Resource group pane appears.

- In the list of resources, select the DNS zone you created in the previous exercise, wideworldimportsXXXX.com. The wideworldimportsXXXX.com DNS zone pane appears.

In the list of resources, select the DNS zone you created in the previous exercise, wideworldimportsXXXX.com. The wideworldimportsXXXX.com DNS zone pane appears.

- In the menu bar, select + Record set . The Add record set pane appears.

In the menu bar, select + Record set . The Add record set pane appears.

- Enter the following values for each setting to create an alias record. Setting Value Name Leave the name blank. Blank indicates the DNS zone for wideworldimportsXXXX.com. Type A. Even though we're creating an alias, the base record type must still be either A, AAAA, or CNAME. Alias record set Yes Alias type Azure resource Azure resource From the list of resources, select myPublicIP . It can take up to 15 minutes for the deployments to propagate. If this resource isn't listed, wait several minutes, refresh the portal, and try again.

Enter the following values for each setting to create an alias record.

Setting

Value

Name

Leave the name blank. Blank indicates the DNS zone for wideworldimportsXXXX.com.

Type

A. Even though we're creating an alias, the base record type must still be either A, AAAA, or CNAME.

Alias record set

Yes

Alias type

Azure resource

From the list of resources, select myPublicIP . It can take up to 15 minutes for the deployments to propagate. If this resource isn't listed, wait several minutes, refresh the portal, and try again.

- Select OK to add the record to your zone.

Select OK to add the record to your zone.

When the new alias record is created, it should look something like this:

Verify that the alias resolves to the load balancer

Now, you need to verify that the alias record is set up correctly. In a real-world scenario, you'd have an actual domain, and would complete the domain delegation to Azure DNS. You'd use the registered domain name for this exercise. Because this unit assumes there's no registered domain, you use the public IP address.

- In the Azure portal, go to the resource group, select myPublicIP , then select the Copy icon next to the IP address.

In the Azure portal, go to the resource group, select myPublicIP , then select the Copy icon next to the IP address.

- In a web browser, paste the Public IP address as the URL.

In a web browser, paste the Public IP address as the URL.

- You see a basic web page that shows the name of the virtual machine (VM) to which the load balancer sent the request.

You see a basic web page that shows the name of the virtual machine (VM) to which the load balancer sent the request.

Unit 3.3.7 - Summary

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/host-domain-azure-dns/7-summary

Summary

Your company recently bought the custom domain name wideworldimporters.com from a third-party domain-name registrar. The domain name is for a new website your organization plans to launch. You need a hosting service for DNS domains. This hosting service would resolve the wideworldimporters.com domain to your Azure-based web server's IP address.

Your company wanted to manage all their infrastructure and related domain name information in one place. You saw how easy it was to manage Domain Name System (DNS) information by using an Azure DNS zone. First, you created an Azure DNS zone, and then you updated the NS records at your domain registrar to point at it.

You learned the uses of the different record sets, A, AAAA, CNAME, NS, and SOA. You also learned how you can use Azure aliases to override the static A/AAAA/CNAME record to provide a dynamic reference to your resources. Using an Azure DNS zone improved your company's administration of resources, because your staff only needed one place to manage DNS-related tasks.

The Azure DNS zone allows better control and integration with your Azure resources. It's possible to achieve some of the more basic record set functions by using the domain registrar's management console. However, linking to any of your Azure resources becomes difficult or impossible without a high degree of complex redirection.

By using an Azure DNS zone to host your domain, your organization benefits by having all the resources managed through a single, common interface. This solution provides better integration with existing Azure resources, improved security, and monitoring tools.

Important

In the optional exercises for this module, you created resources by using your own Azure subscription. Clean up these resources so that you won't continue to be charged for them.

Learn more

- Quickstart: Create an Azure private DNS zone by using the Azure portal

- Overview of DNS zones and records

LP 3 M4 - Configure Azure Virtual Network peering

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-vnet-peering/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 3.4.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-vnet-peering/1-introduction

Introduction

Azure Virtual Network peering lets you connect virtual networks in the same or different regions. Azure Virtual Network peering provides secure communication between resources in the peered networks.

Suppose your engineering company is migrating services to Azure. The company is deploying services into separate Azure virtual networks. Private connectivity between the virtual networks isn't yet configured. Several business units identified services in the virtual networks that need to communicate with each other.

You're responsible for implementing an Azure Virtual Network peering solution and enabling connectivity between the virtual networks. Two of your strategy goals include preventing exposure of the services to the internet, and keeping the integration as simple as possible. Your solution should address transit and connectivity concerns.

The goal of this module is to successfully implement Azure Virtual Network peering.

Learning objectives

In this module, you learn how to:

- Identify usage cases and product features of Azure Virtual Network peering.

- Configure your network to implement Azure VPN Gateway for transit connectivity.

- Extend peering by using a hub and spoke network with user-defined routes and service chaining.

Skills measured

The content in the module helps you prepare for Exam AZ-104: Microsoft Azure Administrator .

Prerequisites

- Basic understanding of cloud networking including virtual networks and virtual machines.

Basic understanding of cloud networking including virtual networks and virtual machines.

- Familiarity with the command line connectivity testing tools.

Familiarity with the command line connectivity testing tools.

Unit 3.4.2 - Determine Azure Virtual Network peering uses

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-vnet-peering/2-determine-uses

Determine Azure Virtual Network peering uses

Perhaps the simplest and quickest way to connect your virtual networks is to use Azure Virtual Network peering. Virtual Network peering enables you to seamlessly connect two Azure virtual networks. After the networks are peered, the two virtual networks operate as a single network, for connectivity purposes.

Things to know about Azure Virtual Network peering

Let's examine some prominent characteristics of Azure Virtual Network peering.

- There are two types of Azure Virtual Network peering: regional and global .

There are two types of Azure Virtual Network peering: regional and global .

- Regional virtual network peering connects Azure virtual networks that exist in the same region.

Regional virtual network peering connects Azure virtual networks that exist in the same region.

- Global virtual network peering connects Azure virtual networks that exist in different regions.

Global virtual network peering connects Azure virtual networks that exist in different regions.

- You can create a regional peering of virtual networks in the same Azure public cloud region, or in the same China cloud region, or in the same Microsoft Azure Government cloud region.

You can create a regional peering of virtual networks in the same Azure public cloud region, or in the same China cloud region, or in the same Microsoft Azure Government cloud region.

- You can create a global peering of virtual networks in any Azure public cloud region, or in any China cloud region.

You can create a global peering of virtual networks in any Azure public cloud region, or in any China cloud region.

- Global peering of virtual networks in different Azure Government cloud regions isn't permitted.

Global peering of virtual networks in different Azure Government cloud regions isn't permitted.

- After you create a peering between virtual networks, the individual virtual networks are still managed as separate resources.

After you create a peering between virtual networks, the individual virtual networks are still managed as separate resources.

- Virtual networks can be peered across subscriptions and tenants.

Virtual networks can be peered across subscriptions and tenants.

Things to consider when using Azure Virtual Network peering

Consider the benefits of using Azure Virtual Network peering.

Benefit

Description

Private network connections

When you implement Azure Virtual Network peering, network traffic between peered virtual networks is private. Traffic between the virtual networks is kept on the Microsoft Azure backbone network. No public internet, gateways, or encryption is required in the communication between the virtual networks.

Strong performance

Because Azure Virtual Network peering utilizes the Azure infrastructure, you gain a low-latency, high-bandwidth connection between resources in different virtual networks.

Simplified communication

Azure Virtual Network peering lets resources in one virtual network communicate with resources in a different virtual network, after the virtual networks are peered.

Seamless data transfer

You can create an Azure Virtual Network peering configuration to transfer data across Azure subscriptions, deployment models, and across Azure regions.

No resource disruptions

Azure Virtual Network peering doesn't require downtime for resources in either virtual network when creating the peering, or after the peering is created.

Things to know about peering requirements and limitations

While VNet peering provides many benefits, there are important constraints to understand.

Requirements/Limitations

Description

Nonoverlapping address spaces

Peered virtual networks must have non-overlapping IP address spaces. Peering creation fails if address ranges overlap.

Address space modification restrictions

If you want to change a VNet's address range, you need to delete the peering first, update the address space, and then set up the peering again.

Basic Load Balancer limitations

Resources in one VNet can’t communicate with Basic Internal Load Balancer IPs in VNets peered across regions. Use the Standard Load Balancer for cross-region connections.

DNS resolution boundaries

Azure's built-in name resolution does not work across peered VNets. Configure Azure Private DNS zones or custom DNS servers for cross-VNet name resolution.

Unit 3.4.3 - Determine gateway transit and connectivity

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-vnet-peering/3-determine-gateway-transit-connectivity

Determine gateway transit and connectivity

When virtual networks are peered, you can configure Azure VPN Gateway in the peered virtual network as a transit point . In this scenario, a peered virtual network uses the remote VPN gateway to gain access to other resources.

Transit and connectivity use

Consider a scenario where three virtual networks in the same region are connected by virtual network peering. Virtual network A and virtual network B are each peered with a hub virtual network. The hub virtual network contains several resources, including a gateway subnet and an Azure VPN gateway. The VPN gateway is configured to allow VPN gateway transit. Virtual network B accesses resources in the hub, including the gateway subnet, by using a remote VPN gateway.

The Azure portal provides four key settings when configuring virtual network peering.

- Traffic to remote virtual network . Controls whether traffic flows from this VNet to the remote VNet.

Traffic to remote virtual network . Controls whether traffic flows from this VNet to the remote VNet.

- Traffic forwarded from remote virtual network . Controls whether forwarded (non-originating) traffic is accepted from the peered VNet.

Traffic forwarded from remote virtual network . Controls whether forwarded (non-originating) traffic is accepted from the peered VNet.

- Virtual network gateway or Route Server . Enables gateway transit. Lets peered VNets use this VNet's VPN Gateway or Azure Route Server.

Virtual network gateway or Route Server . Enables gateway transit. Lets peered VNets use this VNet's VPN Gateway or Azure Route Server.

- Remote virtual network gateway or Route Server . Enables this VNet to use the remote VNet's VPN Gateway or Route Server.

Remote virtual network gateway or Route Server . Enables this VNet to use the remote VNet's VPN Gateway or Route Server.

Things to know about Azure VPN Gateway

Let's take a closer look at how Azure VPN Gateway is implemented with Azure Virtual Network peering.

- A virtual network can have only one VPN gateway.

A virtual network can have only one VPN gateway.

- Gateway transit is supported for both regional and global virtual network peering.

Gateway transit is supported for both regional and global virtual network peering.

- When you allow VPN gateway transit, the virtual network can communicate to resources outside the peering. In our sample illustration, the gateway subnet gateway within the hub virtual network can complete tasks such as: Use a site-to-site VPN to connect to an on-premises network. Use a vnet-to-vnet connection to another virtual network. Use a point-to-site VPN to connect to a client.

When you allow VPN gateway transit, the virtual network can communicate to resources outside the peering. In our sample illustration, the gateway subnet gateway within the hub virtual network can complete tasks such as:

- Use a site-to-site VPN to connect to an on-premises network.

- Use a vnet-to-vnet connection to another virtual network.

- Use a point-to-site VPN to connect to a client.

- Gateway transit allows peered virtual networks to share the gateway and get access to external resources. With this implementation, you don't need to deploy a VPN gateway in the peered virtual network.

Gateway transit allows peered virtual networks to share the gateway and get access to external resources. With this implementation, you don't need to deploy a VPN gateway in the peered virtual network.

- You can apply network security groups in a virtual network to block or allow access to other virtual networks or subnets. When you configure virtual network peering, you can choose to open or close the network security group rules between the virtual networks.

You can apply network security groups in a virtual network to block or allow access to other virtual networks or subnets. When you configure virtual network peering, you can choose to open or close the network security group rules between the virtual networks.

Unit 3.4.4 - Create virtual network peering

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-vnet-peering/4-create

Create virtual network peering

Azure Virtual Network peering can be configured for virtual networks by using PowerShell, the Azure CLI, and in the Azure portal. In this module, we review the steps to create the peering in the Azure portal for virtual networks deployed through Azure Resource Manager.

Things to know about creating virtual network peering

There are a few points to review before we look at how to create the peering in the Azure portal.

- To implement virtual network peering, your Azure account must be assigned to the Network Contributor role. Alternatively, your Azure account can be assigned to a custom role that can complete the necessary peering actions. For details, see Permissions .

To implement virtual network peering, your Azure account must be assigned to the Network Contributor role. Alternatively, your Azure account can be assigned to a custom role that can complete the necessary peering actions. For details, see Permissions .

Network Contributor

- To create a peering, you need two virtual networks.

To create a peering, you need two virtual networks.

- The second virtual network in the peering is referred to as the remote network .

The second virtual network in the peering is referred to as the remote network .

- Initially, the virtual machines in your virtual networks can't communicate with each other. After the peering is established, the machines can communicate within the peered network based on your configuration settings.

Initially, the virtual machines in your virtual networks can't communicate with each other. After the peering is established, the machines can communicate within the peered network based on your configuration settings.

How to connect virtual networks across Azure regions with Azure Global virtual network peering

How to check your peering status

In the Azure portal, you can check the connectivity status of the virtual networks in your virtual network peering. The status conditions depend on how your virtual networks are deployed.

Important

Your peering isn't successfully established until both virtual networks in the peering have a status of Connected .

- The two peering status conditions are Initiated and Connected .

The two peering status conditions are Initiated and Connected .

- When you create the initial peering to the second (remote) virtual network from the first virtual network, the peering status for the first virtual network is Initiated .

When you create the initial peering to the second (remote) virtual network from the first virtual network, the peering status for the first virtual network is Initiated .

Unit 3.4.5 - Extend peering with user-defined routes and service chaining

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-vnet-peering/5-determine-service-chaining-uses

Extend peering with user-defined routes and service chaining

Virtual network peering is nontransitive. The communication capabilities in a peering are available to only the virtual networks and resources in the peering. Other mechanisms have to be used to enable traffic to and from resources and networks outside the private peering network.

Suppose you have three virtual networks: A, B, and C. You establish virtual network peering between networks A and B, and also between networks B and C. You don't set up peering between networks A and C. The virtual network peering capabilities that you set up between networks B and C don't automatically enable peering communication capabilities between networks A and C.

Things to know about extending peering

There are a few ways to extend the capabilities of your peering for resources and virtual networks outside your peering network.

Mechanism

Description

Hub and spoke network

When you deploy a hub-and-spoke network, the hub virtual network can host infrastructure components like a network virtual appliance (NVA) or Azure VPN gateway. All the spoke virtual networks can then peer with the hub virtual network. Traffic can flow through NVAs or VPN gateways in the hub virtual network.

User-defined route (UDR)

Virtual network peering enables the next hop in a user-defined route to be the IP address of a virtual machine in the peered virtual network, or a VPN gateway.

Service chaining

Service chaining is used to direct traffic from one virtual network to a virtual appliance or gateway. To enable service chaining, configure UDRs that point to virtual machines in peered virtual networks as the next hop IP address. UDRs could also point to virtual network gateways to enable service chaining.

Azure Virtual Network Manager

Centrally manages hub-and-spoke or mesh peering topologies at scale. Automates peering creation without manual per-VNet configuration.

The following diagram shows a hub and spoke virtual network with an NVA and VPN gateway. The hub and spoke network is accessible to other virtual networks via user-defined routes and service chaining.

Tip

Use the Ask Learn icon (top right) to learn more about service chaining and user-defined routes .

Unit 3.4.6 - Exercise - Implement Intersite Connectivity

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-vnet-peering/6-simulation-peering

Exercise - Implement Intersite Connectivity

Lab scenario

Your organization segments core IT apps and services (such as DNS and security services) from other parts of the business, including your manufacturing department. However, in some scenarios, apps and services in the core area need to communicate with apps and services in the manufacturing area. In this lab, you configure connectivity between the segmented areas. Separating production from development or separating one subsidiary from another is a common networking scenario.

Architecture diagram

Job skills

- Create a virtual machine in a virtual network.

- Create a virtual machine in a different virtual network.

- Use Network Watcher to test the connection between virtual machines.

- Configure virtual network peerings between different virtual networks.

- Use Azure PowerShell to test the connection between virtual machines.

- Create a custom route. (optional)

Important

Estimated time: 50 minutes.

To complete the exercise, you need an Azure subscription .

Launch the exercise, and follow the instructions. When finished, be sure to return to this page so you can continue learning.

Unit 3.4.7 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-vnet-peering/7-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Your company is implementing an Azure Virtual Network peering solution to enable connectivity between virtual networks. You're working on the plan to support shared access to gateways and resources, and to control internet communication. A few teams submitted questions and configuration requests for your input.

- The IT team needs information about how to check virtual network peering status and verify peered connections.

The IT team needs information about how to check virtual network peering status and verify peered connections.

- The Marketing department has resources in virtual networks in different regions.

The Marketing department has resources in virtual networks in different regions.

Answer the following questions

Choose the best response for each question.

Unit 3.4.8 - Summary and resources

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-vnet-peering/8-summary-resources

Summary and resources

In this module, you learned Azure Virtual Network peering lets you connect virtual networks in a hub and spoke topology. You learned how to configure your virtual networks with Azure VPN Gateway for transit connectivity. You explored how to extend peering with user-defined routes and service chaining.

The main takeaways from this module are:

- Azure Virtual Network peering allows for the connection of virtual networks in a hub and spoke topology.

Azure Virtual Network peering allows for the connection of virtual networks in a hub and spoke topology.

- There are two types of peering: regional and global. Regional peering connects virtual networks in the same region. Global peering connects virtual networks in different regions.

There are two types of peering: regional and global. Regional peering connects virtual networks in the same region. Global peering connects virtual networks in different regions.

- Network traffic between peered virtual networks is private and kept on the Azure backbone network.

Network traffic between peered virtual networks is private and kept on the Azure backbone network.

- You can configure Azure VPN Gateway in the peered virtual network as a transit point to access resources in another network.

You can configure Azure VPN Gateway in the peered virtual network as a transit point to access resources in another network.

- Network security groups can be applied to block or allow access between virtual networks when configuring virtual network peering.

Network security groups can be applied to block or allow access between virtual networks when configuring virtual network peering.

Learn more with Copilot

Copilot can assist you in designing Azure infrastructure solutions. Copilot can compare, recommend, explain, and research products and services where you need more information. Open a Microsoft Edge browser and choose Copilot (top right) or navigate to copilot.microsoft.com. Take a few minutes to try these prompts and extend your learning with Copilot.

- What is Azure virtual network peering and what are the advantages of this feature?

What is Azure virtual network peering and what are the advantages of this feature?

- What are some of the configurations settings for Azure virtual network peering?

What are some of the configurations settings for Azure virtual network peering?

Learn more with documentation

- Azure Virtual Network peering . This article is your starting point for learning about virtual network peering.

Azure Virtual Network peering . This article is your starting point for learning about virtual network peering.

- Create, change, or delete a virtual network peering . This article reviews how to create a virtual network peering and what each setting means.

Create, change, or delete a virtual network peering . This article reviews how to create a virtual network peering and what each setting means.

Learn more with self-paced training

- Introduction to Azure Virtual Networks . Learn how to design and implement core Azure networking infrastructure such as virtual networks, and virtual network peering.

LP 3 M6 - Introduction to Azure Load Balancer

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-load-balancer/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 3.6.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-load-balancer/1-introduction

Introduction

You're responsible for networking at Adatum, a new and expanding online commerce store. Adatum has several three-tier applications that run on virtual machines (VMs) that were migrated from on-premises datacenters. These VMs are hosted across various virtual networks. Some of the applications are available to the public internet and others should be accessible only to users at Adatum’s main office location in Sydney.

When the applications were hosted on-premises, various hardware devices used Open Systems Interconnection (OSI) model Layer 4 load balancing to distribute incoming traffic across the web-tier VMs and across the middle-tier VMs that perform data analysis and transformation tasks. These Layer 4 devices were configured so that you could use remote desktop protocol to connect to individual VMs to perform administrative tasks. The hardware devices would also stop forwarding traffic to any VM that experienced a failure and ensured that client traffic for a session only occurred with one VM in the back-end pool. Now that the VMs are migrated to Azure, you would like to replicate the functionality provided by the Layer 4 hardware devices using native Azure services. You believe you can accomplish this goal with Load Balancer.

Azure Load Balancer distributes inbound traffic across a set of VMs in a back-end pool. The back-end pool can be made up of Azure infrastructure as a service (IaaS) VMs or instances in a Virtual Machine Scale Set. You can configure how incoming traffic is distributed across the back-end pool using load-balancing rules. You can ensure that traffic isn't directed to unresponsive nodes using health probes.

This module explains what Azure Load Balancer does, how it works, and when you should choose to use Load Balancer as a solution to meet your organization's needs.

Learning objectives

In this module, you'll:

- Learn what Azure Load Balancer is and the functionality it provides.

- Determine whether Load Balancer meets the needs of your organization.

Prerequisites

- Understanding of basic networking concepts

Unit 3.6.2 - What is Azure Load Balancer?

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-load-balancer/2-what-is-azure-load-balancer

What is Azure Load Balancer?

Some applications have so much incoming traffic that the single server hosting them becomes overwhelmed and can't respond to client requests in a timely manner. Instead of continuously adding network capacity, processors, disk resources, and RAM, you can address this traffic by implementing load balancing. Load balancing is a process in which you distribute incoming traffic equitably across multiple computers. A pool of computers that have lower levels of resources often responds to traffic more effectively than a single server with higher performance.

Azure Load Balancer is an Azure service that allows you to evenly distribute incoming network traffic across a group of Azure VMs, or across instances in a Virtual Machine Scale Set. Load Balancer delivers high availability and network performance in the following ways:

- Load-balancing rules determine how traffic is distributed to instances that comprise the back end.

- Health probes ensure the resources in the back end are healthy and that traffic isn't directed to unhealthy back-end instances.

You can deploy public load balancers and internal (or private ) load balancers in Azure:

- Public load balancers are used to load balance internet traffic to your virtual machines (VMs). A public load balancer maps the public IP address and port number of incoming traffic to the private IP address and port number of the back-end pool VMs. For example, you can spread the load of incoming web-request traffic from the internet across multiple web servers. A public load balancer can also provide outbound connections for VMs inside your virtual network.

- An internal load balancer directs traffic to resources that are inside a virtual network or that use a VPN to access Azure infrastructure. Internal load balancer front-end IP addresses and virtual networks are never directly exposed to an internet endpoint. Internal line-of-business (LOB) applications run in Azure and are accessed from within Azure or from on-premises resources. An internal load balancer is used where private IPs are needed at the front end only. Internal load balancers are often used to balance traffic from the front-end web tier infrastructure as a service (IaaS) VMs across a set of secondary VMs that perform tasks such as performing calculations or data processing.

An internal load balancer enables the following types of load balancing:

- Within a virtual network : Load balancing from VMs in the virtual network to a set of VMs that reside within the same virtual network.

- For a cross-premises virtual network : Load balancing from on-premises computers to a set of VMs that reside within the same virtual network.

- For multi-tier applications : Load balancing for internet-facing multi-tier applications where the back-end tiers aren't internet-facing. The back-end tiers require traffic load balancing from the internet-facing tier.

- For LOB applications : Load balancing for LOB applications that are hosted in Azure without added load balancer hardware or software. This scenario includes on-premises servers that are in the set of computers whose traffic is load balanced.

Each Load Balancer type can be used for inbound and outbound scenarios and scale up to millions of Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) and User Datagram Protocol (UDP) application flows.

Unit 3.6.3 - How Azure Load Balancer works

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-load-balancer/3-how-azure-load-balancer-works

How Azure Load Balancer works

Azure Load Balancer operates at the transport layer of the Open Systems Interconnection (OSI) model. This Layer 4 functionality allows traffic management based on specific properties of the traffic. Properties including source and destination address, TCP or UDP protocol type, and port number.

Load Balancer has several elements that work together to ensure an application's high availability and performance:

- Front-end IP

- Load balancer rules

- Back-end pool

- Health probes

- Inbound NAT rules

- High availability ports

- Outbound rules

Front-end IP

The front-end IP address is the address clients use to connect to your web application. A front-end IP address can be either a public or a private IP address. Azure load balancers can have multiple front-end IPs. The selection of a public or a private IP address determines which type of load balancer to create:

- Public IP address: A public load balancer : A public load balancer maps the public IP and port of incoming traffic to the private IP and port of the virtual machine (VM). You can distribute specific types of traffic across multiple VMs or services by applying load-balancing rules. For example, you can spread the load of web request traffic across multiple web servers. The load balancer maps the response traffic from the private IP and port of the VM to the public IP and port of the load balancer. Then, it transmits the response back to the requesting client.

Public IP address: A public load balancer : A public load balancer maps the public IP and port of incoming traffic to the private IP and port of the virtual machine (VM). You can distribute specific types of traffic across multiple VMs or services by applying load-balancing rules. For example, you can spread the load of web request traffic across multiple web servers. The load balancer maps the response traffic from the private IP and port of the VM to the public IP and port of the load balancer. Then, it transmits the response back to the requesting client.

- Private IP address: An internal load balancer : An internal load balancer distributes traffic to resources that are inside a virtual network. Azure restricts access to the front-end IP addresses of a virtual network that are load balanced. Front-end IP addresses and virtual networks are never directly exposed to an internet endpoint. Internal line-of-business applications run in Azure and are accessed from within Azure or from on-premises resources through a VPN or ExpressRoute connection.

Private IP address: An internal load balancer : An internal load balancer distributes traffic to resources that are inside a virtual network. Azure restricts access to the front-end IP addresses of a virtual network that are load balanced. Front-end IP addresses and virtual networks are never directly exposed to an internet endpoint. Internal line-of-business applications run in Azure and are accessed from within Azure or from on-premises resources through a VPN or ExpressRoute connection.

Load Balancer rules

A load balancer rule defines how traffic is distributed to the back-end pool. The rule maps a given front-end IP and port combination to a set of back-end IP addresses and port combination.

Traffic is managed using a five-tuple hash made from the following elements:

- Source IP : The IP address of the requesting client.

- Source port : The port of the requesting client.

- Destination IP : The destination IP address of the request.

- Destination port : The destination port of the request.

- Protocol type : The specified protocol type, Transmission Control Protocol (TCP), or User Datagram Protocol (UDP).

- Session affinity : Ensures that the same pool node always handles traffic for a client.

Load Balancer allows you to load balance services on multiple ports, multiple IP addresses, or both. You can configure different load balancing rules for each front-end IP. Multiple front-end configurations are only supported with IaaS VMs.

Load Balancer can't apply different rules based on internal traffic content because it operates at Layer 4 (transport layer) of the OSI model. If you need to manage traffic based on its Layer 7 (application layer) properties, you need to deploy a solution like Azure Application Gateway.

Back-end pool

The back-end pool is a group of VMs or instances in a Virtual Machine Scale Set that responds to the incoming request. To scale cost-effectively to meet high volumes of incoming traffic, computing guidelines generally recommend adding more instances to the back-end pool.

Load Balancer implements automatic reconfiguration to redistribute load across the altered number of instances when you scale instances up or down. For example, if you added two more VMs instances to the back-end pool, Load Balancer would reconfigure itself to start balancing traffic to those instances based on the already configured load balancing rules.

Health probes

A health probe is used to determine the health status of the instances in the back-end pool. This health probe determines if an instance is healthy and can receive traffic. You can define the unhealthy threshold for your health probes. When a probe fails to respond, the load balancer stops sending new connections to the unhealthy instances. A probe failure doesn't affect existing connections. The connection continues until:

- The application ends the flow.

- Idle timeout occurs.

- The VM shuts down.

Load Balancer allows you to configure different health probe types for endpoints: TCP, HTTP, and HTTPS.

- TCP custom probe : This probe relies on establishing a successful TCP session to a defined probe port. If the specified listener on the VM exists, the probe succeeds. If the connection is refused, the probe fails. You can specify the Port, Interval, and Unhealthy threshold.

- HTTP or HTTPS custom probe : The load balancer regularly probes your endpoint (every 15 seconds, by default). The instance is healthy if it responds with an HTTP 200 within the timeout period (default of 31 seconds). Any status other than HTTP 200 causes the probe to fail. You can specify the port (Port), the URI for requesting the health status from the back end (URI), amount of time between probe attempts (Interval), and the number of failures that must occur for the instance to be considered unhealthy (Unhealthy threshold).

Session persistence

By default, Load Balancer distributes network traffic equally among multiple VM instances. It provides stickiness only within a transport session. Session persistence specifies how traffic from a client should be handled. The default behavior (None) is that any healthy VM can handle successive requests from a client.

Session persistence is also known as session affinity, source IP affinity, or client IP affinity. This distribution mode uses a two-tuple (source IP and destination IP) or three-tuple (source IP, destination IP, and protocol type) hash to route to back-end instances. When you use session persistence, connections from the same client go to the same back-end instance within the back-end pool. You can configure one of the following session persistence options:

- None (default) : Specifies that any healthy VM can handle the request.

- Client IP (2-tuple) : Specifies that the same back-end instance can handle successive requests from the same client IP address.

- Client IP and protocol (3-tuple) : Specifies that the same back-end instance can handle successive requests from the same client IP address and protocol combination.

You can change this behavior by configuring one of the options that are described in the following sections.

High availability ports

A load balancer rule configured with protocol - all and port - 0 is known as a high availability (HA) port rule . This rule enables a single rule to load balance all TCP and UDP flows that arrive on all ports of an internal standard load balancer.

protocol - all and port - 0

The load-balancing decision is made per flow. This action is based on the following five-tuple connection:

- Source IP address

- Source port

- Destination IP address

- Destination port

- Protocol

HA ports load-balancing rules help you with critical scenarios, such as high availability and scale for network virtual appliances (NVAs) inside virtual networks. The feature can help when a large number of ports must be load balanced.

Inbound NAT rules

You can use load balancing rules in combination with Network Address Translation (NAT) rules. For example, you could use NAT from the load balancer's public address to TCP 3389 on a specific VM. This rule combination allows remote desktop access from outside of Azure.

Outbound rules

An outbound rule configures Source Network Address Translation (SNAT) for all VMs or instances identified by the back-end pool. This rule enables instances in the back end to communicate (outbound) to the internet or other public endpoints.

Unit 3.6.4 - When to use Azure Load Balancer

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-load-balancer/4-when-to-use-azure-load-balancer

When to use Azure Load Balancer

Azure Load Balancer is best suited for applications that require ultra-low latency and high performance. Load Balancer is suitable for your organization's needs because you're replacing existing network hardware devices that load balance traffic across applications. The applications used multiple virtual machine (VM) tiers when the applications were on-premises with an Azure service that has the same functionality.

Because Load Balancer operates at Layer 4 like hardware devices that were used on-premises before the organization migrated to Azure, you can use Load Balancer to replicate that hardware device functionality. This functionality includes using health probes to ensure that Load Balancer doesn't forward traffic to failed VM nodes. It also includes using session persistence to ensure that clients only communicate with a single VM during a session.

You can configure public load balancers for front-end traffic to web tiers of applications. You can also configure internal load balancers to balance traffic between the web tier and the tier that performs data analysis and transformation tasks.

You can configure inbound NAT rules to allow remote desktop protocol access to a VM instance to perform administrative tasks.

When not to use Azure Load Balancer

Azure Load Balancer isn't appropriate if you have a web application that doesn't require load balancing running on a single IaaS VM instance. For example, if your web application only receives a small amount of traffic and the existing infrastructure already competently deals with the existing load, there's no need to deploy a back-end pool of VMs and no need to use Load Balancer.

Azure provides other load-balancing solutions as alternatives to Azure Load Balancer, including Azure Front Door, Azure Traffic Manager, and Azure Application Gateway:

- Azure Front Door is an application-delivery network that provides a global load balancing and site acceleration service for web applications. It offers Layer 7 capabilities for your application like TLS/SSL offload, path-based routing, fast failover, a web application firewall, and caching to improve performance and high availability of your applications. Choose this option in scenarios such as load balancing a web app deployed across multiple Azure regions.

- Azure Traffic Manager is a DNS-based traffic load balancer that allows you to distribute traffic optimally to services across global Azure regions while providing high availability and responsiveness. Because Traffic Manager is a DNS-based load-balancing service, it load balances only at the domain level. For that reason, it can't fail over as quickly as Front Door, because of common challenges around DNS caching and systems not honoring DNS TTLs.

- Azure Application Gateway provides Application Delivery Controller (ADC) as a service, offering various Layer 7 load-balancing capabilities. Use it to optimize web farm productivity by offloading CPU-intensive TLS/SSL termination to the gateway. Application Gateway works within a region rather than globally.

In comparison to these solutions:

- Azure Load Balancer is a high-performance, ultra-low-latency Layer 4 load-balancing service (inbound and outbound) for all UDP and TCP protocols. Its built to handle millions of requests per second while ensuring your solution is highly available. Azure Load Balancer is zone-redundant, ensuring high availability across availability zones. If Adatum had applications that required web application firewall functionality, Azure Load Balancer wouldn't be an appropriate solution for the company.

Unit 3.6.5 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-load-balancer/5-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Choose the best response for each question.

Check your knowledge

Unit 3.6.6 - Summary

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-load-balancer/6-summary

Summary

In this module, you learned about Azure Load Balancer. An Azure service that allows you to evenly distribute incoming network traffic across a group of Azure virtual machines, or across instances in a Virtual Machine Scale Set. You also learned how Load Balancer delivers high availability and network performance to your applications. You learned about the types of scenarios in which Load Balancer is an appropriate solution for your organization, and how Load Balancer is likely able to meet Adatum's networking needs. You also learned about the difference between Azure Load Balancer and other traffic management technologies, including Azure Application Gateway and Azure Traffic Manager.

Learn more

- What is Azure Load Balancer?

- Load-balancing options

- Azure Load Balancer components

- Module: Introduction to Azure Load Balancer

LP 3 M7 - Introduction to Azure Application Gateway

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-application-gateway/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 3.7.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-application-gateway/1-introduction

Introduction

Azure Application Gateway is an Azure service that processes traffic to web apps that are hosted on a pool of web servers. The processing performed by Azure Application Gateway includes load balancing HTTP traffic and inspecting traffic using web application firewall. It also includes encrypting traffic between users and an application gateway, and encrypting traffic between application servers and an application gateway.

Adatum is a new and expanding online commerce store that sells industrial drones. You're responsible for networking at the company. Adatum has several web applications that are hosted on computers in its on-premises datacenter. At the moment, a special but aging hardware device is deployed on the Adatum perimeter network that manages traffic to the web applications hosted on these computers. You want to retire this device and have traffic mediated by an Azure service.

To meet your goals, you need to ensure that the Azure service replicates the functionality that the special hardware currently provides. Important functionality that must be present in the replacement service includes:

- Detect if one of the on-premises servers becomes unavailable so that traffic is no longer directed to it.

- TLS (Transport Layer Security) termination functionality to reduce the amount of CPU capacity consumed by encryption and decryption operations.

- Session affinity to ensure that the same back-end pool host always serves a client connection to a web application.

- Security filtering of malicious traffic such as SQL injection and cross site scripting attacks.

This module explains what Azure Application Gateway does, how it works, and when you should choose to use Azure Application Gateway as a solution to meet your organization’s needs.

Learning objectives

In this module, you'll:

- Learn what Azure Application Gateway is and the functionality it provides.

- Determine whether Azure Application Gateway meets the needs of your organization.

Prerequisites

- Understanding of basic networking concepts

- Familiarity with Azure virtual machines and Azure App Service

- Familiarity with Azure virtual networking

Unit 3.7.2 - What is Azure Application Gateway?

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-application-gateway/2-what-is-azure-application-gateway

What is Azure Application Gateway?

Azure Application Gateway manages the requests that client applications send to web apps that are hosted on a pool of web servers. The pool of web servers can be Azure virtual machines, Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets, Azure App Service, and even on-premises servers.

Application Gateway provides features such as load balancing HTTP traffic and web application firewall. It provides support for TLS/SSL encryption of traffic between users and an application gateway and between application servers and an application gateway.

Application Gateway uses a round-robin process to load balance requests to the servers in each back-end pool. Session stickiness ensures client requests in the same session are routed to the same back-end server. Session stickiness is especially important with e-commerce applications where you don’t want a transaction to be disrupted because the load balancer bounces it around between back-end servers.

Azure Application Gateway includes the following features:

- Support for the HTTP, HTTPS, HTTP/2, and WebSocket protocols.

- A web application firewall to protect against web application vulnerabilities.

- End-to-end request encryption.

- Autoscaling to dynamically adjust capacity as your web traffic load change.

- Connection draining allowing graceful removal of back-end pool members during planned service updates.

Unit 3.7.3 - How Azure Application Gateway works

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-application-gateway/3-how-azure-application-gateway-works

How Azure Application Gateway works

Azure Application Gateway has a series of components that combine to securely route and load balance requests across a pool of web servers. Application Gateway includes the following components:

- Front-end IP address : Client requests are received through a front-end IP address. You can configure Application Gateway to have a public IP address, a private IP address, or both. Application Gateway can't have more than one public IP address and one private IP address.

- Listeners : Application Gateway uses one or more listeners to receive incoming requests. A listener accepts traffic arriving on a specified combination of protocol, port, host, and IP address. Each listener routes requests to a back-end pool of servers following routing rules that you specify. A listener can be Basic or Multi-site. A Basic listener only routes a request based on the path in the URL. A Multi-site listener can also route requests using the hostname element of the URL. Listeners also handle TLS/SSL certificates for securing your application between the user and Application Gateway.

- Routing rules : A routing rule binds a listener to the back-end pools. A rule specifies how to interpret the hostname and path elements in the URL of a request and direct the request to the appropriate back-end pool. A routing rule also has an associated set of HTTP settings. These HTTP settings indicate whether (and how) traffic is encrypted between Application Gateway and the back-end servers. Other configuration information includes Protocol, Session stickiness, Connection draining, Request timeout period, and Health probes.

Load balancing in Application Gateway

Application Gateway uses a round-robin mechanism to automatically load balance the requests sent to the servers in each back-end pool. Load-balancing works with the Open Systems Interconnection (OSI) Layer 7 routing implemented by Application Gateway routing, which means that it load balances requests based on the routing parameters (host names and paths) used by the Application Gateway rules. In comparison, other load balancers, such as Azure Load Balancer, function at the OSI Layer 4 level and distribute traffic based on the IP address of the target of a request.

You can configure session stickiness if you need to ensure that all requests for a client in the same session are routed to the same server in a back-end pool.

Web application firewall

The web application firewall (WAF) is an optional component that handles incoming requests before they reach a listener. The web application firewall checks each request for many common threats based on the Open Web Application Security Project (OWASP). Common threats include: SQL-injection, Cross-site scripting, Command injection, HTTP request smuggling, HTTP response splitting, Remote file inclusion, Bots, crawlers, and scanners, and HTTP protocol violations and anomalies.

OWASP defines a set of generic rules for detecting attacks. These rules are referred to as the Core Rule Set (CRS). The rule sets are under continuous review as attacks evolve in sophistication. WAF supports four rule sets: CRS 3.2, 3.1, 3.0 and 2.2.9. CRS 3.1 is the default. If necessary, you can opt to select only specific rules in a rule set, targeting certain threats. Additionally, you can customize the firewall to specify which elements in a request to examine, and limit the size of messages to prevent massive uploads from overwhelming your servers.

Back-end pools

A back-end pool is a collection of web servers that can be made up of: a fixed set of virtual machines, a virtual machine scale-set, an app hosted by Azure App Services, or a collection of on-premises servers.

Each back-end pool has an associated load balancer that distributes work across the pool. When configuring the pool, you provide the IP address or name of each web server. All the servers in the back-end pool should be configured in the same way, including their security settings.

If you're using TLS/SSL, the back-end pool has an HTTP setting that references a certificate used to authenticate the back-end servers. The gateway re-encrypts the traffic by using this certificate before sending it to one of your servers in the back-end pool.

If you're using Azure App Service to host the back-end application, you don't need to install any certificates in Application Gateway to connect to the back-end pool. All communications are automatically encrypted. Application Gateway trusts the servers because Azure manages them.

Application Gateway uses a rule to specify how to direct the messages that it receives on its incoming port to the servers in the back-end pool. If the servers are using TLS/SSL, you must configure the rule to indicate:

- That your servers expect traffic through the HTTPS protocol.

- Which certificate to use to encrypt traffic and authenticate the connection to a server.

Application Gateway routing

When the gateway routes a client request to a web server in the back-end pool, it uses a set of rules configured for the gateway to determine where the request should go. There are two primary methods of routing this client request traffic: path-based routing and multiple-site routing.

Path-based routing

Path-based routing sends requests with different URL paths to different pools of back-end servers. For example, you could direct requests with the path /video/* to a back-end pool containing servers that are optimized to handle video streaming, and direct /images/* requests to a pool of servers that handle image retrieval.

Multiple-site routing

Multiple-site routing configures more than one web application on the same Application Gateway instance. In a multi-site configuration, you register multiple domain name system names (CNAMEs) for the IP address of the application gateway, specifying the name of each site. Application Gateway uses separate listeners to wait for requests for each site. Each listener passes the request to a different rule, which can route the requests to servers in a different back-end pool. For example, you could direct all requests for http://contoso.com to servers in one back-end pool, and requests for http://fabrikam.com to another back-end pool. The following diagram shows this configuration:

http://contoso.com

http://fabrikam.com

Multi-site configurations are useful for supporting multitenant applications, where each tenant has its own set of virtual machines or other resources hosting a web application.

Application Gateway routing also includes these features:

- Redirection . Redirection can be used to another site, or from HTTP to HTTPS.

- Rewrite HTTP headers . HTTP headers allow the client and server to pass parameter information with the request or the response.

- Custom error pages . Application Gateway allows you to create custom error pages instead of displaying default error pages. You can use your own branding and layout using a custom error page.

TLS/SSL termination

When you terminate the TLS/SSL connection at the application gateway, it offloads the CPU-intensive TLS/SSL termination workload from your servers. Also, you don’t need to install certificates and configure TLS/SSL on your servers.

If you need end-to-end encryption, Application Gateway can decrypt the traffic on the gateway by using your private key, then re-encrypt again with the public key of the service running in the back-end pool.

Traffic enters the gateway through a front-end port. You can open many ports, and Application Gateway can receive messages on any of these ports. A listener is the first thing that your traffic meets when entering the gateway through a port. The listener is set up to listen for a specific host name, and a specific port on a specific IP address. The listener can use an TLS/SSL certificate to decrypt the traffic that enters the gateway. The listener then uses a rule that you define to direct the incoming requests to a back-end pool.

Exposing your website or web application through the application gateway also means that you don't directly connect your servers to the web. You're exposing only port 80 or port 443 on the application gateway, which is then forwarded to the back-end pool server. In this configuration, your web servers aren't directly accessible from the internet, which reduces the attack surface of your infrastructure.

Health probes

Health probes determine which servers are available for load-balancing in a back-end pool. The Application Gateway uses a health probe to send a request to a server. When the server returns an HTTP response with a status code between 200 and 399, the server is considered healthy. If you don't configure a health probe, Application Gateway creates a default probe that waits for 30 seconds before deciding that a server is unavailable. Health probes ensure that traffic isn't directed to a nonresponsive or failed web endpoint in the back-end pool.

Autoscaling

Application Gateway supports autoscaling, and can scale up or down based on changing traffic load patterns. Autoscaling also removes the requirement to choose a deployment size or instance count during provisioning.

WebSocket and HTTP/2 traffic

Application Gateway provides native support for the WebSocket and HTTP/2 protocols. The WebSocket and HTTP/2 protocols enable full duplex communication between a server and a client over a long-running Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) connection. This type of communication is more interactive between the web server and the client, and can be bidirectional without the need for polling as required in HTTP-based implementations. These protocols have low overhead (unlike HTTP) and can reuse the same TCP connection for multiple request/responses resulting in a more efficient resource utilization. These protocols are designed to work over traditional HTTP ports of 80 and 443.

Unit 3.7.4 - When to use Azure Application Gateway

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-application-gateway/4-when-to-use-azure-application-gateway

When to use Azure Application Gateway

Azure Application Gateway can meet your organization’s needs for the following reasons:

- Azure Application Gateway routing allows traffic to be directed from an endpoint in Azure to a back-end pool made up of servers running in Adatum’s on-premises datacenter. The health-probe functionality of Azure Application Gateway ensures that traffic isn't being directed to any server that becomes unavailable.

- Azure Application Gateway TLS termination functionality reduces the amount of CPU capacity that servers in the back-end pool allocate to encryption and decryption operations.

- Azure Application Gateway allows Adatum to use a web application firewall to block cross-site scripting and SQL injection traffic before it reaches servers in the back-end pool.

- Azure Application Gateway supports session affinity. This support is required because the several web applications deployed by Adatum use user session state information stored locally on individual servers in the back-end pool.

When not to use Azure Application Gateway

Azure Application Gateway isn’t appropriate if you have a web application that doesn’t require load balancing. For example, if you have a web application that only receives a small amount of traffic and the existing infrastructure already competently deals with the existing load, there's no need to deploy a back-end pool of web apps or virtual machines and no need for Application Gateway.

Azure provides other load balancing solutions, including Azure Front Door, Azure Traffic Manager, and Azure Load Balancer. The following list describes the differences between these services:

- Front Door is an application delivery network that provides global load balancing and site acceleration service for web applications. It offers Layer 7 capabilities for your application like TLS/SSL offload, path-based routing, fast failover, web application firewall, and caching to improve performance and high-availability of your applications. Choose this option in scenarios such as load balancing a web app deployed across multiple Azure regions.

- Traffic Manager is a DNS-based traffic load balancer that enables you to distribute traffic optimally to services across global Azure regions while providing high availability and responsiveness. Because Traffic Manager is a DNS-based load-balancing service, it load-balances only at the domain level. For that reason, it can't fail over as quickly as Front Door because of common challenges around DNS caching and systems not honoring DNS TTLs.

- Azure Load Balancer is a high-performance, ultra low-latency Layer 4 load-balancing service (inbound and outbound) for all UDP and TCP protocols. Azure Load Balancer is built to handle millions of requests per second while ensuring that your solution is highly available. Azure Load Balancer is zone-redundant, ensuring high availability across availability zones. Azure Load Balancer works within a region rather than globally.

Unit 3.7.5 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-application-gateway/5-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Choose the best response for each question.

Check your knowledge

Unit 3.7.6 - Summary

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-application-gateway/6-summary

Summary

In this module, you learned about Azure Application Gateway, a service that allows you to manage the requests that client applications can send to a web app. You learned that Application Gateway routes traffic to a pool of web servers based on the URL of a request. The pool of web servers can be Azure virtual machines, Azure virtual machine scale sets, Azure App Service, and even on-premises servers. You learned that Application Gateway provides features such as load balancing HTTP traffic, a web application firewall, and support for TLS/SSL encryption of your data. You also learned that Application Gateway supports encrypting traffic between users and an application gateway, and between application servers and an application gateway.

Learn more

- What is Azure Application Gateway?

- Azure Application Gateway features

- How an application gateway works

- Application gateway components

- Load balance your web service traffic with Application Gateway

LP 3 M8 - Introduction to Azure Network Watcher

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-network-watcher/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 3.8.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-network-watcher/1-introduction

Introduction

Organizations can use Azure Network Watcher to detect and monitor issues related to the network performance of infrastructure as a service (IaaS) resources in Microsoft Azure.

Adatum is a new and expanding online commerce store. You work in DevOps at Adatum, and you're responsible for networking. Adatum has several three-tier applications running on virtual machines that were migrated from on-premises datacenters to Azure. The applications are hosted across multiple Azure virtual networks. Adatum also has several hybrid applications that have compute tiers in both on-premises and cloud locations.

This module explains what Azure Network Watcher does, how it works, and when you should choose to use Azure Network Watcher as a solution to meet your organization's needs.

Learning objectives

In this module, you'll:

- Learn what Azure Network Watcher is and the functionality it provides.

- Determine whether Azure Network Watcher meets the needs of your organization.

Prerequisites

- Understanding of basic networking concepts such as IP addressing, subnetting, routing, and network security groups.

- Basic familiarity with Azure network integration concepts such as VPNs, Azure ExpressRoute, and peering.

Unit 3.8.2 - What is Azure Network Watcher?

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-network-watcher/2-what-is-azure-network-watcher

What is Azure Network Watcher?

Azure Network Watcher provides a suite of tools to monitor, diagnose, view metrics, and enable or disable logs for Azure IaaS (Infrastructure-as-a-Service) resources. Network Watcher enables you to monitor and repair the network health of IaaS products like virtual machines (VMs), virtual networks (VNets), application gateways, load balancers, etc. Network Watcher isn't designed or intended for PaaS monitoring or Web analytics.

Network Watcher consists of three major sets of tools and capabilities:

- Monitoring Topology Connection monitor

- Topology

- Connection monitor

- Network diagnostic IP flow verify NSG diagnostics Next hop Effective security rules Connection troubleshoot Packet capture VPN troubleshoot

- IP flow verify

- NSG diagnostics

- Next hop

- Effective security rules

- Connection troubleshoot

- Packet capture

- VPN troubleshoot

- Traffic Flow logs Traffic analytics

- Flow logs

- Traffic analytics

Monitoring

Network Watcher offers two monitoring tools that help you view and monitor resources:

- Topology

- Connection monitor

Topology

The Topology tool provides a visualization of the entire network for understanding network configuration. It provides an interactive interface to view resources and their relationships in Azure spanning across multiple subscriptions, resource groups, and locations. At the beginning of the troubleshooting process, this tool helps you visualize all of the elements involved in the problem, allowing you to find something that isn't apparent by looking at the contents of resource groups.

Connection monitor

Connection monitor provides end-to-end connection monitoring for Azure and hybrid endpoints. It helps you understand network performance between various endpoints in your network infrastructure. You can use connection monitor to verify that two IaaS VMs that host the components of a multi-tier application can communicate with each other. You can also use it to verify connectivity in hybrid scenarios.

Network diagnostic tools

Network Watcher offers seven network diagnostic tools that help troubleshoot and diagnose network issues:

- IP flow verify

- NSG diagnostics

- Next hop

- Effective security rules

- Connection troubleshoot

- Packet capture

- VPN troubleshoot

IP flow verify

IP flow verify allows you to detect traffic filtering issues at a virtual machine level. It checks if a packet is allowed or denied to or from an IP address (IPv4 or IPv6 address). It also tells you which security rule allowed or denied the traffic.

NSG diagnostics

NSG diagnostics allows you to detect traffic filtering issues at a virtual machine, virtual machine scale set, or application gateway level. It checks if a packet is allowed or denied to or from an IP address, IP prefix, or a service tag. It tells you which security rule allowed or denied the traffic. It also allows you to add a new security rule with a higher priority to allow or deny the traffic.

Next hop

Next hop allows you to detect routing issues. It checks if traffic is routed correctly to the intended destination. It provides you with information about the Next hop type, IP address, and Route table ID for a specific destination IP address.

Effective security rules

Effective security rules allows you to view the effective security rules applied to a network interface. It shows you all security rules applied to the network interface, the subnet the network interface is in, and the aggregate of both.

Connection troubleshoot

Connection troubleshoot enables you to test a connection between a virtual machine, a virtual machine scale set, an application gateway, or a Bastion host and a virtual machine, an FQDN, a URI, or an IPv4 address. The test returns similar information returned when using the connection monitor tool, but tests the connection at a point in time instead of monitoring it over time, as connection monitor does.

Packet capture

Packet capture allows you to remotely create packet capture sessions to record all network traffic to and from a virtual machine (VM) or a virtual machine scale set.

VPN troubleshoot

VPN troubleshoot enables you to troubleshoot virtual network gateways and their connections.

Traffic

Network Watcher offers two traffic tools that help you log and visualize network traffic:

- Flow logs

- Traffic analytics

Flow logs

Flow logs allows you to log information about your Azure IP traffic and stores the data in Azure storage. You can log IP traffic flowing through a network security group or Azure virtual network.

Traffic analytics

Traffic analytics provides rich visualizations of flow logs data.

Unit 3.8.3 - How Azure Network Watcher works

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-network-watcher/3-how-azure-network-watcher-works

How Azure Network Watcher works

Network Watcher becomes automatically available when you create a virtual network in an Azure region in your subscription. You can access Network Watcher directly in the Azure portal by typing Network Watcher in the Search bar.

Network Watcher Topology tool

The topology capability of Azure Network Watcher allows you to view all of the following resources in a virtual network. Including, the resources associated to resources in a virtual network and the relationships between the resources.

- Subnets

- Network interfaces

- Network security groups

- Load balancer

- Load balancer health probes

- Public IP addresses

- Virtual network peering

- Virtual network gateways

- VPN gateway connections

- Virtual machines

- Virtual Machine Scale Sets

All resources returned in a topology have the following properties:

- Name : The name of the resource.

- Id : The URI of the resource.

- Location : The Azure region the resource is in.

- Associations : A list of associations to the referenced object. Each association has the following properties: AssociationType : References the relationship between the child object and the parent. Valid values are Contains and Associated . Name : The name of the referenced resource. ResourceId : The URI of the resource referenced in the association.

- AssociationType : References the relationship between the child object and the parent. Valid values are Contains and Associated .

Contains

Associated

- Name : The name of the referenced resource.

- ResourceId : The URI of the resource referenced in the association.

Connection Monitor tool

Connection Monitor provides unified, end-to-end connection monitoring in Azure Network Watcher. Connection Monitor supports both hybrid and Azure cloud deployments. You can use the Connection Monitor tool to measure the latency between resources. Connection Monitor can detect changes that affect connectivity, such as network configuration changes or modifications to NSG rules. You can configure Connection Monitor to probe VMs at regular intervals to look for failures or changes. Connection Monitor can diagnose problems and provide explanations about why the issue occurred and the steps that you can take to fix an issue.

To use Connection Monitor for monitoring, you need to install monitoring agents on the hosts that you monitor. Connection Monitor uses lightweight executable files to run connectivity checks, whether a host is located in an Azure virtual network or in an on-premises network. With Azure VMs, you can install the Network Watcher Agent VM, also known as the Network Watcher extension.

IP flow verify

The IP flow verify tool uses a 5-tuple packet parameter-based verification mechanism to detect whether packets that are inbound or outbound are allowed or denied from a VM. Within the tool, you can specify a local and remote port, the protocol (TCP or UDP), the local IP, the remote IP, the VM, and the VM's network adapter.

Next hop

Traffic from an IaaS VM is sent to a destination based on the effective routes associated with a network interface (NIC). Next hop gets the next hop type and IP address of a packet from a specific VM and NIC. Knowing the next hop helps you determine whether traffic is being directed to the intended destination or whether the traffic is being sent nowhere. An improper configuration of routes, in which traffic is directed to an on-premises location or to a virtual appliance, might lead to connectivity issues. Next hop also returns the route table associated with the next hop. If the route is defined as a user-defined route, that route is returned. Otherwise, next hop returns System Route .

System Route

Effective security rules

Network security groups (NSGs) filter packets based on their source and destination IP address and port numbers. More than one NSG can apply to an IaaS resource on an Azure virtual network. By taking into account all rules that are applied across all NSGs for a resource, the Effective Security Rules tool allows you to determine why some traffic might be denied or allowed.

Packet capture

Packet capture is a virtual machine extension that is remotely started through Network Watcher. This capability eases the burden of running a packet capture manually on a specific virtual machine by using operating system tools or third-party utilities. Packet capture can be triggered through the portal, PowerShell, the Azure CLI, or REST API. Network Watcher allows you to configure filters for the capture session to ensure you capture traffic you want to monitor. Filters are based on 5-tuple (protocol, local IP address, remote IP address, local port, and remote port) information. The captured data is stored on the local disk or in a storage blob.

Connection troubleshoot

The connection troubleshoot tool checks TCP connectivity between a source and a destination VM. You can specify the destination VM by using an FQDN, a URI, or an IP address. If the connection is successful, information about the communication appears, including:

- The latency in milliseconds.

- The number of probe packets sent.

- The number of hops in the complete route to the destination.

If the connection is unsuccessful, the tool displays details about the fault. You might see the following fault types:

- CPU : The connection failed because of high CPU utilization.

- Memory : The connection failed because of high memory utilization.

- GuestFirewall : A firewall outside of Azure blocked the connection.

- DNSResolution : The destination IP address couldn't be resolved.

- NetworkSecurityRule : An NSG blocked the connection.

- UserDefinedRoute : There's an incorrect user route in a routing table.

VPN troubleshoot

Network Watcher provides the capability to troubleshoot gateways and connections. The capability can be called through the portal, PowerShell, the Azure CLI, or REST API. When called, Network Watcher diagnoses the health of the gateway or connection, and then it returns the appropriate results. The request is a long-running transaction. The preliminary results that are returned give an overall picture of the health of the resource.

The following list describes the values that are returned by calling the VPN troubleshoot API:

- startTime : The time the troubleshooting started.

- endTime : The time the troubleshooting ended.

- code : This value is UnHealthy if there's a single diagnosis failure.

UnHealthy

- results : A collection of results returned on the connection or the virtual network gateway. id : The fault type. summary : A summary of the fault. detailed : A detailed description of the fault. recommendedActions : A collection of recommended actions to take. actionText : Text that describes what action to take. actionUri : The URI for documentation that describes what action to take. actionUriText : A short description of the action text.

- id : The fault type.

- summary : A summary of the fault.

- detailed : A detailed description of the fault.

- recommendedActions : A collection of recommended actions to take.

- actionText : Text that describes what action to take.

- actionUri : The URI for documentation that describes what action to take.

- actionUriText : A short description of the action text.

Unit 3.8.4 - When to use Azure Network Watcher

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-network-watcher/4-when-to-use-azure-network-watcher

When to use Azure Network Watcher

Azure Network Watcher is useful when you're attempting to troubleshoot networking issues related to Azure IaaS products. For example, you can use the tools included in Azure Network Watcher in the following scenarios:

- Resolve connectivity issues related to IaaS VMs.

- Troubleshoot VPN connections.

- Determine cross region network latencies.

Resolve connectivity issues related to IaaS VMs

Recently, a Windows Server IaaS VM was deployed to Azure. The developers who deployed the VM are unable to establish a remote PowerShell session to this IaaS VM from another IaaS VM on the same virtual network.

You can troubleshoot this issue using the IP flow verify tool. This tool lets you specify a local and remote port, the protocol (TCP/UDP), the local IP, and the remote IP to check the connection status. It also lets you specify the direction of the connection (inbound or outbound). IP flow verify runs a logical test on the rules in place on your network.

In this case, you can use IP flow verify to specify the VM's IP address and the TCP port 5986 (used by PowerShell when using HTTPS). Then, specify the remote VM's IP address and port. Choose the TCP protocol, then select Check . If an NSG rule is blocking traffic, the IP flow verify rule reports which rule is responsible for the dropped traffic.

Troubleshoot VPN connections

An IaaS VM is deployed on an Azure virtual network. Connections to this IaaS VM from on-premises hosts are made through a site-to-site VPN connection.

You can troubleshoot this VPN connection using the Azure VPN troubleshoot tool. This tool runs diagnostics on a virtual network gateway connection, and returns a health diagnosis. You can run this tool from the Azure portal, PowerShell, or the Azure CLI.

When you run the tool, it checks the gateway for common issues and returns the health diagnosis. You can also view the log file to get more information. The diagnosis shows whether the VPN connection is working. If the VPN connection isn't working, the Azure VPN troubleshoot tool suggests ways to resolve the issue.

Determine cross-region network latency

You can use Network Watcher tools to determine the best location to place IaaS resources based on network latencies. For example, you can use Network Watcher to have IaaS VMs in different regions regularly ping each other to determine cross region network latency. This information can allow you to determine whether all your IaaS VMs need to be located in a single region. Or, if they can be spread across different regions to support specific application architectures.

Let's say you have an on-premises hybrid application and an application running in an Azure IaaS VM that connects to the same storage account endpoint. You could use Network Watcher to perform a comparison of latencies for the two applications. If the latency for the on-premises application is too high, it might strengthen a case for migrating that application to Azure. If the latency for the Azure IaaS VM is too high, it might strengthen a case for migrating the VM to another region with lower latency.

When not to use Network Watcher

Network Watcher tools provide intermediate levels of network diagnostic functionality. These tools don't provide some of the advanced features available in some third-party tools. If your organization needs access to this advanced functionality, you might need to deploy a third-party tool that includes this advanced functionality to accomplish your diagnostic goals.

It's important to realize that Network Watcher is mostly used for IaaS resources on Azure virtual networks. You can't use Azure Network Watcher to diagnose connectivity issues related to PaaS services or Web analytics. If you're encountering problems related to these services, you should check the Azure status or service health dashboard.

Unit 3.8.5 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-network-watcher/5-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Choose the best response for each question.

Check your knowledge

Unit 3.8.6 - Summary

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-network-watcher/6-summary

Summary

In this module, you learned about Azure Network Watcher, a service you can use to perform monitoring and diagnostic tasks on IaaS resources deployed on Azure virtual networks. You learned about the monitoring and diagnostic tools that are available in Network Watcher, and which tool is appropriate for specific troubleshooting scenarios.

Learn more

- What is Azure Network Watcher?

- Enable or disable Azure Network Watcher

- Monitor and troubleshoot your end-to-end Azure network infrastructure by using network monitoring tools

- Configure Network Watcher

- Design and implement network monitoring

LP 4 M1 - Configure storage accounts

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-accounts/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 4.1.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-accounts/1-introduction

Introduction

Azure Storage is Microsoft's cloud storage solution for modern data storage scenarios.

Suppose you work for a large e-commerce company that needs to store and serve a vast number of product images to its customers. The company wants a scalable and reliable solution that can handle high traffic and ensure data durability. They want to quickly restore data if there's an outage.

In this module, you learn how to configure storage accounts and select appropriate storage types in Azure. The module covers topics such as implementing replication strategies, and configuring secure access to storage.

The goal of this module is to provide Azure Administrators with the knowledge and skills to effectively configure and manage Azure storage accounts.

Learning objectives

In this module, you learn how to:

- Identify features and usage cases for Azure storage accounts.

- Select between different types of Azure Storage and create storage accounts.

- Select a storage replication strategy.

- Configure secure network access to storage endpoints.

Skills measured

The content in the module helps you prepare for Exam AZ-104: Microsoft Azure Administrator .

Prerequisites

- Experience with the Azure portal.

- Familiarity with managing different types of data storage.

Unit 4.1.2 - Implement Azure Storage

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-accounts/2-implement-azure-storage

Implement Azure Storage

Azure Storage is Microsoft's cloud storage solution for modern data storage scenarios. Azure Storage offers a massively scalable object store for data objects. It provides a file system service for the cloud, a messaging store for reliable messaging, and a NoSQL store.

Azure Storage is an AI-ready service that you can use to store files, messages, tables, and other types of information. You use Azure Storage for applications like file shares. Developers use Azure Storage for working data. Working data includes websites, mobile apps, and desktop applications. Azure Storage is also used by IaaS virtual machines, and PaaS cloud services.

Things to know about Azure Storage

You can think of Azure Storage as supporting three categories of data: structured data, unstructured data, and virtual machine data. Review the following categories and think about which types of storage are used in your organization.

Category

Description

Storage examples

Virtual machine data

Virtual machine data storage includes disks and files. Disks are persistent block storage for Azure IaaS virtual machines. Files are fully managed file shares in the cloud.

Storage for virtual machine data is provided through Azure managed disks. Data disks are used by virtual machines to store data like database files, website static content, or custom application code. The number of data disks you can add depends on the virtual machine size.

Unstructured data

Unstructured data is the least organized. The format of unstructured data is referred to as nonrelational .

Unstructured data can be stored by using Azure Blob Storage and Azure Data Lake Storage. Blob Storage is a highly scalable, REST-based cloud object store. Azure Data Lake Storage is the Hadoop Distributed File System (HDFS) as a service.

Structured data

Structured data is stored in a relational format that has a shared schema. Structured data is often contained in a database table with rows, columns, and keys. Tables are an autoscaling NoSQL store.

Structured data can be stored by using Azure Table Storage, Azure Cosmos DB, and Azure SQL Database. Azure Cosmos DB is a globally distributed database service. Azure SQL Database is a fully managed database-as-a-service built on SQL.

Things to consider when using Azure Storage

As you think about your configuration plan for Azure Storage, consider these prominent features.

- Consider durability and availability . Azure Storage is durable and highly available. Redundancy ensures your data is safe during transient hardware failures. You replicate data across datacenters or geographical regions for protection from local catastrophe or natural disaster. Replicated data remains highly available during an unexpected outage.

Consider durability and availability . Azure Storage is durable and highly available. Redundancy ensures your data is safe during transient hardware failures. You replicate data across datacenters or geographical regions for protection from local catastrophe or natural disaster. Replicated data remains highly available during an unexpected outage.

- Consider secure access . Azure Storage encrypts all data. Azure Storage provides you with fine-grained control over who has access to your data.

Consider secure access . Azure Storage encrypts all data. Azure Storage provides you with fine-grained control over who has access to your data.

- Consider scalability . Azure Storage is designed to be massively scalable to meet the data storage and performance needs of modern applications.

Consider scalability . Azure Storage is designed to be massively scalable to meet the data storage and performance needs of modern applications.

- Consider manageability . Microsoft Azure handles hardware maintenance, updates, and critical issues for you.

Consider manageability . Microsoft Azure handles hardware maintenance, updates, and critical issues for you.

- Consider data accessibility . Data in Azure Storage is accessible from anywhere in the world over HTTP or HTTPS. Microsoft provides SDKs for Azure Storage in various languages. You can use .NET, Java, Node.js, Python, PHP, Ruby, Go, and the REST API. Azure Storage supports scripting in Azure PowerShell or the Azure CLI. The Azure portal and Azure Storage Explorer offer easy visual solutions for working with your data.

Consider data accessibility . Data in Azure Storage is accessible from anywhere in the world over HTTP or HTTPS. Microsoft provides SDKs for Azure Storage in various languages. You can use .NET, Java, Node.js, Python, PHP, Ruby, Go, and the REST API. Azure Storage supports scripting in Azure PowerShell or the Azure CLI. The Azure portal and Azure Storage Explorer offer easy visual solutions for working with your data.

- Consider SFTP support . Blob Storage can use SFTP (SSH File Transfer Protocol), so you can keep using existing SFTP tools to move files directly to and from blobs. To use SFTP, enable hierarchical namespace (HNS). You can turn it on when you create the storage account (Advanced tab) or later under Settings → Configuration.

Consider SFTP support . Blob Storage can use SFTP (SSH File Transfer Protocol), so you can keep using existing SFTP tools to move files directly to and from blobs. To use SFTP, enable hierarchical namespace (HNS). You can turn it on when you create the storage account (Advanced tab) or later under Settings → Configuration.

- Consider NFSv3 protocol support . Blob Storage can also be accessed using NFSv3, which lets Linux clients mount a container like an NFS share. NFSv3 can simplify migrations from Linux file workloads to Azure.

Consider NFSv3 protocol support . Blob Storage can also be accessed using NFSv3, which lets Linux clients mount a container like an NFS share. NFSv3 can simplify migrations from Linux file workloads to Azure.

- Consider default authorization preferences . In the Azure portal, you can enable Default to Microsoft Entra authorization . This authentication makes role-based access control (RBAC) the default instead of shared access keys, which can improve security.

Consider default authorization preferences . In the Azure portal, you can enable Default to Microsoft Entra authorization . This authentication makes role-based access control (RBAC) the default instead of shared access keys, which can improve security.

Unit 4.1.3 - Explore Azure Storage services

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-accounts/3-explore-azure-storage-services

Explore Azure Storage services

Let's examine the details of these services.

Azure Blob Storage

Azure Blob Storage is Microsoft's object storage solution for the cloud. Blob Storage is optimized for storing massive amounts of unstructured or nonrelational data, such as text or binary data. Blob Storage is ideal for:

- Serving images or documents directly to a browser.

- Storing files for distributed access.

- Streaming video and audio.

- Storing data for backup and restore, disaster recovery, and archiving.

- Storing data for analysis by an on-premises or Azure-hosted service.

Objects in Blob Storage can be accessed from anywhere in the world via HTTP or HTTPS. Users or client applications can access blobs via URLs, the Azure Storage REST API, Azure PowerShell, the Azure CLI, or an Azure Storage client library. The storage client libraries are available for multiple languages, including .NET, Java, Node.js, Python, PHP, and Ruby.

Azure Files

Azure Files enables you to set up highly available network file shares. Shares can be accessed by using the Server Message Block (SMB) protocol and the Network File System (NFS) protocol. Multiple virtual machines can share the same files with both read and write access. You can also read the files by using the REST interface or the storage client libraries.

File shares can be used for many common scenarios:

- Many on-premises applications use file shares. This feature makes it easier to migrate those applications that share data to Azure. If you mount the file share to the same drive letter that the on-premises application uses, the part of your application that accesses the file share should work with minimal, if any, changes.

- Configuration files can be stored on a file share and accessed from multiple virtual machines. Tools and utilities used by multiple developers in a group can be stored on a file share, ensuring that everybody can find them, and that they use the same version.

- Diagnostic logs, metrics, and crash dumps are just three examples of data that can be written to a file share and processed or analyzed later.

The storage account credentials are used to provide authentication for access to the file share. All users who have the share mounted should have full read/write access to the share.

Azure Queue Storage

Azure Queue Storage is used to store and retrieve messages. Queue messages can be up to 64 KB in size, and a queue can contain millions of messages. Queues are used to store lists of messages to be processed asynchronously.

Consider a scenario where you want your customers to be able to upload pictures, and you want to create thumbnails for each picture. You could have your customer wait for you to create the thumbnails while uploading the pictures. An alternative is to use a queue. When the customer finishes the upload, you can write a message to the queue. Then you can use an Azure Function to retrieve the message from the queue and create the thumbnails. Each of the processing parts can be scaled separately, which gives you more control when tuning the configuration.

Azure Table Storage

Azure Table storage is a service that stores nonrelational structured data (also known as structured NoSQL data) in the cloud, providing a key/attribute store with a schemaless design. Because Table storage is schemaless, it's easy to adapt your data as the needs of your application evolve. Access to Table storage data is fast and cost-effective for many types of applications, and is typically lower in cost than traditional SQL for similar volumes of data.

In addition to the existing Azure Table Storage service, there's a new Azure Cosmos DB Table API offering that provides throughput-optimized tables, global distribution, and automatic secondary indexes.

Things to consider when choosing Azure Storage services

As you think about your configuration plan for Azure Storage, consider the prominent features of the types of Azure Storage and which options support your application needs.

- Consider storage optimization for massive data . Azure Blob Storage is optimized for storing massive amounts of unstructured data. Objects in Blob Storage can be accessed from anywhere in the world via HTTP or HTTPS. Blob Storage is ideal for serving data directly to a browser, streaming data, and storing data for backup and restore.

Consider storage optimization for massive data . Azure Blob Storage is optimized for storing massive amounts of unstructured data. Objects in Blob Storage can be accessed from anywhere in the world via HTTP or HTTPS. Blob Storage is ideal for serving data directly to a browser, streaming data, and storing data for backup and restore.

- Consider storage with high availability . Azure Files supports highly available network file shares. On-premises apps use file shares for easy migration. By using Azure Files, all users can access shared data and tools. Storage account credentials provide file share authentication to ensure all users who have the file share mounted have the correct read/write access.

Consider storage with high availability . Azure Files supports highly available network file shares. On-premises apps use file shares for easy migration. By using Azure Files, all users can access shared data and tools. Storage account credentials provide file share authentication to ensure all users who have the file share mounted have the correct read/write access.

- Consider storage for messages . Use Azure Queue Storage to store large numbers of messages. Queue Storage is commonly used to create a backlog of work to process asynchronously.

Consider storage for messages . Use Azure Queue Storage to store large numbers of messages. Queue Storage is commonly used to create a backlog of work to process asynchronously.

- Consider storage for structured data . Azure Table Storage is ideal for storing structured, nonrelational data. It provides throughput-optimized tables, global distribution, and automatic secondary indexes. Because Azure Table Storage is part of Azure Cosmos DB, you have access to a fully managed NoSQL database service for modern app development.

Consider storage for structured data . Azure Table Storage is ideal for storing structured, nonrelational data. It provides throughput-optimized tables, global distribution, and automatic secondary indexes. Because Azure Table Storage is part of Azure Cosmos DB, you have access to a fully managed NoSQL database service for modern app development.

Unit 4.1.4 - Determine storage account types

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-accounts/4-determine-storage-account-kinds

Determine storage account types

General purpose Azure storage accounts have two basic types : Standard and Premium.

Things to know about storage account types

Standard storage accounts are backed by magnetic hard disk drives (HDD). A standard storage account provides the lowest cost per GB. You can use Standard storage for applications that require bulk storage or where data is infrequently accessed.

Premium storage accounts are backed by solid-state drives (SSD) and offer consistent low-latency performance. You can use Premium storage for Azure virtual machine disks with I/O-intensive applications like databases.

Note

You can't convert a Standard storage account to a Premium storage account or vice versa. You must create a new storage account with the desired type and copy data, if applicable, to a new storage account. All storage account types are encrypted by using Storage Service Encryption (SSE) for data at rest.

Storage account

Supported services

Redundancy options

Recommended usage

Standard general-purpose v2

Blob Storage (including Data Lake Storage), Queue Storage, Table Storage, and Azure Files

LRS, GRS, RA-GRS, ZRS, GZRS, RA-GZRS

Standard storage account for most scenarios, including blobs, file shares, queues, tables, and disks (page blobs).

Premium block blobs

Blob Storage (including Data Lake Storage)

LRS, ZRS

Premium storage account for block blobs and append blobs. Recommended for applications with high transaction rates. Use Premium block blobs if you work with smaller objects or require consistently low storage latency. This storage is designed to scale with your applications.

Premium file shares

Azure Files

LRS, ZRS

Premium storage account for file shares only. Recommended for enterprise or high-performance scale applications. Use Premium file shares if you require support for both Server Message Block (SMB) and NFS file shares.

Premium page blobs

Page blobs only

LRS only

Premium high-performance storage account for page blobs only. Page blobs are ideal for storing index-based and sparse data structures, such as operating systems, data disks for virtual machines, and databases.

Note

Administrators managing existing Azure subscriptions may encounter legacy storage account types such as General-purpose v1 (GPv1) and legacy BlobStorage accounts. Microsoft recommends upgrading legacy accounts to General-purpose v2 for access to all current capabilities. Upgrades are supported in-place via the Azure portal, Azure CLI, or PowerShell.

Tip

Before continuing, consider working through the Create a storage account training module.

Unit 4.1.5 - Determine replication strategies

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-accounts/5-determine-replication-strategies

Determine replication strategies

The data in your Azure storage account is always replicated to ensure durability and high availability. Azure Storage replication copies your data to protect from planned and unplanned events. These events range from transient hardware failures, network or power outages, massive natural disasters, and so on. You can choose to replicate your data within the same data center, across zonal data centers within the same region, and even across regions. Replication ensures your storage account meets the Service-Level Agreement (SLA) for Azure Storage even if there are failures.

Locally redundant storage

Locally redundant storage is the lowest-cost replication option and offers the least durability compared to other strategies. If a data center-level disaster occurs, such as fire or flooding, all replicas might be lost or unrecoverable. Despite its limitations, LRS can be appropriate in several scenarios:

- Your application stores data that can be easily reconstructed if data loss occurs.

- Your data is constantly changing like in a live feed, and storing the data isn't essential.

- Your application is restricted to replicating data only within a location due to data governance requirements.

Zone redundant storage

Zone redundant storage synchronously replicates your data across three storage clusters in a single region. Each storage cluster is physically separated from the others and resides in its own availability zone. Each availability zone, and the ZRS cluster within it, is autonomous, and has separate utilities and networking capabilities. Storing your data in a ZRS account ensures you can access and manage your data if a zone becomes unavailable. ZRS provides excellent performance and low latency.

- ZRS isn't currently available in all regions.

- Changing to ZRS from another data replication option requires the physical data movement from a single storage stamp to multiple stamps within a region.

Geo-redundant storage

Geo-redundant storage replicates your data to a secondary region (hundreds of miles away from the primary location of the source data). GRS provides a higher level of durability even during a regional outage. GRS is designed to provide at least 99.99999999999999% (16 9's) durability . When your storage account has GRS enabled, your data is durable even when there's a complete regional outage or a disaster where the primary region isn't recoverable.

If you implement GRS, you have two related options to choose from:

- GRS replicates your data to another data center in a secondary region. The data is available to be read only if Microsoft initiates a failover from the primary to secondary region.

GRS replicates your data to another data center in a secondary region. The data is available to be read only if Microsoft initiates a failover from the primary to secondary region.

- Read-access geo-redundant storage (RA-GRS) is based on GRS. RA-GRS replicates your data to another data center in a secondary region, and also provides you with the option to read from the secondary region. With RA-GRS, you can read from the secondary region regardless of whether Microsoft initiates a failover from the primary to the secondary.

Read-access geo-redundant storage (RA-GRS) is based on GRS. RA-GRS replicates your data to another data center in a secondary region, and also provides you with the option to read from the secondary region. With RA-GRS, you can read from the secondary region regardless of whether Microsoft initiates a failover from the primary to the secondary.

For a storage account with GRS or RA-GRS enabled, all data is first replicated with locally redundant storage. An update is first committed to the primary location and replicated by using LRS. The update is then replicated asynchronously to the secondary region by using GRS. Data in the secondary region uses LRS. Both the primary and secondary regions manage replicas across separate fault domains and upgrade domains within a storage scale unit. The storage scale unit is the basic replication unit within the datacenter. Replication at this level is provided by LRS.

Geo-zone redundant storage

Geo-zone-redundant storage combines the high availability of zone-redundant storage with protection from regional outages as provided by geo-redundant storage. Data in a GZRS storage account is replicated across three Azure availability zones in the primary region, and also replicated to a secondary geographic region for protection from regional disasters. Each Azure region is paired with another region within the same geography, together making a regional pair.

With a GZRS storage account, you can continue to read and write data if an availability zone becomes unavailable or is unrecoverable. Additionally, your data is also durable during a complete regional outage or during a disaster in which the primary region isn't recoverable. GZRS is designed to provide at least 99.99999999999999% (16 9's) durability of objects over a given year. GZRS also offers the same scalability targets as LRS, ZRS, GRS, or RA-GRS. You can optionally enable read access to data in the secondary region with read-access geo-zone-redundant storage (RA-GZRS).

Tip

Microsoft recommends using GZRS for applications that require consistency, durability, high availability, excellent performance, and resilience for disaster recovery. Enable RA-GZRS for read access to a secondary region when there's a regional disaster.

Things to consider when choosing replication strategies

Let's examine the scope of durability and availability for the different replication strategies. The following table describes several key factors during the replication process, including node unavailability within a data center, and whether the entire data center (zonal or nonzonal) becomes unavailable. The table identifies read access to data in a remote, geo-replicated region during region-wide unavailability, and the supported Azure storage account types.

Node in data center unavailable

Entire data center unavailable

Region-wide outage

Read access during region-wide outage

- LRS - ZRS - GRS - RA-GRS - GZRS - RA-GZRS

- ZRS - GRS - RA-GRS - GZRS - RA-GZRS

- GRS - RA-GRS - GZRS - RA-GZRS

- RA-GRS - RA-GZRS

Unit 4.1.6 - Access storage

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-accounts/6-access-storage

Access storage

Every object you store in Azure Storage has a unique URL address. Your storage account name forms the subdomain portion of the URL address. The combination of the subdomain and the domain name, which is specific to each service, forms an endpoint for your storage account.

Let's look at an example. If your storage account name is mystorageaccount , default endpoints for your storage account are formed for the Azure services as shown in the following table:

Service

Default endpoint

Container service

// mystorageaccount .blob.core.windows.net

//

mystorageaccount

.blob.core.windows.net

Table service

// mystorageaccount .table.core.windows.net

//

mystorageaccount

.table.core.windows.net

Queue service

// mystorageaccount .queue.core.windows.net

//

mystorageaccount

.queue.core.windows.net

File service

// mystorageaccount .file.core.windows.net

//

mystorageaccount

.file.core.windows.net

We create the URL to access an object in your storage account by appending the object's location in the storage account to the endpoint.

For example, to access the myblob data in the mycontainer location in your storage account, we use the following URL address:

// mystorageaccount .blob.core.windows.net/ mycontainer / myblob .

//

mystorageaccount

.blob.core.windows.net/

mycontainer

/

myblob

Configure custom domains

You can configure a custom domain to access blob data in your Azure storage account. As we reviewed, the default endpoint for Azure Blob Storage is \<storage-account-name>.blob.core.windows.net . If you map a custom domain and subdomain, such as www.contoso.com , to the blob or web endpoint for your storage account, your users can use that domain to access blob data in your storage account.

\<storage-account-name>.blob.core.windows.net

www.contoso.com

Direct mapping lets you enable a custom domain for a subdomain to an Azure storage account. For this approach, you create a CNAME record that points from the subdomain to the Azure storage account.

CNAME

The following example shows how a subdomain is mapped to an Azure storage account to create a CNAME record in the domain name system (DNS):

CNAME

- Subdomain: blobs.contoso.com

blobs.contoso.com

- Azure storage account: \<storage account>\.blob.core.windows.net

\<storage account>\.blob.core.windows.net

- Direct CNAME record: contosoblobs.blob.core.windows.net

CNAME

contosoblobs.blob.core.windows.net

Unit 4.1.7 - Secure storage endpoints

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-accounts/7-secure-storage-endpoints

Secure storage endpoints

In the Azure portal, each Azure service requires certain steps to configure the service endpoints and restrict network access.

To access these settings for your storage account, you use the Firewalls and virtual networks settings. You add the virtual networks that should have access to the service for the account. - This setting restricts access to your storage account from specific subnets on virtual networks or public IPs.

The service endpoints for a storage account provide the base URL for any blob, queue, table, or file object in Azure Storage. Use this base URL to construct the address for any given resource.

Things to know about configuring service endpoints

Here are some points to consider about configuring service access settings:

- You can configure the service to allow access to one or more public IP ranges.

You can configure the service to allow access to one or more public IP ranges.

- Subnets and virtual networks must exist in the same Azure region or region pair as your storage account.

Subnets and virtual networks must exist in the same Azure region or region pair as your storage account.

Important

Be sure to test the service endpoint and verify the endpoint limits access as expected.

Things to know about configuring private endpoints

In addition to service endpoints, Azure Storage supports private endpoints for enhanced security and network isolation. Private endpoints are the recommended approach for production workloads requiring secure access.

A private endpoint uses a private IP address from your virtual network to bring the Azure Storage service into your VNet. All traffic between your VNet and the storage service goes over the Microsoft backbone network, eliminating exposure to the public internet.

Key differences from service endpoints

- Private endpoints assign a private IP from your VNet to the storage account, keeping all traffic within the Microsoft backbone. Use private endpoints for production workloads requiring complete network isolation and compliance requirements

Private endpoints assign a private IP from your VNet to the storage account, keeping all traffic within the Microsoft backbone. Use private endpoints for production workloads requiring complete network isolation and compliance requirements

- Service endpoints keep the storage account on its public endpoint but restrict access to specific VNets and subnets. Use service endpoints for development scenarios or when you need simpler configuration with some public internet access

Service endpoints keep the storage account on its public endpoint but restrict access to specific VNets and subnets. Use service endpoints for development scenarios or when you need simpler configuration with some public internet access

Tip

Learn more with the Secure and isolate access to Azure resources by using network security groups and service endpoints training module. This module has a sandbox where you can restrict access to Azure Storage by using service endpoints.

Unit 4.1.8 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-accounts/8-knowledge-check

Module assessment

An organization has diverse requirements for their cloud-hosted data. They need to configure secure storage access.

- The admin team requests help implementing a storage replication strategy. They have questions about how to configure storage accounts.

The admin team requests help implementing a storage replication strategy. They have questions about how to configure storage accounts.

- The manufacturing division has sensors that record time-relative data. Only the most recent data is useful. The company wants the lowest cost storage solution for this data.

The manufacturing division has sensors that record time-relative data. Only the most recent data is useful. The company wants the lowest cost storage solution for this data.

Answer the following questions

Choose the best response for each question.

Unit 4.1.9 - Summary and resources

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-accounts/9-summary-resources

Summary and resources

In this module, you learned about Azure Storage and how to create a storage account.

The main takeaways from this module are:

- Azure Storage provides a range of storage options for different types of data, including virtual machine data, unstructured data, and structured data.

Azure Storage provides a range of storage options for different types of data, including virtual machine data, unstructured data, and structured data.

- There are different types of storage accounts available, each with its own features and pricing model. It's important to consider the specific requirements of your application when choosing the right storage account type.

There are different types of storage accounts available, each with its own features and pricing model. It's important to consider the specific requirements of your application when choosing the right storage account type.

- Azure Storage offers four data services: Azure Blob Storage, Azure Files, Azure Queue Storage, and Azure Table Storage. Each service is optimized for different types of data and has its own use cases and benefits.

Azure Storage offers four data services: Azure Blob Storage, Azure Files, Azure Queue Storage, and Azure Table Storage. Each service is optimized for different types of data and has its own use cases and benefits.

- Replication is an important consideration for ensuring data durability and high availability. Azure Storage offers different replication strategies to choose from based on your requirements.

Replication is an important consideration for ensuring data durability and high availability. Azure Storage offers different replication strategies to choose from based on your requirements.

- Configuring custom domains and secure endpoints allow you to access and secure your storage account in Azure.

Configuring custom domains and secure endpoints allow you to access and secure your storage account in Azure.

Learn more with Copilot

Copilot can assist you in configuring Azure infrastructure solutions. Copilot can compare, recommend, explain, and research products and services where you need more information. Open a Microsoft Edge browser and choose Copilot (top right) or navigate to copilot.microsoft.com. Take a few minutes to try these prompts and extend your learning with Copilot.

- What is an Azure storage account? What type of storage accounts are available?

What is an Azure storage account? What type of storage accounts are available?

- Explain for a nontechnical person Azure data redundancy for storage accounts.

Explain for a nontechnical person Azure data redundancy for storage accounts.

Learn more with Azure documentation

- Storage account overview . This article is your starting point for learning about Azure storage accounts.

Storage account overview . This article is your starting point for learning about Azure storage accounts.

- Azure storage redundancy . This article reviews how to tradeoff cost and availability when selecting a redundancy option.

Azure storage redundancy . This article reviews how to tradeoff cost and availability when selecting a redundancy option.

Learn more with self-paced training

- Create an Azure storage account . Learn how to create an Azure Storage account with the correct options for your business needs.

Create an Azure storage account . Learn how to create an Azure Storage account with the correct options for your business needs.

- Design and implement private access to Azure Services . Learn how to implement private access to Azure Services with Azure Private Link, and virtual network service endpoints.

Design and implement private access to Azure Services . Learn how to implement private access to Azure Services with Azure Private Link, and virtual network service endpoints.

LP 4 M2 - Configure Azure Blob Storage

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-blob-storage/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 4.2.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-blob-storage/1-introduction

Introduction

Azure Blob Storage is an AI-ready service for storing large amounts of unstructured object data. Unstructured data is data that doesn't adhere to a particular data model or definition, such as text or binary data.

In this module, your media company has an extensive library of video clips that are accessed thousands of times a day. The company relies on you to configure Blob Storage for the video data. You plan to use access tiers to reduce cost and improve performance. You're developing a lifecycle management strategy for the older videos. Your plan also includes configuring object replication for failover.

Learning objectives

In this module, you will:

- Understand the purpose and benefits of Azure Blob Storage.

- Create and configure Azure Blob Storage accounts.

- Manage containers and blobs within Azure Blob Storage.

- Optimize blob storage performance and scalability.

- Implement lifecycle management policies to automate data movement and deletion.

- Determine the best pricing plans for your Azure Blob Storage.

Skills measured

The content in the module helps you prepare for Exam AZ-104: Microsoft Azure Administrator .

Prerequisites

Here are some common prerequisites that can be beneficial for understanding and successfully completing this module.

- Basic understanding of cloud computing: Familiarity with cloud computing concepts, such as virtualization, scalability, and pay-as-you-go pricing models, can provide a foundation for understanding how Azure Blob Storage fits into the broader cloud ecosystem.

Basic understanding of cloud computing: Familiarity with cloud computing concepts, such as virtualization, scalability, and pay-as-you-go pricing models, can provide a foundation for understanding how Azure Blob Storage fits into the broader cloud ecosystem.

- Knowledge of Azure fundamentals: Having a basic understanding of Microsoft Azure services and concepts, such as Azure Resource Manager, Azure Storage Accounts, and Azure Virtual Networks, can help you navigate and configure blob storage effectively.

Knowledge of Azure fundamentals: Having a basic understanding of Microsoft Azure services and concepts, such as Azure Resource Manager, Azure Storage Accounts, and Azure Virtual Networks, can help you navigate and configure blob storage effectively.

- Understand fundamental storage concepts like file systems, directories, files, and data replication can be beneficial when working with blob storage.

Understand fundamental storage concepts like file systems, directories, files, and data replication can be beneficial when working with blob storage.

- Experience with Azure portal or Azure CLI: Familiarity with the Azure portal (web-based management interface) or Azure CLI (command-line interface) can help you navigate and configure blob storage resources efficiently.

Experience with Azure portal or Azure CLI: Familiarity with the Azure portal (web-based management interface) or Azure CLI (command-line interface) can help you navigate and configure blob storage resources efficiently.

- Basic programming or scripting skills: While not always required, having some knowledge of programming or scripting languages like PowerShell or Python can be advantageous when automating blob storage configuration tasks.

Basic programming or scripting skills: While not always required, having some knowledge of programming or scripting languages like PowerShell or Python can be advantageous when automating blob storage configuration tasks.

Unit 4.2.2 - Implement Azure Blob Storage

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-blob-storage/2-implement

Implement Azure Blob Storage

Azure Blob Storage is a service that stores unstructured data in the cloud as objects or blobs. Blob stands for Binary Large Object. Blob Storage is also referred to as object storage or container storage .

Things to know about Azure Blob Storage

Let's examine some configuration characteristics of Blob Storage.

- Blob Storage can store any type of text or binary data. Some examples are text documents, images, video files, and application installers.

Blob Storage can store any type of text or binary data. Some examples are text documents, images, video files, and application installers.

- Blob Storage uses three resources to store and manage your data: An Azure storage account Containers in an Azure storage account Blobs in a container

Blob Storage uses three resources to store and manage your data:

- An Azure storage account

- Containers in an Azure storage account

- Blobs in a container

- To implement Blob Storage, you configure several settings: Blob container options. Blob types and upload options. Blob Storage access tiers. Blob lifecycle rules. Blob object replication options.

To implement Blob Storage, you configure several settings:

- Blob container options.

- Blob types and upload options.

- Blob Storage access tiers.

- Blob lifecycle rules.

- Blob object replication options.

Things to consider when implementing Azure Blob Storage

There are many common uses for Blob Storage. Consider the following scenarios and think about your own data needs:

- Consider browser uploads . Use Blob Storage to serve images or documents directly to a browser.

Consider browser uploads . Use Blob Storage to serve images or documents directly to a browser.

- Consider distributed access . Blob Storage can store files for distributed access, such as during an installation process.

Consider distributed access . Blob Storage can store files for distributed access, such as during an installation process.

- Consider streaming data . Stream video and audio by using Blob Storage.

Consider streaming data . Stream video and audio by using Blob Storage.

- Consider archiving and recovery . Blob Storage is a great solution for storing data for backup and restore, disaster recovery, and archiving.

Consider archiving and recovery . Blob Storage is a great solution for storing data for backup and restore, disaster recovery, and archiving.

- Consider application access . You can store data in Blob Storage for analysis by an on-premises or Azure-hosted service.

Consider application access . You can store data in Blob Storage for analysis by an on-premises or Azure-hosted service.

Unit 4.2.3 - Create blob containers

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-blob-storage/3-create-blob-containers

Create blob containers

Azure Blob Storage uses a container resource to group a set of blobs. A blob can't exist by itself in Blob Storage. A blob must be stored in a container resource.

Things to know about containers and blobs

Let's look at the configuration characteristics of containers and blobs.

- All blobs must be in a container.

All blobs must be in a container.

- Containers organize your blob storage.

Containers organize your blob storage.

- A container can store an unlimited number of blobs.

A container can store an unlimited number of blobs.

- An Azure storage account can contain an unlimited number of containers.

An Azure storage account can contain an unlimited number of containers.

- You must create a storage container before you can begin to upload data.

You must create a storage container before you can begin to upload data.

Configure a container

In the Azure portal, you configure settings to create a container for an Azure storage account. As you review these details, consider how you might organize containers in your storage account.

- Name : Enter a name for your container. The name must be unique within the Azure storage account. The name can contain only lowercase letters, numbers, and hyphens. The name must begin with a letter or a number. The minimum length for the name is three characters. The maximum length for the name is 63 characters.

Name : Enter a name for your container. The name must be unique within the Azure storage account.

- The name can contain only lowercase letters, numbers, and hyphens.

- The name must begin with a letter or a number.

- The minimum length for the name is three characters.

- The maximum length for the name is 63 characters.

- Public access level : The access level specifies whether the container and its blobs can be accessed publicly. By default, container data is private and visible only to the account owner. There are three access level choices: Private : (Default) Prohibit anonymous access to the container and blobs. Blob : Allow anonymous public read access for the blobs only. Container : Allow anonymous public read and list access to the entire container, including the blobs.

Public access level : The access level specifies whether the container and its blobs can be accessed publicly. By default, container data is private and visible only to the account owner. There are three access level choices:

- Private : (Default) Prohibit anonymous access to the container and blobs.

- Blob : Allow anonymous public read access for the blobs only.

- Container : Allow anonymous public read and list access to the entire container, including the blobs.

Important

The Blob and Container access levels have no effect unless the storage account's Allow Blob anonymous access setting is enabled. When disabled, all containers remain private regardless of their individual access level settings. Microsoft recommends keeping anonymous access disabled at the account level unless serving public content scenarios.

Unit 4.2.4 - Assign blob access tiers

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-blob-storage/4-create-blob-access-tiers

Assign blob access tiers

Azure Storage supports several access tiers for blob data. These tiers include Hot, Cool, Cold, and Archive. Each access tier is optimized to support a particular pattern of data usage.

Things to know about blob access tiers

Let's examine characteristics of the blob access tiers.

Hot tier

The Hot tier is optimized for frequent reads and writes of objects in the Azure storage account. A good usage case is data that is actively being processed. The hot tier has the highest storage costs, but the lowest access costs.

Cool tier

The Cool tier is optimized for storing large amounts of infrequently accessed data. This tier is intended for data that remains in the Cool tier for at least 30 days. A usage case for the Cool tier is short-term backup and disaster recovery datasets and older media content. This content shouldn't be viewed frequently, but it needs to be immediately available. Storing data in the Cool tier is more cost-effective. The cool tier has lower storage costs and higher access costs compared to the hot tier.

Cold tier

The Cold tier is also optimized for storing large amounts of infrequently accessed data. This tier is intended for data that can remain in the tier for at least 90 days. The cold tier has lower storage costs and higher access costs compared to the cool tier.

Archive tier

The Archive tier is an offline tier that's optimized for data that can tolerate several hours of retrieval latency. Data must remain in the Archive tier for at least 180 days or be subject to an early deletion charge. Data for the Archive tier includes secondary backups, original raw data, and legally required compliance information. This tier is the most cost-effective option for storing data. Accessing data is more expensive in the Archive tier than accessing data in the other tiers.

To access the blob's content, you can rehydrate it to the hot, cool, or cold tier using two methods: Copy Blob (recommended - creates a new blob in an online tier) or Set Blob Tier (changes tier in place). Both methods support Standard priority (up to 15 hours) or High priority (within 1 hour for objects under 10 GB, at higher cost). Use High priority for urgent data retrieval in disaster recovery scenarios.

Compare access tiers

The access options for Azure Blob Storage offer a range of features and support levels to help you optimize your storage costs. As you compare the features and support, think about which access options can best support your application needs.

Comparison

Hot access tier

Cool access tier

Cold access tier

Archive access tier

Availability

99.9%

99%

Availability (RA-GRS reads)

99.99%

99.9%

Latency (time to first byte)

milliseconds

hours

Minimum storage duration

N/A

30 days

90 days

180 days

Unit 4.2.5 - Add blob lifecycle management rules

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-blob-storage/5-add-blob-lifecycle-management-rules

Add blob lifecycle management rules

Every data set has a unique lifecycle. Early in the lifecycle, users tend to access some of the data in the set, but not all of the data. As the data set ages, access to all of the data in the set tends to dramatically reduce. Some data set stays idle in the cloud and is rarely accessed. Some data expires within a few days or months after creation. Other data is actively read and modified throughout the data set lifetime.

Azure Blob Storage supports lifecycle management for data sets. It offers a rich rule-based policy for GPv2 accounts and Premium block blob accounts. Legacy Blob Storage accounts are also supported, but GPv2 is recommended for new deployments. You can use lifecycle policy rules to transition your data to the appropriate access tiers, and set expiration times for the end of a data set's lifecycle.

Things to know about lifecycle management

You can use Azure Blob Storage lifecycle management policy rules to accomplish several tasks.

- Transition blobs to a cooler storage tier (Hot to Cool, Hot to Cold, Hot to Archive, Cool to Cold, Cool to Archive, Cold to Archive) to optimize for performance and cost.

Transition blobs to a cooler storage tier (Hot to Cool, Hot to Cold, Hot to Archive, Cool to Cold, Cool to Archive, Cold to Archive) to optimize for performance and cost.

- Delete current versions of a blob, previous versions of a blob, or blob snapshots at the end of their lifecycles.

Delete current versions of a blob, previous versions of a blob, or blob snapshots at the end of their lifecycles.

- Automatically transition blobs from Cool back to Hot when accessed. This setting optimizes for unpredictable access patterns without early deletion charges.

Automatically transition blobs from Cool back to Hot when accessed. This setting optimizes for unpredictable access patterns without early deletion charges.

- Apply rules to an entire storage account, to select containers, or to a subset of blobs using name prefixes or blob index tags as filters.

Apply rules to an entire storage account, to select containers, or to a subset of blobs using name prefixes or blob index tags as filters.

Business scenario

Consider a scenario where data is frequently accessed in the early stages of the lifecycle, but only occasionally after two weeks. After the first month, the data set is rarely accessed. In this scenario, the Hot tier of Blob Storage is best during the early stages. Cool tier storage is most appropriate for occasional access. Archive tier storage is the best option after the data ages over a month. To achieve this transition, lifecycle management policy rules are available to move aging data to cooler tiers.

Configure lifecycle management policy rules

In the Azure portal, you create lifecycle management policy rules for your Azure storage account by specifying several settings. For each rule, you create If - Then block conditions to transition or expire data based on your specifications. As you review these details, consider how you can set up lifecycle management policy rules for your data sets.

- If : The If clause sets the evaluation clause for the policy rule. When the If clause evaluates to true, the Then clause is executed. Use the If clause to set the time period to apply to the blob data. The lifecycle management feature checks if the data is accessed or modified according to the specified time. More than (days ago) : The number of days to use in the evaluation condition.

If : The If clause sets the evaluation clause for the policy rule. When the If clause evaluates to true, the Then clause is executed. Use the If clause to set the time period to apply to the blob data. The lifecycle management feature checks if the data is accessed or modified according to the specified time.

- More than (days ago) : The number of days to use in the evaluation condition.

- Then : The Then clause sets the action clause for the policy rule. When the If clause evaluates to true, the Then clause is executed. Use the Then clause to set the transition action for the blob data. The lifecycle management feature transitions the data based on the setting. Move to cool storage : The blob data is transitioned to Cool tier storage. Move to cold storage : The blob data is transitioned to Cold tier storage. Move to archive storage : The blob data is transitioned to Archive tier storage. Delete the blob : The blob data is deleted.

Then : The Then clause sets the action clause for the policy rule. When the If clause evaluates to true, the Then clause is executed. Use the Then clause to set the transition action for the blob data. The lifecycle management feature transitions the data based on the setting.

- Move to cool storage : The blob data is transitioned to Cool tier storage.

- Move to cold storage : The blob data is transitioned to Cold tier storage.

- Move to archive storage : The blob data is transitioned to Archive tier storage.

- Delete the blob : The blob data is deleted.

By designing policy rules to adjust storage tiers in respect to the age of data, you can design the least expensive storage options for your needs.

Tip

Expand your knowledge in the Manage the Azure Blob storage lifecycle training module.

Unit 4.2.6 - Determine blob object replication

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-blob-storage/6-determine-blob-object-replication

Determine blob object replication

Object replication copies blobs in a container asynchronously according to policy rules that you configure.

Replication includes the blob content, metadata properties, and versions. The following illustration shows an example of asynchronous replication of blob containers between regions.

Things to know about blob object replication

There are several considerations to keep in mind when planning your configuration for blob object replication.

- Object replication requires that Blob versioning is enabled on both the source and destination accounts. When blob versioning is enabled, you can access earlier versions of a blob. This access lets you recover your modified or deleted data.

Object replication requires that Blob versioning is enabled on both the source and destination accounts. When blob versioning is enabled, you can access earlier versions of a blob. This access lets you recover your modified or deleted data.

- Object replication doesn't support blob snapshots. Any snapshots on a blob in the source account aren't replicated to the destination account.

Object replication doesn't support blob snapshots. Any snapshots on a blob in the source account aren't replicated to the destination account.

- Object replication is supported when the source and destination accounts are in the Hot, Cool, or Cold tier. The source and destination accounts can be in different tiers.

Object replication is supported when the source and destination accounts are in the Hot, Cool, or Cold tier. The source and destination accounts can be in different tiers.

- When you configure object replication, you create a replication policy that specifies the source Azure storage account and the destination storage account.

When you configure object replication, you create a replication policy that specifies the source Azure storage account and the destination storage account.

- A replication policy includes one or more rules that specify a source container and a destination container. The policy identifies the blobs in the source container to replicate.

A replication policy includes one or more rules that specify a source container and a destination container. The policy identifies the blobs in the source container to replicate.

Things to consider when configuring blob object replication

There are many benefits to using blob object replication. Consider the following scenarios and think about how replication can be a part of your Blob Storage strategy.

- Consider latency reductions . Minimize latency with blob object replication. You can reduce latency for read requests by enabling clients to consume data from a region that's in closer physical proximity.

Consider latency reductions . Minimize latency with blob object replication. You can reduce latency for read requests by enabling clients to consume data from a region that's in closer physical proximity.

- Consider efficiency for compute workloads . Improve efficiency for compute workloads by using blob object replication. With object replication, compute workloads can process the same sets of blobs in different regions.

Consider efficiency for compute workloads . Improve efficiency for compute workloads by using blob object replication. With object replication, compute workloads can process the same sets of blobs in different regions.

- Consider data distribution . Optimize your configuration for data distribution. You can process or analyze data in a single location and then replicate only the results to other regions.

Consider data distribution . Optimize your configuration for data distribution. You can process or analyze data in a single location and then replicate only the results to other regions.

- Consider costs benefits . Manage your configuration and optimize your storage policies. After your data is replicated, you can reduce costs by moving the data to the Archive tier by using lifecycle management policies.

Consider costs benefits . Manage your configuration and optimize your storage policies. After your data is replicated, you can reduce costs by moving the data to the Archive tier by using lifecycle management policies.

Unit 4.2.7 - Manage blobs

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-blob-storage/7-upload-blobs

Manage blobs

A blob can be any type of data and any size file. Azure Storage offers three types of blobs: block blob , page blob , and append blob .

Things to know about blob types

Let's take a closer look at the characteristics of blob types.

- Block blobs . A block blob consists of blocks of data that are assembled to make a blob. Most Blob Storage scenarios use block blobs. Block blobs are ideal for storing text and binary data in the cloud, like files, images, and videos. The block blob type is the default type for a new blob. When you're creating a new blob, if you don't choose a specific type, the new blob is created as a block blob.

Block blobs . A block blob consists of blocks of data that are assembled to make a blob. Most Blob Storage scenarios use block blobs. Block blobs are ideal for storing text and binary data in the cloud, like files, images, and videos. The block blob type is the default type for a new blob. When you're creating a new blob, if you don't choose a specific type, the new blob is created as a block blob.

- Append blobs . An append blob is similar to a block blob because the append blob also consists of blocks of data. The blocks of data in an append blob are optimized for append operations. Append blobs are useful for logging scenarios, where the amount of data can increase as the logging operation continues.

Append blobs . An append blob is similar to a block blob because the append blob also consists of blocks of data. The blocks of data in an append blob are optimized for append operations. Append blobs are useful for logging scenarios, where the amount of data can increase as the logging operation continues.

- Page blobs . A page blob can be up to 8 TB in size. Page blobs are more efficient for frequent read/write operations. Azure Virtual Machines uses page blobs for operating system disks and data disks.

Page blobs . A page blob can be up to 8 TB in size. Page blobs are more efficient for frequent read/write operations. Azure Virtual Machines uses page blobs for operating system disks and data disks.

Note

After you create a blob, you can't change its type.

Things to consider when managing blob storage

You can use the portal to upload and manage blobs. This option is good for a few files. After you identify the files to upload, you choose the blob type and block size, and the container folder. You also set the access tier and the encryption scope.

For larger numbers of files, it's best to use a tool. Review the following options and consider which tools would suit your configuration needs.

- Azure Storage Explorer . Upload, download, and manage blobs, files, queues, and tables, as well as Azure Data Lake Storage entities and managed disks. You can also view, edit, and manage resources, preview data, and configure storage permissions and access controls.

- AzCopy . An easy-to-use command-line tool for Windows and Linux. You can copy data to and from Blob Storage, across containers, and across storage accounts.

AzCopy . An easy-to-use command-line tool for Windows and Linux. You can copy data to and from Blob Storage, across containers, and across storage accounts.

- Azure Data Box Disk . A service for transferring on-premises data to Blob Storage when large datasets or network constraints make uploading data over the wire unrealistic. You can use Azure Data Box Disk to request solid-state disks (SSDs) from Microsoft. You can copy your data to those disks and ship them back to Microsoft to be uploaded into Blob Storage.

Azure Data Box Disk . A service for transferring on-premises data to Blob Storage when large datasets or network constraints make uploading data over the wire unrealistic. You can use Azure Data Box Disk to request solid-state disks (SSDs) from Microsoft. You can copy your data to those disks and ship them back to Microsoft to be uploaded into Blob Storage.

Unit 4.2.8 - Determine Blob Storage pricing

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-blob-storage/8-determine-storage-pricing

Determine Blob Storage pricing

Understanding your access patterns and correlating them with your durability and availability needs helps you to best manage your Azure Blob Storage costs. The primary tool for estimating these costs is the Azure pricing calculator. The pricing tool can calculate migration, monthly estimates, and future pricing estimates based on the workload-driven input that you specify. In general, the cost of block blob storage depends on:

- Volume of data stored per month.

- Quantity and types of operations performed, along with any data transfer costs.

- Data redundancy option selected.

You can use the Azure Pricing Calculator to estimate your storage costs.

Things to know about pricing for Blob Storage

Review the following billing considerations for an Azure storage account and Blob Storage.

- Performance tiers . The Blob Storage tier determines the amount of data stored and the cost for storing that data. As the performance tier gets cooler, the per-gigabyte cost decreases.

Performance tiers . The Blob Storage tier determines the amount of data stored and the cost for storing that data. As the performance tier gets cooler, the per-gigabyte cost decreases.

- Data access costs . Data access charges increase as the tier gets cooler. For data in the Cool, Cold, and Archive tiers, you're billed a per-gigabyte data access charge for read actions.

Data access costs . Data access charges increase as the tier gets cooler. For data in the Cool, Cold, and Archive tiers, you're billed a per-gigabyte data access charge for read actions.

- Transaction costs . There's a per-transaction charge for all tiers. The charge increases as the tier gets cooler.

Transaction costs . There's a per-transaction charge for all tiers. The charge increases as the tier gets cooler.

- Geo-replication data transfer costs . This charge only applies to accounts that have geo-replication configured. Geo-replication data transfer incurs a per-gigabyte charge.

Geo-replication data transfer costs . This charge only applies to accounts that have geo-replication configured. Geo-replication data transfer incurs a per-gigabyte charge.

- Outbound data transfer costs . Outbound data transfers incur billing for bandwidth usage on a per-gigabyte basis. This billing is consistent with general-purpose Azure storage accounts.

Outbound data transfer costs . Outbound data transfers incur billing for bandwidth usage on a per-gigabyte basis. This billing is consistent with general-purpose Azure storage accounts.

- Changes to the storage tier . If you change the account storage tier from Cool to Hot, you incur a charge equal to reading all the data existing in the storage account. Changing the account storage tier from Hot to Cool incurs a charge equal to writing all the data into the Cool tier (GPv2 accounts only).

Changes to the storage tier . If you change the account storage tier from Cool to Hot, you incur a charge equal to reading all the data existing in the storage account. Changing the account storage tier from Hot to Cool incurs a charge equal to writing all the data into the Cool tier (GPv2 accounts only).

Unit 4.2.9 - Exercise - Provide storage for the public website

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-blob-storage/9-simulation-blobs

Exercise - Provide storage for the public website

Exercise scenario

The company website supplies product images, videos, marketing literature, and customer success stories. Customers are located worldwide and demand is rapidly expanding. The content is mission-critical and requires low latency load times. It’s important to keep track of the document versions and to quickly restore documents if they’re deleted.

Job skills

- Create a storage account with high availability.

- Ensure the storage account has anonymous public access.

- Create a blob storage container for the website documents.

- Enable soft delete so files can be easily restored.

- Enable blob versioning.

Note

Estimated time: 30 minutes.

To complete this exercise, you need an Azure subscription .

Launch the exercise, and follow the instructions. When finished, be sure to return to this page so you can continue learning.

Unit 4.2.10 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-blob-storage/10-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Your organization has an extensive video library. Users access the library thousands of times a day. You're configuring Azure Blob Storage for the video data. The admin team asks for guidance about the supported access tiers and object replication for failover. The executive team wants an implementation that can help reduce cost and improve performance.

Answer the following questions

Choose the best response for each question.

Unit 4.2.11 - Summary and resources

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-blob-storage/11-summary-resources

Summary and resources

In this module, you learned about Azure Blob Storage and how to configure it. You discovered that Blob Storage is Microsoft's object storage solution for the cloud. You learned Azure blob storage is optimized for storing massive amounts of unstructured data like text or binary files. You explored the features of Blob Storage and its use cases. You also learned how to configure Blob Storage, including choosing the appropriate access tiers to reduce cost and improve performance. And, you learned about creating a lifecycle management strategy, and configuring object replication for failover.

The main takeaways from this module are:

- Azure Blob Storage is a powerful solution for storing unstructured data in the cloud, such as text documents, images, and videos.

- Blob Storage offers different access tiers (Hot, Cool, Cold, and Archive) to optimize performance and cost based on the usage patterns of your data.

- You can configure lifecycle management policies to automatically transition data between access tiers and set expiration times for data.

- Object replication allows you to asynchronously copy blobs between containers in different regions, providing redundancy and reducing latency for read requests.

Learn more with Copilot

Copilot can assist you in configuring Azure infrastructure solutions. Copilot can compare, recommend, explain, and research products and services where you need more information. Open a Microsoft Edge browser and choose Copilot (top right) or navigate to copilot.microsoft.com. Take a few minutes to try these prompts and extend your learning with Copilot.

- What are common administration tasks associated with Azure blob storage?

What are common administration tasks associated with Azure blob storage?

- How is Azure blob storage priced?

How is Azure blob storage priced?

Learn more with Azure documentation

- Azure Blob Storage documentation - Microsoft Azure's official documentation provides comprehensive information on configuring and managing blob storage. You can find detailed guides, tutorials, and examples to help you navigate through different aspects of blob storage configuration.

Azure Blob Storage documentation - Microsoft Azure's official documentation provides comprehensive information on configuring and managing blob storage. You can find detailed guides, tutorials, and examples to help you navigate through different aspects of blob storage configuration.

- Azure Blob Storage Concepts - This article provides an overview of the key concepts related to Azure Blob Storage, including storage accounts, containers, and blobs. It explains how to create and manage these entities and covers various configuration options.

Azure Blob Storage Concepts - This article provides an overview of the key concepts related to Azure Blob Storage, including storage accounts, containers, and blobs. It explains how to create and manage these entities and covers various configuration options.

- Azure Blob Storage Security - Understanding the security aspects of blob storage is crucial for proper configuration. This article explores authentication, authorization, and encryption options available in Azure Blob Storage. It also covers best practices for securing your blob storage resources.

Azure Blob Storage Security - Understanding the security aspects of blob storage is crucial for proper configuration. This article explores authentication, authorization, and encryption options available in Azure Blob Storage. It also covers best practices for securing your blob storage resources.

- Azure Blob Storage Performance and Scalability - This article delves into performance considerations when configuring blob storage. The module covers the storage account type, and optimizing data transfer.

Azure Blob Storage Performance and Scalability - This article delves into performance considerations when configuring blob storage. The module covers the storage account type, and optimizing data transfer.

- Azure Blob Storage Lifecycle Management - Blob storage lifecycle management allows you to automate the movement and deletion of data based on predefined rules. This article explains how to configure and manage lifecycle policies to optimize storage costs and improve data management.

Azure Blob Storage Lifecycle Management - Blob storage lifecycle management allows you to automate the movement and deletion of data based on predefined rules. This article explains how to configure and manage lifecycle policies to optimize storage costs and improve data management.

LP 4 M3 - Configure Azure Storage security

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-security/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 4.3.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-security/1-introduction

Introduction

Azure Storage provides a comprehensive set of security capabilities that work together to enable developers to build secure applications.

In this module, your company is storing sensitive data in Azure Storage, including personal information. The data is used internally and by external application developers. You're responsible for ensuring the data is secure for all users. You're tasked with providing configuration solutions to grant secure access to the information.

Learning objectives

In this module, you learn how to:

- Configure a shared access signature, including the uniform resource identifier (URI) and SAS parameters.

- Configure Azure Storage encryption.

- Implement customer-managed keys.

- Recommend opportunities to improve Azure Storage security.

Skills measured

The content in the module helps you prepare for Exam AZ-104: Microsoft Azure Administrator .

Prerequisites

- Familiarity with navigating the Azure portal.

Unit 4.3.2 - Review Azure Storage security strategies

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-security/2-review-strategies

Review Azure Storage security strategies

Administrators use different strategies to ensure their data is secure. Common approaches include encryption, authentication, authorization, and user access control with credentials, file permissions, and private signatures. Azure Storage offers a suite of security capabilities based on common strategies to help you secure your data.

Note

The video refers to Active Directory, which is now branded as Microsoft Entra ID.

Things to know about Azure Storage security strategies

Let's look at some characteristics of Azure Storage security. As you go through this module, consider defense in depth. How can you apply storage security features to this concept?

- Encryption at rest . Storage Service Encryption (SSE) with a 256-bit Advanced Encryption Standard (AES) cipher encrypts all data written to Azure Storage. When you read data from Azure Storage, Azure Storage decrypts the data before returning it. This process incurs no extra charges and doesn't degrade performance. Encryption at rest includes encrypting virtual hard disks (VHDs) with Azure Disk Encryption. This encryption uses BitLocker for Windows images, and uses dm-crypt for Linux.

Encryption at rest . Storage Service Encryption (SSE) with a 256-bit Advanced Encryption Standard (AES) cipher encrypts all data written to Azure Storage. When you read data from Azure Storage, Azure Storage decrypts the data before returning it. This process incurs no extra charges and doesn't degrade performance. Encryption at rest includes encrypting virtual hard disks (VHDs) with Azure Disk Encryption. This encryption uses BitLocker for Windows images, and uses dm-crypt for Linux.

- Encryption in transit . You can configure your storage account to only accept requests from secure connections by setting the Secure transfer required property for the storage account. Existing accounts should explicitly disallow TLS 1.0 and 1.1, which are deprecated.

Encryption in transit . You can configure your storage account to only accept requests from secure connections by setting the Secure transfer required property for the storage account. Existing accounts should explicitly disallow TLS 1.0 and 1.1, which are deprecated.

- Encryption models . Azure supports various encryption models, including server-side encryption that uses service-managed keys, customer-managed keys in Key Vault, or customer-managed keys on customer-controlled hardware. With client-side encryption, you can manage and store keys on-premises or in another secure location.

Encryption models . Azure supports various encryption models, including server-side encryption that uses service-managed keys, customer-managed keys in Key Vault, or customer-managed keys on customer-controlled hardware. With client-side encryption, you can manage and store keys on-premises or in another secure location.

- Authorize requests . For optimal security, Microsoft recommends using Microsoft Entra ID with managed identities to authorize requests against blob, queue, and table data, whenever possible. Authorization with Microsoft Entra ID and managed identities provides superior security and ease of use over Shared Key authorization.

Authorize requests . For optimal security, Microsoft recommends using Microsoft Entra ID with managed identities to authorize requests against blob, queue, and table data, whenever possible. Authorization with Microsoft Entra ID and managed identities provides superior security and ease of use over Shared Key authorization.

- RBAC . RBAC ensures that resources in your storage account are accessible only when you want them to be, and to only those users or applications whom you grant access. Assign RBAC roles scoped to an Azure storage account.

RBAC . RBAC ensures that resources in your storage account are accessible only when you want them to be, and to only those users or applications whom you grant access. Assign RBAC roles scoped to an Azure storage account.

- Storage analytics . Azure Storage Analytics performs logging for a storage account. You can use this data to trace requests, analyze usage trends, and diagnose issues with your storage account.

Storage analytics . Azure Storage Analytics performs logging for a storage account. You can use this data to trace requests, analyze usage trends, and diagnose issues with your storage account.

Tip

The Microsoft storage cloud security benchmark provides recommendations on how you can secure your cloud storage solutions.

Things to consider when using authorization security

Review the following strategies for authorizing requests to Azure Storage. Think about what security strategies would work for your Azure Storage.

Authorization strategy

Description

Microsoft Entra ID

Microsoft Entra ID is Microsoft's cloud-based identity and access management service. With Microsoft Entra ID, you can assign fine-grained access to users, groups, or applications by using role-based access control.

Shared Key

Access is authorized with an account access key. The key can be the primary or secondary access key. To enforce Entra ID authorization, disable the Shared Key at the storage account level.

Shared access signatures

A SAS delegates access to a particular resource in your Azure storage account with specified permissions and for a specified time interval.

Anonymous access to containers and blobs

Anonymous public access is disabled by default on new storage accounts. Microsoft recommends keeping anonymous access disabled for accounts containing sensitive data.

Unit 4.3.3 - Create shared access signatures

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-security/3-create-shared-access-signatures

Create shared access signatures

A shared access signature (SAS) is a uniform resource identifier (URI) that grants restricted access rights to Azure Storage resources. SAS is a secure way to share your storage resources without compromising your account keys.

You can provide a SAS to clients who shouldn't have access to your storage account key. By distributing a SAS URI to these clients, you grant them access to a resource for a specified period of time. You'd typically use a SAS for a service where users read and write their data to your storage account.

- A user delegation SAS is secured with Microsoft Entra credentials and also by the permissions specified for the SAS. A user delegation SAS is supported for Blob Storage and Data Lake Storage,

A user delegation SAS is secured with Microsoft Entra credentials and also by the permissions specified for the SAS. A user delegation SAS is supported for Blob Storage and Data Lake Storage,

- An account-level SAS to allow access to anything that a service-level SAS can allow, plus other resources and abilities. For example, you can use an account-level SAS to allow the ability to create file systems.

An account-level SAS to allow access to anything that a service-level SAS can allow, plus other resources and abilities. For example, you can use an account-level SAS to allow the ability to create file systems.

- A service-level SAS to allow access to specific resources in a storage account. You'd use this type of SAS, for example, to allow an app to retrieve a list of files in a file system, or to download a file.

A service-level SAS to allow access to specific resources in a storage account. You'd use this type of SAS, for example, to allow an app to retrieve a list of files in a file system, or to download a file.

- A stored access policy can provide another level of control when you use a service-level SAS on the server side. You can group SASs and provide other restrictions by using a stored access policy.

A stored access policy can provide another level of control when you use a service-level SAS on the server side. You can group SASs and provide other restrictions by using a stored access policy.

Recommendations for managing risks

Let's look at some recommendations that can help mitigate risks when working with a SAS.

Recommendation

Description

Always use HTTPS for creation and distribution

If a SAS is passed over HTTP and intercepted, an attacker can intercept and use the SAS. These man-in-the-middle attacks can compromise sensitive data or allow for data corruption by the malicious user.

Reference stored access policies where possible

Stored access policies give you the option to revoke permissions without having to regenerate the Azure storage account keys. Set the storage account key expiration date far in the future.

Set near-term expiry times for an unplanned SAS

If a SAS is compromised, you can mitigate attacks by limiting the SAS validity to a short time. This practice is important if you can't reference a stored access policy. Near-term expiration times also limit the amount of data that can be written to a blob by limiting the time available to upload to it.

Require clients automatically renew the SAS

Require your clients to renew the SAS well before the expiration date. By renewing early, you allow time for retries if the service providing the SAS is unavailable.

Plan carefully for the SAS start time

If you set the start time for a SAS to now, then due to clock skew (differences in current time according to different machines), failures might be observed intermittently for the first few minutes. In general, set the start time to at least 15 minutes in the past. Or, don't set a specific start time, which causes the SAS to be valid immediately in all cases. The same conditions generally apply to the expiry time. You might observe up to 15 minutes of clock skew in either direction on any request. For clients that use a REST API version earlier than 2012-02-12, the maximum duration for a SAS that doesn't reference a stored access policy is 1 hour. Any policies that specify a longer term fail.

Define minimum access permissions for resources

A security best practice is to provide a user with the minimum required privileges. If a user only needs read access to a single entity, then grant them read access to that single entity, and not read/write/delete access to all entities. This practice also helps lessen the damage if a SAS is compromised because the SAS has less power in the hands of an attacker.

Validate data written by using a SAS

When a client application writes data to your Azure storage account, keep in mind there can be problems with the data. If your application requires validated or authorized data, validate the data after written, but before used. This practice also protects against corrupt or malicious data being written to your account, either by a user who properly acquired the SAS, or by a user exploiting a leaked SAS.

Don't assume a SAS is always the correct choice

In some scenarios, the risks associated with a particular operation against your Azure storage account outweigh the benefits of using a SAS. For such operations, create a middle-tier service that writes to your storage account after performing business rule validation, authentication, and auditing. Also, sometimes it's easier to manage access in other ways. If you want to make all blobs in a container publicly readable, you can make the container Public, rather than providing a SAS to every client for access.

Unit 4.3.4 - Identify URI and SAS parameters

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-security/4-identify-uri-sas-parameters

Identify URI and SAS parameters

When you create your shared access signature (SAS), a uniform resource identifier (URI) is created by using parameters and tokens. The URI consists of your Azure Storage resource URI and the SAS token.

Things to know about URI definitions

Let's look at an example URI definition and examine the parameters. This example creates a service-level SAS that grants read and write permissions to a blob. Consider how you might configure the parameters to support your Azure Storage resources.

https://myaccount.blob.core.windows.net/?restype=service&comp=properties&sv=2015-04-05&ss=bf&st=2015-04-29T22%3A18%3A26Z&se=2015-04-30T02%3A23%3A26Z&sr=b&sp=rw&sip=168.1.5.60-168.1.5.70&spr=https&sig=F%6GRVAZ5Cdj2Pw4tgU7IlSTkWgn7bUkkAg8P6HESXwmf%4B

Parameter

Example

Description

Resource URI

https://myaccount. blob .core.windows.net/ ?restype= service &amp;comp=properties

https://myaccount.

blob

.core.windows.net/

?restype=

service

&amp;comp=properties

Defines the Azure Storage endpoint and other parameters. This example defines an endpoint for Blob Storage and indicates that the SAS applies to service-level operations. When the URI is used with GET , the Storage properties are retrieved. When the URI is used with SET , the Storage properties are configured.

GET

SET

Storage version

sv =2015-04-05

sv

=2015-04-05

For Azure Storage version 2012-02-12 and later, this parameter indicates the version to use. This example indicates that version 2015-04-05 (April 5, 2015) should be used.

Storage service

ss =bf

ss

=bf

Specifies the Azure Storage to which the SAS applies. This example indicates that the SAS applies to Blob Storage and Azure Files.

Start time

st =2015-04-29T22%3A18%3A26Z

st

=2015-04-29T22%3A18%3A26Z

(Optional) Specifies the start time for the SAS in UTC time. This example sets the start time as April 29, 2015 22:18:26 UTC. If you want the SAS to be valid immediately, omit the start time.

Expiry time

se =2015-04-30T02%3A23%3A26Z

se

=2015-04-30T02%3A23%3A26Z

Specifies the expiration time for the SAS in UTC time. This example sets the expiry time as April 30, 2015 02:23:26 UTC.

Resource

sr =b

sr

=b

Specifies which resources are accessible via the SAS. This example specifies that the accessible resource is in Blob Storage.

Permissions

sp =rw

sp

=rw

Lists the permissions to grant. This example grants access to read and write operations.

IP range

sip =168.1.5.60-168.1.5.70

sip

=168.1.5.60-168.1.5.70

Specifies a range of IP addresses from which a request is accepted. This example defines the IP address range 168.1.5.60 through 168.1.5.70.

Protocol

spr =https

spr

=https

Specifies the protocols from which Azure Storage accepts the SAS. This example indicates that only requests by using HTTPS are accepted.

Signature

sig =F%6GRVAZ5Cdj2Pw4tgU7Il STkWgn7bUkkAg8P6HESXwmf%4B

sig

=F%6GRVAZ5Cdj2Pw4tgU7Il

STkWgn7bUkkAg8P6HESXwmf%4B

Specifies that access to the resource is authenticated by using a Hash-Based Message Authentication Code (HMAC) signature. The signature is computed with a key using the SHA256 algorithm, and encoded by using Base64 encoding.

Tip

Continue your learning with the Implement shared access signatures training modules.

Unit 4.3.5 - Determine Azure Storage encryption

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-security/5-determine-storage-service-encryption

Determine Azure Storage encryption

Azure Storage encryption for data at rest protects your data by ensuring your organizational security and compliance commitments are met. The encryption and decryption processes happen automatically. Because your data is secured by default, you don't need to modify your code or applications.

When you create a storage account, Azure generates two 512-bit storage account access keys for that account. These keys can be used to authorize access to data in your storage account via Shared Key authorization, or via SAS tokens that are signed with the shared key.

Microsoft recommends that you use Azure Key Vault to manage your access keys, and that you regularly rotate and regenerate your keys. Azure Key Vault supports automatic key rotation policies, allowing you to define rotation schedules (for example, every 90 days) that rotate keys automatically. You can also manually rotate your keys when needed.

Things to know about Azure Storage encryption

Examine the following characteristics of Azure Storage encryption.

- Data is automatically encrypted before written to Azure storage.

Data is automatically encrypted before written to Azure storage.

- Data is automatically decrypted when retrieved.

Data is automatically decrypted when retrieved.

- Azure Storage encryption, encryption at rest, decryption, and key management are transparent to users.

Azure Storage encryption, encryption at rest, decryption, and key management are transparent to users.

- All data written to Azure Storage is encrypted through 256-bit advanced encryption standard (AES) encryption. AES is one of the strongest block ciphers available.

All data written to Azure Storage is encrypted through 256-bit advanced encryption standard (AES) encryption. AES is one of the strongest block ciphers available.

- Azure Storage encryption is enabled for all new and existing storage accounts and can't be disabled.

Azure Storage encryption is enabled for all new and existing storage accounts and can't be disabled.

Configure Azure Storage encryption

In the Azure portal, you configure Azure Storage encryption by specifying the encryption type. You can manage the keys yourself, or you can have the keys managed by Microsoft. Consider how you might implement Azure Storage encryption for your storage security.

- Infrastructure encryption . Infrastructure encryption can be enabled for the entire storage account, or for an encryption scope within an account. When infrastructure encryption is enabled for a storage account or an encryption scope, data is encrypted twice—once at the service level and once at the infrastructure level—with two different encryption algorithms and two different keys.

Infrastructure encryption . Infrastructure encryption can be enabled for the entire storage account, or for an encryption scope within an account. When infrastructure encryption is enabled for a storage account or an encryption scope, data is encrypted twice—once at the service level and once at the infrastructure level—with two different encryption algorithms and two different keys.

- Platform-managed keys . Platform-managed keys (PMKs) are encryption keys generated, stored, and managed entirely by Azure. Customers don't interact with PMKs. The keys used for Azure Data Encryption-at-Rest, for instance, are PMKs by default.

Platform-managed keys . Platform-managed keys (PMKs) are encryption keys generated, stored, and managed entirely by Azure. Customers don't interact with PMKs. The keys used for Azure Data Encryption-at-Rest, for instance, are PMKs by default.

- Customer-managed keys . Customer managed keys (CMK), on the other hand, are keys read, created, deleted, updated, and/or administered by one or more customers. Keys stored in a customer-owned key vault or hardware security module (HSM) are CMKs. Bring Your Own Key (BYOK) is a CMK scenario in which a customer imports (brings) keys from an outside storage location. This topic is discussed in more detail on the next page.

Customer-managed keys . Customer managed keys (CMK), on the other hand, are keys read, created, deleted, updated, and/or administered by one or more customers. Keys stored in a customer-owned key vault or hardware security module (HSM) are CMKs. Bring Your Own Key (BYOK) is a CMK scenario in which a customer imports (brings) keys from an outside storage location. This topic is discussed in more detail on the next page.

Unit 4.3.6 - Create customer-managed keys

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-security/6-create-customer-managed-keys

Create customer-managed keys

For your Azure Storage security solution, you can use Azure Key Vault to manage your encryption keys. The Azure Key Vault APIs can be used to generate encryption keys. You can also create your own encryption keys and store them in a key vault.

Things to know about customer-managed keys

Consider the following characteristics of customer-managed keys.

- By creating your own keys (referred to as customer-managed keys), you have more flexibility and greater control.

By creating your own keys (referred to as customer-managed keys), you have more flexibility and greater control.

- You can create, disable, audit, rotate, and define access controls for your encryption keys.

You can create, disable, audit, rotate, and define access controls for your encryption keys.

- Customer-managed keys can be used with Azure Storage encryption. You can use a new key or an existing key vault and key. The Azure storage account and the key vault must be in the same region, but they can be in different subscriptions.

Customer-managed keys can be used with Azure Storage encryption. You can use a new key or an existing key vault and key. The Azure storage account and the key vault must be in the same region, but they can be in different subscriptions.

- Customer-managed keys are stored in a customer-owned Azure Key Vault or Azure Key Vault Managed HSM. Managed HSM provides FIPS 140-2 Level 3 validation for organizations with the highest compliance requirements.

Customer-managed keys are stored in a customer-owned Azure Key Vault or Azure Key Vault Managed HSM. Managed HSM provides FIPS 140-2 Level 3 validation for organizations with the highest compliance requirements.

Configure customer-managed keys

In the Azure portal, you can configure customer-managed encryption keys. You can create your own keys, or you can have the keys managed by Microsoft. Consider how you might use Azure Key Vault to create your own customer-managed encryption keys.

- Encryption type : Choose how the encryption key is managed: by Microsoft or by yourself (customer).

Encryption type : Choose how the encryption key is managed: by Microsoft or by yourself (customer).

- Encryption key : Specify an encryption key by entering a URI, or select a key from an existing key vault.

Encryption key : Specify an encryption key by entering a URI, or select a key from an existing key vault.

Tip

Expand your understanding of storage security in the Plan and implement security for storage training module.

Unit 4.3.7 - Apply Azure Storage security best practices

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-security/7-apply-best-practices

Apply Azure Storage security best practices

Storage insights provides comprehensive monitoring of your Azure Storage accounts. Storage Insights delivers a unified view of your Azure Storage services performance, capacity, and availability.

What are the benefits of Storage insights?

- Detailed Metrics and Logs . Azure Storage Insights offers detailed metrics, logs, and diagnostic information that enhance visibility into storage operations. Insights helps in monitoring key performance indicators (KPIs) such as latency, throughput, capacity utilization, and transactions.

Detailed Metrics and Logs . Azure Storage Insights offers detailed metrics, logs, and diagnostic information that enhance visibility into storage operations. Insights helps in monitoring key performance indicators (KPIs) such as latency, throughput, capacity utilization, and transactions.

- Enhanced Security and Compliance . By using Azure Storage Insights, you can ensure enhanced security and compliance. It provides actionable insights and alerts that help in swiftly identifying and resolving security issues.

Enhanced Security and Compliance . By using Azure Storage Insights, you can ensure enhanced security and compliance. It provides actionable insights and alerts that help in swiftly identifying and resolving security issues.

Role-Based Access Control (RBAC) . Azure Storage Insights integrates with Azure's security features, including role-based access control (RBAC), Microsoft Entra ID, connection strings, and access control list (ACL) permissions. RBAC ensures secure access to your data and resources.

- Unified View . It delivers a unified view of your Azure Storage services' performance, capacity, and availability, which is crucial for maintaining the security and efficiency of your storage accounts.

Unified View . It delivers a unified view of your Azure Storage services' performance, capacity, and availability, which is crucial for maintaining the security and efficiency of your storage accounts.

When to use Storage Insights

- Real-Time Monitoring . Azure Storage Insights enables real-time monitoring of storage accounts, allowing you to track usage trends, monitor performance, and set up alerts for any anomalies.

Real-Time Monitoring . Azure Storage Insights enables real-time monitoring of storage accounts, allowing you to track usage trends, monitor performance, and set up alerts for any anomalies.

- Security Auditing . It aids in security auditing by providing comprehensive monitoring and detailed logs, which are essential for ensuring compliance and identifying any security issues.

Security Auditing . It aids in security auditing by providing comprehensive monitoring and detailed logs, which are essential for ensuring compliance and identifying any security issues.

- Health Analysis and Optimization . The tool helps in health analysis and optimization of storage accounts, ensuring security and optimal performance.

Health Analysis and Optimization . The tool helps in health analysis and optimization of storage accounts, ensuring security and optimal performance.

When to use Microsoft Defender for Storage

While Storage Insights provides passive monitoring and historical analysis, Microsoft Defender for Storage offers proactive threat detection for active security threats.

Key capabilities

- Malware scanning . Automatically scans blob uploads for malware and viruses.

Malware scanning . Automatically scans blob uploads for malware and viruses.

- Sensitive data threat detection . Identifies when personally identifiable information (PII) or credentials are stored inappropriately.

Sensitive data threat detection . Identifies when personally identifiable information (PII) or credentials are stored inappropriately.

- Activity-based threat detection . Monitors for unusual access patterns, suspicious download volumes, and hash reputation analysis.

Activity-based threat detection . Monitors for unusual access patterns, suspicious download volumes, and hash reputation analysis.

Microsoft Defender for Storage complements Storage Insights by providing active threat detection rather than reactive monitoring and historical reporting.

Unit 4.3.8 - Exercise: Manage Azure Storage

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-security/8-simulation-storage

Exercise: Manage Azure Storage

Lab scenario

In this lab, you learn to create storage accounts for Azure blobs and Azure files. You learn to configure and secure blob containers. You also learn to use Storage Browser to configure and secure Azure file shares.

Note

This lab covers storage accounts, blobs, and files. As you go through the steps, consider the security features you learned about.

Architecture diagram

Job skills

- Create and configure a storage account.

- Create and configure secure blob storage.

- Create and configure secure Azure file storage.

Note

Estimated timing: 50 minutes.

To complete this exercise, you need an Azure subscription .

Launch the exercise, and follow the instructions. When finished, be sure to return to this page so you can continue learning.

Unit 4.3.9 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-security/9-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Your company uses an Azure storage account for storing large numbers of images, audio, and video.

Answer the following questions

Choose the best response for each question.

Unit 4.3.10 - Summary and resources

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-storage-security/10-summary-resources

Summary and resources

Azure Administrators must be familiar with how to configure storage security.

In this module, you examined several options for securing Azure Storage. You discovered how to configure shared access signatures (SAS), including the uniform resource identifier (URI) and SAS parameters. You reviewed how to implement customer-managed keys and define stored access policies to configure Azure Storage encryption. You explored opportunities for improving your Azure Storage security solution.

Learn more with Copilot

Copilot can assist you in configuring Azure infrastructure solutions. Copilot can compare, recommend, explain, and research products and services where you need more information. Open a Microsoft Edge browser and choose Copilot (top right) or navigate to copilot.microsoft.com. Take a few minutes to try these prompts and extend your learning with Copilot.

- What are the different ways to secure Azure storage? Provide usage case examples.

What are the different ways to secure Azure storage? Provide usage case examples.

- How do I configure an Azure Shared Access Signature?

How do I configure an Azure Shared Access Signature?

Learn more with documentation

- Grant limited access to Azure Storage resources with shared access signatures .

Grant limited access to Azure Storage resources with shared access signatures .

- Read about Azure Storage encryption for data at rest .

Read about Azure Storage encryption for data at rest .

- Create a SAS for your Azure storage account .

Create a SAS for your Azure storage account .

- Create a service-level SAS .

Create a service-level SAS .

- Construct a user delegation SAS .

Construct a user delegation SAS .

- Use customer-managed keys for Azure Storage encryption .

Use customer-managed keys for Azure Storage encryption .

Learn more with self-paced training

- Secure your Azure storage account .

Secure your Azure storage account .

- Implement Azure Storage security .

Implement Azure Storage security .

LP 4 M4 - Configure Azure Files

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-files-file-sync/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 4.4.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-files-file-sync/1-introduction

Introduction

Azure Files offers fully managed file shares in the cloud that are accessible via industry standard protocols. Azure File Sync is a service that allows you to cache several Azure Files shares on an on-premises Windows Server or cloud virtual machine.

In this module, your company has a large repository of organizational documents. Offices are located in different geographical regions, and users need the most current versions of the documents. You're researching how to implement Azure Files shares to provide a central location for the documents.

Learning objectives

In this module, you learn how to:

- Identify storage for file shares.

- Compare file shares to blob storage.

- Configure Azure file shares, file share snapshots, and soft delete.

- Use Azure Storage Explorer to access your file share.

Skills measured

The content in the module helps you prepare for Exam AZ-104: Microsoft Azure Administrator .

Prerequisites

- Familiarity with shared file systems.

- Familiarity with navigating the Azure portal.

Unit 4.4.2 - Compare storage for file shares and blob data

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-files-file-sync/2-compare-files-to-blobs

Compare storage for file shares and blob data

Azure Files offers fully managed file shares in the cloud. You can access Azure file shares by using the Server Message Block (SMB), Network File System (NFS), and HTTP protocols. Clients can connect to Azure file shares from Windows, Linux, and macOS devices.

Things to know about Azure Files

Here are some characteristics of Azure files:

- Serverless deployment . An Azure file share is a PaaS offering of a fully managed file share that doesn't require any infrastructure. You don't need to take care of any VMs, operating systems, or updates.

Serverless deployment . An Azure file share is a PaaS offering of a fully managed file share that doesn't require any infrastructure. You don't need to take care of any VMs, operating systems, or updates.

- Almost unlimited storage . A single Azure file share can store up to 100 tebibytes (TiB) of files, and a file can be up to 4 TiB in size. The files are organized in a hierarchical folder structure in the same way as on on-premises file servers.

Almost unlimited storage . A single Azure file share can store up to 100 tebibytes (TiB) of files, and a file can be up to 4 TiB in size. The files are organized in a hierarchical folder structure in the same way as on on-premises file servers.

- Data encryption . The data on an Azure file share is encrypted at rest in an Azure datacenter and in transit on a network.

Data encryption . The data on an Azure file share is encrypted at rest in an Azure datacenter and in transit on a network.

- Access from anywhere . By default, clients can access Azure file shares from anywhere if they have internet connectivity.

Access from anywhere . By default, clients can access Azure file shares from anywhere if they have internet connectivity.

- Integration into an existing environment . You can control access to Azure file shares by using Microsoft Entra identities or AD DS identities that are synced to Microsoft Entra ID. This helps ensure that users can have the same experience accessing an Azure file share as when they access an on-premises file server.

Integration into an existing environment . You can control access to Azure file shares by using Microsoft Entra identities or AD DS identities that are synced to Microsoft Entra ID. This helps ensure that users can have the same experience accessing an Azure file share as when they access an on-premises file server.

- Previous versions and backups . You can create Azure file share snapshots that integrate with the Previous Versions feature in File Explorer. You can also use Azure Backup to back up Azure file shares.

Previous versions and backups . You can create Azure file share snapshots that integrate with the Previous Versions feature in File Explorer. You can also use Azure Backup to back up Azure file shares.

- Data redundancy . Azure file share data replicates to multiple locations in the same Azure datacenter or across many Azure datacenters. The replication setting of the Azure storage account that includes the file share controls the data redundancy.

Data redundancy . Azure file share data replicates to multiple locations in the same Azure datacenter or across many Azure datacenters. The replication setting of the Azure storage account that includes the file share controls the data redundancy.

Things to consider when using Azure Files

There are many common scenarios for using Azure Files. As you review the following suggestions, think about how Azure Files can provide solutions for your organization.

- Consider replacement and supplement options . Replace or supplement traditional on-premises file servers or NAS devices by using Azure Files.

Consider replacement and supplement options . Replace or supplement traditional on-premises file servers or NAS devices by using Azure Files.

- Consider global access . Directly access Azure file shares by using most operating systems, such as Windows, macOS, and Linux, from anywhere in the world.

Consider global access . Directly access Azure file shares by using most operating systems, such as Windows, macOS, and Linux, from anywhere in the world.

- Consider lift and shift support . Lift and shift applications to the cloud with Azure Files for apps that expect a file share to store file application or user data.

Consider lift and shift support . Lift and shift applications to the cloud with Azure Files for apps that expect a file share to store file application or user data.

- Consider using Azure File Sync . Replicate Azure file shares to Windows Servers by using Azure File Sync. You can replicate on-premises or in the cloud for performance and distributed caching of the data where it's being used. We take a closer look at Azure File Sync in a later unit.

Consider using Azure File Sync . Replicate Azure file shares to Windows Servers by using Azure File Sync. You can replicate on-premises or in the cloud for performance and distributed caching of the data where it's being used. We take a closer look at Azure File Sync in a later unit.

- Consider shared applications . Store shared application settings such as configuration files in Azure Files.

Consider shared applications . Store shared application settings such as configuration files in Azure Files.

- Consider diagnostic data . Use Azure Files to store diagnostic data such as logs, metrics, and crash dumps in a shared location.

Consider diagnostic data . Use Azure Files to store diagnostic data such as logs, metrics, and crash dumps in a shared location.

- Consider tools and utilities . Azure Files is a good option for storing tools and utilities that are needed for developing or administering Azure VMs or cloud services.

Consider tools and utilities . Azure Files is a good option for storing tools and utilities that are needed for developing or administering Azure VMs or cloud services.

Compare Azure Files to Azure Blob Storage

It's important to understand when to use Azure Files to store data in file shares rather than using Azure Blob Storage to store data as blobs. The following table compares different features of these services and common implementation scenarios.

Azure Files (file shares)

Azure Blob Storage (blobs)

Azure Files provides the SMB and NFS protocols, client libraries, and a REST interface that allows access from anywhere to stored files.

Azure Blob Storage provides client libraries and a REST interface that allows unstructured data to be stored and accessed at a massive scale in block blobs.

- Files in an Azure Files share are true directory objects. - Data in Azure Files is accessed through file shares across multiple virtual machines.

- Blobs in Azure Blob Storage are a flat namespace. - Blob data in Azure Blob Storage is accessed through a container.

Azure Files is ideal to lift and shift an application to the cloud that already uses the native file system APIs. Share data between the app and other applications running in Azure. Azure Files is a good option when you want to store development and debugging tools that need to be accessed from many virtual machines.

Azure Blob Storage is ideal for applications that need to support streaming and random-access scenarios. Azure Blob Storage is a good option when you want to be able to access application data from anywhere.

Unit 4.4.3 - Manage Azure file shares

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-files-file-sync/3-manage-file-shares

Manage Azure file shares

Azure Files offers two industry-standard file system protocols for mounting Azure file shares: the Server Message Block (SMB) protocol and the Network File System (NFS) protocol. Azure file shares don't support both the SMB and NFS protocols on the same file share, although you can create SMB and NFS Azure file shares within the same storage account.

Types of Azure file shares

Azure Files supports two storage tiers: premium and standard. Standard file shares are created in general purpose (GPv2) storage accounts, while premium file shares are created in FileStorage storage accounts. The two storage tiers have the attributes described in the following table.

Storage tier

Performance

Storage account type

Redundancy options

Billing model

Use cases

Premium

SSD-backed, consistent low latency

FileStorage

LRS, ZRS

Provisioned (pay for capacity reserved)

High-performance workloads requiring low latency

Transaction Optimized

HDD-backed, standard performance

General-purpose v2 (GPv2)

LRS, GRS, RA-GRS, ZRS, GZRS, RA-GZRS

Pay-as-you-go

High-transaction workloads, frequently accessed data

Hot

HDD-backed, standard performance

General-purpose v2 (GPv2)

LRS, GRS, RA-GRS, ZRS, GZRS, RA-GZRS

Pay-as-you-go

General-purpose team shares and collaborative workloads

Cool

HDD-backed, standard performance

General-purpose v2 (GPv2)

LRS, GRS, RA-GRS, ZRS, GZRS, RA-GZRS

Pay-as-you-go

Cost-efficient online archive and backup scenarios

Note

Transaction Optimized, Hot, and Cool are all Standard (HDD-based) tiers with different pricing structures optimized for specific access patterns. Premium tier uses SSD storage with provisioned billing (you pay for the capacity you reserve), while Standard tiers use pay-as-you-go billing.

Types of authentication

There are three main authentications methods that Azure Files supports.

Authentication method

Description

Identity-based authentication over SMB

SMB identity-based authentication supports three Active Directory sources: On-premises AD DS, Microsoft Entra Domain Services, and Microsoft Entra Kerberos. Once your Active Directory source is selected, assign Azure RBAC roles to users who need access to the file share.

Access key

An access key is an older and less flexible option. An Azure storage account has two access keys that can be used when making a request to the storage account, including to Azure Files. Access keys are static and provide full control access to Azure Files. Access keys should be secured and not shared with users, because they bypass all access control restrictions. A best practice is to avoid sharing storage account keys and use identity-based authentication whenever possible.

A Shared Access Signature (SAS) token

SAS is a dynamically generated Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) that's based on the storage access key. SAS provides restricted access rights to an Azure storage account. Restrictions include allowed permissions, start and expiry time, allowed IP addresses from where requests can be sent, and allowed protocols. With Azure Files, a SAS token is only used to provide REST API access from code.

Creating SMB Azure file shares (classic)

Classic Azure file shares live inside a storage account, so they follow the same limits as that account. You can choose between two storage tiers: SSD (premium) and HDD (standard).

SSD file shares are great when you need fast, consistent performance with low latency—usually in the single digit milliseconds. HDD shares are more budget friendly and work well for general purpose storage.

If you need SMB access, make sure to create your file share inside a storage account. SMB file shares let you pick from several access tiers, including transaction optimized, hot, and cool.

Note

When connecting over SMB, don’t forget that traffic uses port 445. Many ISPs block port 445 outbound, which is the most common connectivity issue when mounting Azure file shares from on-premises environments.

Important

File shares (preview) are now generally available that don't require an Azure storage account. This option provides simplified management for scenarios where you only need file shares without other storage services.

Unit 4.4.4 - Create file share snapshots

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-files-file-sync/4-create-file-share-snapshots

Create file share snapshots

Azure Files provides the capability to take share snapshots of file shares . Share snapshots provide point-in-time copies of your Azure file shares that protect against accidental deletion and enable recovery from application errors.

Things to know about file share snapshots

- Snapshots are incremental, read-only point-in-time copies at the share level.

- To reduce time and cost only captures from the last snapshot.

- Same experience for SMB and NFS shares in all Azure public regions.

- Snapshot adds a unique timestamp to the share URI.

- Uses the shares redundancy settings.

- Up to 200 snapshots per file share for low-RPO recovery points.

- Snapshots persist until deleted. Deleting the share deletes all snapshots.

- Azure Backup can lease snapshots to help prevent accidental deletion.

- Restore a file, folder, or full share; full restore requires only the latest snapshot.

Things to consider when using file share snapshots

File share snapshots can help you protect and recover your data. As you review the benefits, consider where snapshots fit into your Azure Files setup.

Benefit

Description

Protect against application error and data corruption

File-share workloads constantly read and write data. If a misconfiguration, bad deployment, or software bug overwrites or corrupts data, a snapshot lets you roll the share back to a known-good point in time. Take a snapshot before releasing new code so you have a clean restore point if something goes wrong.

Protect against accidental deletions or unintended changes

If a file is changed, snapshots give you a quick way to restore an earlier version. Use snapshots to roll back to the last good copy when something unexpected happens.

Support backup and recovery

Create snapshots on a schedule to build a backup history for your file share. Keeping prior versions makes it easier to meet audit needs and recover data after mistakes or a broader outage.

For automated snapshot creation or integration with existing scripts, PowerShell and Azure CLI provide programmatic access to snapshot operations. Both tools support adding metadata to snapshots and can be scheduled through Azure Automation, GitHub Actions, or any continuous integration system.

Unit 4.4.5 - Implement soft delete for Azure Files

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-files-file-sync/5-implement-file-sync

Implement soft delete for Azure Files

Azure Files offers soft delete for file shares . Soft delete lets you recover deleted files and file shares.

Things to know about soft delete for Azure Files

Let's take a look at the characteristics of soft delete for Azure Files.

- Soft delete for file shares is enabled at the storage account level.

Soft delete for file shares is enabled at the storage account level.

- Soft delete transitions content to a soft deleted state instead of being permanently erased.

Soft delete transitions content to a soft deleted state instead of being permanently erased.

- Soft delete lets you configure the retention period. The retention period is the amount of time that soft deleted file shares are stored and available for recovery.

Soft delete lets you configure the retention period. The retention period is the amount of time that soft deleted file shares are stored and available for recovery.

- Soft delete provides a retention period between 1 and 365 days.

Soft delete provides a retention period between 1 and 365 days.

- Soft delete can be enabled on either new or existing file shares.

Soft delete can be enabled on either new or existing file shares.

Things to consider when using soft delete for Azure Files

There are many advantages to using soft delete for Azure Files. Consider the following scenarios, and think about how you can use soft delete.

- Recover from accidental data loss . You can recover deleted or corrupted data with soft delete.

Recover from accidental data loss . You can recover deleted or corrupted data with soft delete.

- Upgrade scenarios . Use soft delete to restore to a known good state after a failed upgrade attempt.

Upgrade scenarios . Use soft delete to restore to a known good state after a failed upgrade attempt.

- Ransomware protection . Use soft delete to recover data without paying ransom to cybercriminals.

Ransomware protection . Use soft delete to recover data without paying ransom to cybercriminals.

- Long-term retention . Use soft delete to comply with data retention requirements.

Long-term retention . Use soft delete to comply with data retention requirements.

- Business continuity . Use soft delete to prepare your infrastructure to be highly available for critical workloads.

Business continuity . Use soft delete to prepare your infrastructure to be highly available for critical workloads.

Unit 4.4.6 - Use Azure Storage Explorer

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-files-file-sync/6-identify-components

Use Azure Storage Explorer

Azure Storage Explorer is a standalone application that makes it easy to work with Azure Storage data on Windows, macOS, and Linux. With Azure Storage Explorer, you can access multiple accounts and subscriptions, and manage all your Storage content.

Things to know about Azure Storage Explorer

Azure Storage Explorer has the following characteristics.

- Azure Storage Explorer requires both management (Azure Resource Manager) and data layer permissions to allow full access to your resources. You need Microsoft Entra ID permissions to access your storage account, the containers in your account, and the data in the containers.

Azure Storage Explorer requires both management (Azure Resource Manager) and data layer permissions to allow full access to your resources. You need Microsoft Entra ID permissions to access your storage account, the containers in your account, and the data in the containers.

- Azure Storage Explorer lets you connect to different storage accounts. Connect to storage accounts associated with your Azure subscriptions. Connect to storage accounts and services that are shared from other Azure subscriptions. Connect to and manage local storage by using the Azure Storage Emulator.

Azure Storage Explorer lets you connect to different storage accounts.

- Connect to storage accounts associated with your Azure subscriptions.

- Connect to storage accounts and services that are shared from other Azure subscriptions.

- Connect to and manage local storage by using the Azure Storage Emulator.

Things to consider when using Azure Storage Explorer

Azure Storage Explorer supports many scenarios for working with storage accounts in Azure. As you review these options, think about which scenarios apply to your Azure Storage implementation.

Scenario

Description

Connect to an Azure subscription

Manage storage resources that belong to your Azure subscription.

Work with local development storage

Manage local storage by using the Azure Storage Emulator.

Attach to external storage

Manage storage resources that belong to another Azure subscription or that are under national Azure clouds by using the storage account name, key, and endpoints. This scenario is described in more detail in the next section.

Attach a storage account with a SAS

Manage storage resources that belong to another Azure subscription by using a shared access signature (SAS).

Attach a service with a SAS

Manage a specific Azure Storage service (blob container, queue, or table) that belongs to another Azure subscription by using a SAS.

Attach to external storage account

Azure Storage Explorer lets you attach to external storage accounts so storage accounts can be easily shared.

To create the connection, you need the external storage Account name and Account key . In the Azure portal, the account key is called key1 .

To use a storage account name and key from a national Azure cloud, use the Storage endpoints domain drop-down menu to select Other , and then enter the custom storage account endpoint domain.

Access keys

Access keys provide access to the entire storage account. You're provided two access keys so you can maintain connections by using one key while regenerating the other.

Important

Store your access keys securely. We recommend regenerating your access keys regularly.

When you regenerate your access keys, you must update any Azure resources and applications that access this storage account to use the new keys. This action doesn't interrupt access to disks from your virtual machines.

Unit 4.4.7 - Consider Azure File Sync

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-files-file-sync/7-deploy-azure-file-sync

Consider Azure File Sync

Azure File Sync enables you to cache several Azure Files shares on an on-premises Windows Server or cloud virtual machine. You can use Azure File Sync to centralize your organization's file shares in Azure Files, while keeping the flexibility, performance, and compatibility of an on-premises file server.

Azure File Sync consists of five main components that work together to synchronize files between on-premises Windows Servers and Azure file shares.

- The Storage Sync Service is the primary Azure resource responsible for managing file synchronization. It can support up to 100 sync groups, operates within a single Azure region, and allows for up to 99 registered Windows Servers.

The Storage Sync Service is the primary Azure resource responsible for managing file synchronization. It can support up to 100 sync groups, operates within a single Azure region, and allows for up to 99 registered Windows Servers.

- The sync group establishes the synchronization setup, containing one cloud endpoint (Azure file share) and up to 50 server endpoints. Server endpoints are specific NTFS paths on registered Windows Servers, but cannot be on the system volume, and cloud tiering is not supported there.

The sync group establishes the synchronization setup, containing one cloud endpoint (Azure file share) and up to 50 server endpoints. Server endpoints are specific NTFS paths on registered Windows Servers, but cannot be on the system volume, and cloud tiering is not supported there.

- The cloud endpoint is an Azure file share that participates in the sync group. Only one cloud endpoint is allowed per sync group.

The cloud endpoint is an Azure file share that participates in the sync group. Only one cloud endpoint is allowed per sync group.

- The server endpoint is a path on a registered Windows Server that syncs with the cloud endpoint. The server endpoint must be an NTFS-formatted volume, and can’t be a system volume.

The server endpoint is a path on a registered Windows Server that syncs with the cloud endpoint. The server endpoint must be an NTFS-formatted volume, and can’t be a system volume.

- The Azure File Sync Agent is installed on each Windows Server. The agent is a background Windows service for sync operations and management tasks.

The Azure File Sync Agent is installed on each Windows Server. The agent is a background Windows service for sync operations and management tasks.

Things to know about Azure File Sync

Let's take a look at the characteristics of Azure File Sync.

- Azure File Sync transforms Windows Server into a quick cache of your Azure Files shares.

Azure File Sync transforms Windows Server into a quick cache of your Azure Files shares.

- You can use any protocol that's available on Windows Server to access your data locally with Azure File Sync, including SMB, NFS, and FTPS.

You can use any protocol that's available on Windows Server to access your data locally with Azure File Sync, including SMB, NFS, and FTPS.

- Azure File Sync supports as many caches as you need around the world.

Azure File Sync supports as many caches as you need around the world.

- There is a maximum of 100 sync groups per Storage Sync Service, and 50 server endpoints per sync group.

There is a maximum of 100 sync groups per Storage Sync Service, and 50 server endpoints per sync group.

Things to consider when using Azure File Sync

There are many advantages to using Azure File Sync. Consider the following scenarios, and think about how you can use Azure File Sync with your Azure Files shares.

- Consider application lift and shift . Use Azure File Sync to move applications that require access between Azure and on-premises systems. Provide write access to the same data across Windows Servers and Azure Files.

Consider application lift and shift . Use Azure File Sync to move applications that require access between Azure and on-premises systems. Provide write access to the same data across Windows Servers and Azure Files.

- Consider support for branch offices . Support your branch offices that need to back up files by using Azure File Sync. Use the service to set up a new server that connects to Azure storage.

Consider support for branch offices . Support your branch offices that need to back up files by using Azure File Sync. Use the service to set up a new server that connects to Azure storage.

- Consider backup and disaster recovery . After you implement Azure File Sync, Azure Backup backs up your on-premises data. Restore file metadata immediately and recall data as needed for rapid disaster recovery.

Consider backup and disaster recovery . After you implement Azure File Sync, Azure Backup backs up your on-premises data. Restore file metadata immediately and recall data as needed for rapid disaster recovery.

- Consider file archiving with cloud tiering . Azure File Sync stores only recently accessed data on local servers. Implement cloud tiering so older data moves to Azure Files.

Consider file archiving with cloud tiering . Azure File Sync stores only recently accessed data on local servers. Implement cloud tiering so older data moves to Azure Files.

Unit 4.4.8 - Knowledge check

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-files-file-sync/8-knowledge-check

Knowledge check

Your company maintains a large document repository. You're implementing Azure Files shares to provide a central location for the documents. Users at offices in different geographical regions need access to the latest versions of the documents. You're configuring Azure File Sync to keep the information up to date across multiple offices.

One scenario you're working to resolve involves the manufacturing division. They're running dedicated software in their warehouse to keep track of product stock. The software needs to run on machines in the warehouse, but the management team wants to access the stock data from the main office. Limited bandwidth in the warehouse is causing issues when accessing cloud based solutions. You proposed using cloud tiering, soft delete, and snapshots.

Answer the following questions

Choose the best response for each question.

Unit 4.4.9 - Summary and resources

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-files-file-sync/9-summary-resources

Summary and resources

Azure Administrators are familiar with Azure Files and the Azure File Sync agent. They know how to implement fully managed file shares in the cloud by using industry standard protocols. They understand how to use Azure File Sync to cache Azure Files shares on an on-premises Windows Server or cloud virtual machine.

In this module, you learned when to use Azure Files and how the service compares to Azure Blob Storage. You also reviewed Azure Files features such as snapshots and soft delete. You learned how Azure File Sync can be used with on-premises data stores. You also were introduced to Azure Storage Explorer.

The main takeaways for this module are:

- Azure Files provides the SMB and NFS protocols, client libraries, and a REST interface that allows access from anywhere to stored files.

Azure Files provides the SMB and NFS protocols, client libraries, and a REST interface that allows access from anywhere to stored files.

- Azure Files is ideal to lift and shift an application to the cloud that already uses the native file system APIs. Share data between the app and other applications running in Azure.

Azure Files is ideal to lift and shift an application to the cloud that already uses the native file system APIs. Share data between the app and other applications running in Azure.

- Azure Files offers two industry-standard file system protocols for mounting Azure file shares: the Server Message Block (SMB) protocol and the Network File System (NFS) protocol.

Azure Files offers two industry-standard file system protocols for mounting Azure file shares: the Server Message Block (SMB) protocol and the Network File System (NFS) protocol.

- Azure Files offers two types of file shares: standard and premium. The premium tier stores data on modern solid-state drives (SSDs), while the standard tier uses hard disk drives (HDDs).

Azure Files offers two types of file shares: standard and premium. The premium tier stores data on modern solid-state drives (SSDs), while the standard tier uses hard disk drives (HDDs).

- File share snapshots capture a point-in-time, read-only copy of your data.

File share snapshots capture a point-in-time, read-only copy of your data.

- Soft delete allows you to recover your deleted file share.

Soft delete allows you to recover your deleted file share.

- Azure Storage Explorer is a standalone application that makes it easy to work with stored data on Windows, macOS, and Linux.

Azure Storage Explorer is a standalone application that makes it easy to work with stored data on Windows, macOS, and Linux.

- Azure File Sync enables you to cache file shares on an on-premises Windows Server or cloud virtual machine.

Azure File Sync enables you to cache file shares on an on-premises Windows Server or cloud virtual machine.

Learn more with Copilot

Copilot can assist you in configuring Azure infrastructure solutions. Copilot can compare, recommend, explain, and research products and services where you need more information. Open a Microsoft Edge browser and choose Copilot (top right) or navigate to copilot.microsoft.com. Take a few minutes to try these prompts and extend your learning with Copilot.

- What are Azure Files and how are they different from Azure blob storage?

What are Azure Files and how are they different from Azure blob storage?

- What are some common configuration and administration tasks for Azure Files?

What are some common configuration and administration tasks for Azure Files?

Learn more with documentation

- Azure Files documentation . This page is your starting point for all things related to Azure Files.

Azure Files documentation . This page is your starting point for all things related to Azure Files.

- Azure File Sync documentation . This page is your starting point for all things related to Azure File Sync.

Azure File Sync documentation . This page is your starting point for all things related to Azure File Sync.

Learn more with self-paced training

- Implement a hybrid file server infrastructure . In this module, you learn to deploy Azure File Sync and use Storage Migration Services to migrate file servers to Azure.

Implement a hybrid file server infrastructure . In this module, you learn to deploy Azure File Sync and use Storage Migration Services to migrate file servers to Azure.

- Guided Project - Azure Files and Azure Blobs . In this module, you practice storing business data securely by using Azure Blob Storage and Azure Files. The lab combines both learning and practical experience.

Guided Project - Azure Files and Azure Blobs . In this module, you practice storing business data securely by using Azure Blob Storage and Azure Files. The lab combines both learning and practical experience.

LP 5 M1 - Introduction to Azure virtual machines

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-virtual-machines/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 5.1.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-virtual-machines/1-introduction

Introduction

Suppose you work for a company doing medical research and you're responsible for managing the on-premises servers. The servers you administer run all the company infrastructure, from web servers to databases. However, the hardware is aging and starting to struggle to keep up with some of the new data analysis applications being deployed to it.

You could upgrade all the hardware, but that's not appealing for several reasons:

- The servers are physically scattered all around the world with minimal staff in each location. We'd like to centralize the upgrade to our home office.

The servers are physically scattered all around the world with minimal staff in each location. We'd like to centralize the upgrade to our home office.

- The company runs custom data analysis software on several versions and flavors of Windows and Linux, sometimes set up with odd configurations that aren't entirely understood. We need a way to test our deployments completely and try different configurations to make sure everything is working before we transition the work.

The company runs custom data analysis software on several versions and flavors of Windows and Linux, sometimes set up with odd configurations that aren't entirely understood. We need a way to test our deployments completely and try different configurations to make sure everything is working before we transition the work.

- Business is booming, and the company is growing fast. It's likely that the load on the internal servers, particularly the databases, will continue to grow. This growth requires us to either buy for the future or come up with a scaling plan to handle the growth.

Business is booming, and the company is growing fast. It's likely that the load on the internal servers, particularly the databases, will continue to grow. This growth requires us to either buy for the future or come up with a scaling plan to handle the growth.

For these reasons, you decide that it's time to explore the cloud to see if it can help solve the load and scale problem. Since you have a bunch of mixed servers and custom software, it makes sense to look at trying to move servers one at a time into Azure using Azure Virtual Machines (VMs).

Azure VMs are one of several types of on-demand, scalable computing resources that Azure offers. With VMs, you have total control over the configuration and can install anything you need to perform the work. You don't need to purchase physical hardware when you need to scale or extend your datacenter. Finally, Azure provides other services to monitor, secure, and manage updates and patches to the OS.

We're going to look at the decisions made before creating a VM, the options to create and manage the VM, and the extensions and services you use to manage your VM.

Learning objectives

In this module, you learn how to:

- Compile a checklist for creating a virtual machine

- Describe the options to create and manage virtual machines

- Describe the other services available to administer virtual machines

Unit 5.1.2 - Compile a checklist for creating an Azure Virtual Machine

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-virtual-machines/2-compile-a-checklist-for-creating-a-vm

Compile a checklist for creating an Azure Virtual Machine

Performing a migration of on-premises servers to Azure requires planning and care. You can move them all at once, or more likely, in small batches or even individually. Before you create a single VM, you should sit down and sketch out your current infrastructure model and see how it might map to the cloud.

What is an Azure resource?

An Azure resource is a manageable item in Azure. Just like a physical computer in your datacenter, VMs have several elements that are needed to do their job:

- The VM itself

- Disks for storage

- Virtual network

- Network interface to communicate on the network

- Network Security Group (NSG) to secure the network traffic

- An IP address (public, private, or both)

Azure creates all of these resources if necessary, or you can supply existing ones as part of the deployment process. Each resource needs a name that's used to identify it. If Azure creates the resource, it uses the VM name to generate a resource name - another reason to be consistent with your VM names!

Required resources for IaaS Virtual Machines

Let's walk through a checklist of things to think about.

- The network

- VM name

- Location

- The VM size

- Disks

- Operating system

The network

The first thing you should think about isn't the virtual machine at all - it's the network. Take a look at one of your on-premises servers:

- What does the server communicate with?

- Which ports are open?

Virtual networks (VNets) are used in Azure to provide private connectivity between Azure Virtual Machines and other Azure services. VMs and services that are part of the same virtual network can access one another. By default, services outside the virtual network can't connect to services within the virtual network. You can, however, configure the network to allow access to the external service, including your on-premises servers.

This latter point is why you should spend some time thinking about your network configuration. Network addresses and subnets aren't trivial to change once you have them set up. If you plan to connect your private company network to the Azure services, you want to make sure you consider the topology before putting any VMs into place.

When you set up a virtual network, you specify the available address spaces, subnets, and security. If the VNet is connected to other VNets, you must select address ranges that aren't overlapping. This is the range of private addresses that the VMs and services in your network can use. You can use unroutable IP addresses such as 10.0.0.0/8, 172.16.0.0/12, or 192.168.0.0/16, or define your own range. Azure treats any address range as part of the private VNet IP address space if it's only reachable within the VNet, within interconnected VNets, and from your on-premises location. If someone else is responsible for the internal networks, you should work with that person before selecting your address space to make sure there's no overlap. Let them know what space you want to use, so they don’t try to use the same range of IP addresses.

Segregate your network

After deciding the virtual network address space(s), you can create one or more subnets for your virtual network. You create these subnets to break up your network into more manageable sections. For example, you might assign 10.1.0.0 to VMs, 10.2.0.0 to back-end services, and 10.3.0.0 to SQL Server VMs.

Note

Azure reserves the first four addresses and the last address in each subnet for its use.

Secure the network

By default, there's no security boundary between subnets, so services in each of these subnets can talk to one another. However, you can set up Network Security Groups (NSGs), which allow you to control the traffic flow to and from subnets and to and from VMs. NSGs act as software firewalls, applying custom rules to each inbound or outbound request at the network interface and subnet level. This way, you can fully control every network request coming in or out of the VM.

Plan each VM deployment

Once you have mapped out your communication and network requirements, you can start thinking about the VMs you want to create. A good plan is to select a server and take an inventory:

- Which OS is used?

- How much disk space is in use?

- What kind of data does this use? Are there restrictions (legal or otherwise) around how it's stored or where it's physically located?

- What sort of CPU, memory, and disk I/O load does the server have? Is there burst traffic to account for?

We can then start to answer some of the questions Azure has for a new virtual machine.

VM name

The VM name is used as the computer name, which is configured as part of the operating system. You can specify a name of up to 64 characters on a Linux VM and 15 characters on a Windows VM.

This name also defines a manageable Azure resource , and it's not trivial to change later. That means you should choose names that are meaningful and consistent, so you can easily identify what the VM does. A good convention is to include the following information in the name:

Element

Example

Notes

Environment

dev, prod, QA

Identifies the environment for the resource

Location

eus for East US, jw for Japan West

eus

jw

Identifies the region into which the resource is deployed

Instance

01, 02

For resources that have more than one named instance (web servers, etc.)

Product or Service

service

Identifies the product, application, or service that the resource supports

Role

sql, web, messaging

Identifies the role of the associated resource

For example, deveus-webvm01 might represent the first development web server hosted in the East US location.

deveus-webvm01

Decide the location for the VM

Azure has datacenters all over the world filled with servers and disks. These datacenters are grouped into geographic regions ('West US', 'North Europe', 'Southeast Asia', etc.) to provide redundancy and availability.

When you create and deploy a virtual machine, you must select a region where you want to allocate the resources. You can place your VMs as close as possible to your users to improve performance and to meet any legal, compliance, or tax requirements.

Two other things to think about regarding the location choice. First, the location can limit your available options. Each region has different hardware available and some configurations aren't available in all regions. Second, there are price differences between locations. If your workload isn't bound to a specific location, it can be very cost effective to check your required configuration in multiple regions to find the lowest price.

Determine the size of the VM

Once you have the name and location set, you need to decide on the size of your VM . Rather than specify processing power, memory, and storage capacity independently, Azure provides different VM sizes that offer variations of these elements in different sizes. Azure provides a wide range of VM size options allowing you to select the appropriate mix of compute, memory, and storage for what you want to do.

The best way to determine the appropriate VM size is to consider the type of workload your VM needs to run. Based on the workload, you're able to choose from a subset of available VM sizes. Workload options are classified as follows on Azure:

Option

Description

General purpose

General-purpose VMs are designed to have a balanced CPU-to-memory ratio. Ideal for testing and development, small to medium databases, and low to medium traffic web servers.

Compute optimized

Compute optimized VMs are designed to have a high CPU-to-memory ratio. Suitable for medium traffic web servers, network appliances, batch processes, and application servers.

Memory optimized

Memory optimized VMs are designed to have a high memory-to-CPU ratio. Great for relational database servers, medium to large caches, and in-memory analytics.

Storage optimized

Storage optimized VMs are designed to have high disk throughput and IO. Ideal for VMs running databases.

GPU

GPU VMs are specialized virtual machines targeted for heavy graphics rendering and video editing. These VMs are ideal options for model training and inferencing with deep learning.

High performance compute

High performance compute is the fastest and most powerful CPU virtual machines with optional high-throughput network interfaces.

You're able to filter on the workload type when you configure the VM size in the Azure. The size you choose directly affects the cost of your service. The more CPU, memory, and GPU you need, the higher the price point.

What if my size needs change?

Azure allows you to change the VM size when the existing size no longer meets your needs. You can upgrade or downgrade the VM, as long as your current hardware configuration is allowed in the new size. The ability to change VM size provides a fully agile and scalable approach to VM management.

The VM size can be changed while the VM is running, as long as the new size is available in the current hardware cluster the VM is running on. The Azure portal makes the size options obvious by only showing you available size choices. The command line tools report an error if you attempt to resize a VM to an unavailable size. Changing a running VM size automatically reboots the machine to complete the request.

If you stop and deallocate the VM, you can then select any size available in your region since deallocation removes your VM from the cluster it was running on.

Warning

Be careful about resizing production VMs - they will be rebooted automatically which can cause a temporary outage and change some configuration settings such as the IP address.

Parts of a VM and how they're billed

When you create a virtual machine, you're also creating resources that support the virtual machine. These resources come with their own costs that should be considered.

The default resources supporting a virtual machine and how they're billed are detailed in the following table:

Resource

Description

Cost

Virtual network

For giving your virtual machine the ability to communicate with other resources

Virtual Network pricing

A virtual Network Interface Card (NIC)

For connecting to the virtual network

There is no separate cost for NICs. However, there is a limit to how many NICs you can use based on your VM's size . Size your VM accordingly and reference Virtual Machine pricing .

A private IP address and sometimes a public IP address.

For communication and data exchange on your network and with external networks

IP Addresses pricing

Network security group (NSG)

For managing the network traffic too and from your VM. For example, you might need to open port 22 for SSH access, but you might want to block traffic to port 80. Blocking and allowing port access is done through the NSG.

There are no additional charges for network security groups in Azure.

OS Disk and possibly separate disks for data.

It's a best practice to keep your data on a separate disk from your operating system, in case you ever have a VM fail, you can simply detach the data disk, and attach it to a new VM.

All new virtual machines have an operating system disk and a local disk. Azure doesn't charge for local disk storage. The operating system disk, which is usually 127GiB but is smaller for some images, is charged at the regular rate for disks . You can see the cost for attach Premium (SSD based) and Standard (HDD) based disks to your virtual machines on the Managed Disks pricing page .

In some cases, a license for the OS

For providing your virtual machine runs to run the OS

The cost varies based on the number of cores on your VM, so size your VM accordingly . The cost can be reduced through the Azure Hybrid Benefit .

Understanding the pricing model

There are two separate costs the subscription is charged for every VM: compute and storage. By separating these costs, you scale them independently and only pay for what you need.

Compute costs - Compute expenses are priced on a per-hour basis but billed on a per-minute basis. For example, you're only charged for 55 minutes of usage if the VM is deployed for 55 minutes. You're not charged for compute capacity if you stop and deallocate the VM since deallocation releases the hardware. The hourly price varies based on the VM size and OS you select. Linux-based instances are cheaper because there's no operating system license charge. For Windows, the cost for a VM includes the charge for the operating system.

Tip

You might be able to save money by reusing existing licenses with the Azure Hybrid benefit for Linux or Windows .

You're able to choose from two payment options for compute costs.

Option

Description

Pay as you go

With the pay-as-you-go option, you pay for compute capacity by the second, with no long-term commitment or upfront payments. You're able to increase or decrease compute capacity on demand and start or stop at any time. Select this option if you run applications with short-term or unpredictable workloads that can't be interrupted. For example, if you're doing a quick test, or developing an app in a VM, pay-as-you-go is the appropriate option.

Reserved Virtual Machine Instances

The Reserved Virtual Machine Instances (RI) option is an advance purchase of a virtual machine for one or three years in a specified region. The commitment is made up front, and in return, you get up to 72% price savings compared to pay-as-you-go pricing. RIs are flexible and can easily be exchanged or returned for an early termination fee. Select this option if the VM has to run continuously, or you need budget predictability, and you can commit to using the VM for at least a year.

Storage costs - You're charged separately for the storage the VM uses. The status of the VM has no relation to the storage charges that are incurred. If the VM is stopped/deallocated and you aren’t billed for the running VM, you're still charged for the storage used by the disks.

Storage for the VM

All Azure virtual machines have at least two virtual hard disks (VHDs). The first disk stores the operating system, and the second is used as temporary storage. You should add more data disks to store application data. Separating out the data to different disks allows you to manage the disks independently. The VM size determines the maximum number of data disks you can attach to your VM, typically two per vCPU.

There are five disk types, each intended to address a specific customer scenario:

- Ultra disks

- Premium SSD v2 (preview)

- Premium SSDs (solid-state drives)

- Standard SSDs

- Standard HDDs (hard disk drives)

The following table provides a comparison of the five disk types to help you decide which to use.

Ultra disk

Premium SSD v2

Premium SSD

Standard SSD

Standard HDD

Disk type

SSD

HDD

Scenario

IO-intensive workloads such as SAP HANA , top tier databases (for example, SQL, Oracle), and other transaction-heavy workloads.

Production and performance-sensitive workloads that consistently require low latency and high IOPS and throughput

Production and performance sensitive workloads

Web servers, lightly used enterprise applications and dev/test

Backup, noncritical, infrequent access

Max disk size

65,536 gibibytes (GiB)

65,536 GiB

32,767 GiB

Max throughput

4,000 MB/s

1,200 MB/s

900 MB/s

750 MB/s

500 MB/s

Max IOPS

160,000

80,000

20,000

6,000

2,000

Usable as OS Disk?

No

Yes

Select an operating system

Azure provides various OS images that you can install into the VM, including many Linux distributions. The choice of OS might influence your hourly compute pricing as Azure bundles the cost of the OS license into the price.

If you're looking for more than just base OS images, you can search the Azure Marketplace for more sophisticated images that include the OS and popular software tools for specific scenarios. For example, if you needed a new WordPress site, the standard technology stack would consist of a Linux server, Apache web server, a MySQL database, and PHP. Instead of setting up and configuring each component, you can use a Marketplace image and install the entire stack all at once.

Finally, if you can't find a suitable OS image, you can create your own image with what you need, and use them to create VMs. You can create individual images for use in development and test. Or, you can create an Azure Compute Gallery to manage multiple images and replicate them to the regions where they're needed.

Unit 5.1.3 - Exercise - Create a VM using the Azure portal

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-virtual-machines/3-create-a-vm

Exercise - Create a VM using the Azure portal

You've planned out the network infrastructure and identified a few VMs to migrate to the cloud. You have several choices for creating your VMs. The choice you make depends on the environment you're comfortable with. Azure supports a web-based portal for creating and administering resources. You can also choose to use command-line tools that run on Linux, macOS, and Windows.

Note

This exercise is optional. If you want to complete this exercise, you'll need to create an Azure subscription before you begin. If you don't have an Azure account or you don't want to create one at this time, you can read through the instructions so you understand the information that's being presented.

Note

You need to use a resource group to complete the steps in this exercise. You can use a resource group that you already created, or you can create a new resource group specifically for this exercise. If you choose to create a new resource group, that will make it easier to clean up any resources that you create as you complete the exercise. If you don't have an existing resource group or you want to create a new one specifically for this exercise, you can follow the steps in Use the Azure portal and Azure Resource Manager to manage resource groups to create a resource group by using the Azure portal, or you can follow the steps in Manage Azure resource groups by using Azure CLI to create a resource group by using the the Azure CLI.

Note

Throughout this exercise, replace myResourceGroupName in the examples with the name of an existing resource group, or the name of the resource group that you created for this exercise.

Options to create and manage VMs

Let's explore the Azure portal first - it's the easiest way to start with Azure.

Azure portal

The Azure portal provides an easy-to-use browser-based user interface that enables you to create and manage all your Azure resources. For example, you can set up a new database, increase the compute power of your virtual machines, and monitor your monthly costs. It's also a great learning tool, because you can survey all available resources and use guided wizards to create the ones you need.

Create an Azure VM with the Azure portal

Let's assume you want to create a VM running a web server on Ubuntu. Setting up a site isn't difficult, but there are a couple of things to keep in mind. You need to install and configure an operating system, configure a website, install a database, and worry about things like firewalls. We're going to cover creating VMs in the next few modules, but let's create one here to see how easy it is. We don't go through all the options - check out one of the Create a VM modules to get complete details on each option.

- Sign in to the Azure portal .

Sign in to the Azure portal .

- On the Azure home page, under Azure services , select Create a resource . The Create a resource pane appears, displaying popular products for Azure services.

On the Azure home page, under Azure services , select Create a resource . The Create a resource pane appears, displaying popular products for Azure services.

- We want to create a VM, so select Virtual machine .

We want to create a VM, so select Virtual machine .

- The Create virtual machine pane appears.

The Create virtual machine pane appears.

Configure the VM

You need to configure the basic parameters of your virtual machine. If some of the options at this point are unfamiliar to you, that's OK. We're going to describe all of these options in a future module. You're welcome to copy the values used here.

- On the Basics tab, enter the following values for each setting. Setting Value Project details Subscription Select your subscription Resource group Select myResourceGroupName from the drop-down Instance details Virtual machine name Enter test-ubuntu-cus-vm Region From the dropdown list, select a geographical location close to you. Availability options No infrastructure redundancy required Security type Standard Image Ubuntu Server 24.04 LTS - Gen2 VM architecture x64 Run with Azure Spot discount Unchecked Size Standard D2s V3 Administrator account Authentication type SSH public key Username Enter a username SSH public key source Generate a new key pair Key pair name test-ubuntu-cus-vm_key Inbound port rules Public inbound ports Allow selected ports Select inbound ports SSH (22)

On the Basics tab, enter the following values for each setting.

Setting

Value

Project details

Subscription

Select your subscription

Resource group

Select myResourceGroupName from the drop-down

Instance details

Virtual machine name

Enter test-ubuntu-cus-vm

Region

From the dropdown list, select a geographical location close to you.

Availability options

No infrastructure redundancy required

Security type

Standard

Image

Ubuntu Server 24.04 LTS - Gen2

VM architecture

x64

Run with Azure Spot discount

Unchecked

Size

Standard D2s V3

Administrator account

Authentication type

SSH public key

Username

Enter a username

SSH public key source

Generate a new key pair

Key pair name

test-ubuntu-cus-vm_key

Inbound port rules

Public inbound ports

Allow selected ports

Select inbound ports

SSH (22)

- There are several other tabs you can explore to see the settings you can influence during the VM creation. After you're finished exploring, select Review + create to review and validate the settings.

There are several other tabs you can explore to see the settings you can influence during the VM creation. After you're finished exploring, select Review + create to review and validate the settings.

- Azure validates your configuration settings for a resource before it creates it. You might need to supply some additional information based on the requirements of the image creator built into Azure. It's simple; just open the tab that has an error. Verify all the settings are set the way you want, and then select Create to deploy and create the VM.

Azure validates your configuration settings for a resource before it creates it. You might need to supply some additional information based on the requirements of the image creator built into Azure. It's simple; just open the tab that has an error. Verify all the settings are set the way you want, and then select Create to deploy and create the VM.

- The Generate new key pair window opens. Select Download private key and create resource .

The Generate new key pair window opens. Select Download private key and create resource .

- You can monitor the deployment in the Deployment details on the Overview pane or through the Notifications pane. Select the notifications icon in the top right toolbar to show or hide the Notifications pane. The VM deployment process takes a few minutes to complete. You receive a notification informing you that the deployment succeeded.

You can monitor the deployment in the Deployment details on the Overview pane or through the Notifications pane. Select the notifications icon in the top right toolbar to show or hide the Notifications pane.

The VM deployment process takes a few minutes to complete. You receive a notification informing you that the deployment succeeded.

- Select Go to resource . The Overview page of your VM appears. Here, you can see all the information and configuration options for your newly created Ubuntu VM. One of the pieces of information is the Public IP address . When you enabled SSH public key authentication in an earlier step, the user interface also gave an option to enable SSH. SSH allows you to connect to your VM via the public IP using any SSH client.

Select Go to resource . The Overview page of your VM appears.

Here, you can see all the information and configuration options for your newly created Ubuntu VM. One of the pieces of information is the Public IP address .

When you enabled SSH public key authentication in an earlier step, the user interface also gave an option to enable SSH. SSH allows you to connect to your VM via the public IP using any SSH client.

Congratulations! With a few steps, you deployed a VM that runs Linux. Let's explore some other ways we could have created a VM.

Unit 5.1.4 - Describe the options available to create and manage an Azure Virtual Machine

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-virtual-machines/4-describe-other-create-vm-options

Describe the options available to create and manage an Azure Virtual Machine

The Azure portal is the easiest way to create resources such as VMs when you're getting started. However, it's not necessarily the most efficient or quickest way to work with Azure, particularly if you need to create several resources together. In our case, we eventually create dozens of VMs to handle different tasks. Creating them manually in the Azure portal wouldn't be a fun task!

Let's look at some other ways to create and administer resources in Azure:

- Azure Resource Manager templates

- Azure PowerShell

- Azure CLI

- Azure REST API

- Azure Client SDK

- Azure VM Extensions

- Azure Automation Services

Resource Manager templates

Let's assume you want to create a copy of a VM with the same settings. You could create a VM image, upload it to Azure, and reference it as the basis for your new VM. This process is inefficient and time-consuming. Azure provides you with the option to create a template from which to create an exact copy of a VM.

Resource Manager templates are JSON files that define the resources you need to deploy for your solution.

You can create a resource template for your VM. From the VM menu, under Automation select Export template .

Note

The policies for the resources included in the sandbox for this Learn module prevent you from being able to export the VM you just created; that said, an exported template is an easy-to-edit JSON file.

You have the option to download or save a template for later use, or immediately deploy a new VM based on the template. For example, you might create a VM from a template in a test environment, and find it doesn’t quite work to replace your on-premises machine. You can delete the resource group, which deletes all of the resources, tweak the template, and try again. If you only want to make changes to the existing deployed resources, you can change the template used to create it, and redeploy it. Resource Manager will change the resources to match the new template.

After you have it working the way you want it, you can use that template to easily replicate multiple versions of your infrastructure, such as staging and production. You can parameterize fields such as the VM name, network name, storage account name, and so on, and load the template repeatedly, using different parameters to customize each environment.

For more information about using templates, see Quickstart: Create an Ubuntu Linux virtual machine using an ARM template .

Azure CLI

An option for scripting and command-line Azure interaction is the Azure CLI .

The Azure CLI is Microsoft's cross-platform command-line tool for managing Azure resources such as virtual machines and disks from the command line. It's available for Linux, macOS, Windows, or in a browser using the Cloud Shell.

For example, from the CLI, you can create an Azure VM with the az vm create command.

az vm create

az vm create \

--resource-group TestResourceGroup \

--name test-wp1-eus-vm \

--image Ubuntu2204 \

--admin-username azureuser \

--generate-ssh-keys

az vm create \

--resource-group TestResourceGroup \

--name test-wp1-eus-vm \

--image Ubuntu2204 \

--admin-username azureuser \

--generate-ssh-keys

The Azure CLI can be used with other scripting languages, like Ruby and Python.

Learn more about creating and managing VMs in the Manage virtual machines with the Azure CLI tool module.

For more information about using the Azure CLI to create VMs, see Quickstart: Create a Linux virtual machine using the CLI .

Azure PowerShell

Azure PowerShell is ideal for one-off interactive tasks and/or the automation of repeated tasks.

Note

PowerShell is a cross-platform shell that provides services like the shell window and command parsing. Azure PowerShell is an optional add-on package that adds the Azure-specific commands (referred to as cmdlets ). You can learn more about installing and using Azure PowerShell in a separate training module.

For example, you can use the New-AzVM cmdlet to create a new Debian-based Azure virtual machine.

New-AzVM

New-AzVm `

-ResourceGroupName "TestResourceGroup" `

-Name "test-wp1-eus-vm" `

-Location "East US" `

-Image Debian11 `

-VirtualNetworkName "test-wp1-eus-network" `

-SubnetName "default" `

-SecurityGroupName "test-wp1-eus-nsg" `

-PublicIpAddressName "test-wp1-eus-pubip" `

-GenerateSshKey `

-SshKeyName myPSKey

-OpenPorts 22

New-AzVm `

-ResourceGroupName "TestResourceGroup" `

-Name "test-wp1-eus-vm" `

-Location "East US" `

-Image Debian11 `

-VirtualNetworkName "test-wp1-eus-network" `

-SubnetName "default" `

-SecurityGroupName "test-wp1-eus-nsg" `

-PublicIpAddressName "test-wp1-eus-pubip" `

-GenerateSshKey `

-SshKeyName myPSKey

-OpenPorts 22

As shown here, you supply various parameters to handle the large number of VM configuration settings available. Most of the parameters have reasonable values; you only need to specify the required parameters. Learn more about creating and managing VMs with Azure PowerShell in the Automate Azure tasks using scripts with PowerShell module.

For more information about using PowerShell to create VMs, see Quickstart: Create a Linux virtual machine using PowerShell .

Terraform

Azure also has a Terraform provider, so you can easily use Terraform to create and manage your VMs. Terraform enables the definition, preview, and deployment of cloud infrastructure. Using Terraform, you create configuration files using HCL syntax. The HCL syntax allows you to specify the cloud provider - such as Azure - and the elements that make up your cloud infrastructure. After you create your configuration files, you create an execution plan that allows you to preview your infrastructure changes before they're deployed. Once you verify the changes, you apply the execution plan to deploy the infrastructure.

For more information, see the Azure Terraform Provider and Quickstart: Use Terraform to create a VM .

Programmatic (APIs)

Generally speaking, both Azure PowerShell and Azure CLI are good options if you have simple scripts to run and want to stick to command-line tools. When it comes to more complex scenarios, where the creation and management of VMs form part of a larger application with complex logic, another approach is needed.

You can interact with every type of resource in Azure programmatically.

Azure REST API

The Azure REST API provides developers with operations categorized by resource and the ability to create and manage VMs. Operations are exposed as URIs with corresponding HTTP methods ( GET , PUT , POST , DELETE , and PATCH ) and a corresponding response.

GET

PUT

POST

DELETE

PATCH

The Azure Compute APIs give you programmatic access to virtual machines and their supporting resources.

For more information, see the Virtual Machines REST API reference .

Azure Client SDK

Even though the REST API is platform and language agnostic, most often developers look toward a higher level of abstraction. The Azure Client SDK encapsulates the Azure REST API, making it much easier for developers to interact with Azure.

The Azure Client SDKs are available for various languages and frameworks, including .NET-based languages such as C#, Java, Node.js, PHP, Python, Ruby, and Go.

Here's an example snippet of C# code to create an Azure VM using the Microsoft.Azure.Management.Fluent NuGet package.

Microsoft.Azure.Management.Fluent

var azure = Azure

.Configure()

.WithLogLevel(HttpLoggingDelegatingHandler.Level.Basic)

.Authenticate(credentials)

.WithDefaultSubscription();

// ...

var vmName = "test-wp1-eus-vm";

azure.VirtualMachines.Define(vmName)

.WithRegion(Region.USEast)

.WithExistingResourceGroup("TestResourceGroup")

.WithExistingPrimaryNetworkInterface(networkInterface)

.WithLatestWindowsImage("MicrosoftWindowsServer", "WindowsServer", "2012-R2-Datacenter")

.WithAdminUsername("jonc")

.WithAdminPassword("aReallyGoodPasswordHere")

.WithComputerName(vmName)

.WithSize(VirtualMachineSizeTypes.StandardDS1)

.Create();

var azure = Azure

.Configure()

.WithLogLevel(HttpLoggingDelegatingHandler.Level.Basic)

.Authenticate(credentials)

.WithDefaultSubscription();

// ...

var vmName = "test-wp1-eus-vm";

azure.VirtualMachines.Define(vmName)

.WithRegion(Region.USEast)

.WithExistingResourceGroup("TestResourceGroup")

.WithExistingPrimaryNetworkInterface(networkInterface)

.WithLatestWindowsImage("MicrosoftWindowsServer", "WindowsServer", "2012-R2-Datacenter")

.WithAdminUsername("jonc")

.WithAdminPassword("aReallyGoodPasswordHere")

.WithComputerName(vmName)

.WithSize(VirtualMachineSizeTypes.StandardDS1)

.Create();

Here's the same snippet in Java using the Azure Java SDK .

String vmName = "test-wp1-eus-vm";

// ...

VirtualMachine virtualMachine = azure.virtualMachines()

.define(vmName)

.withRegion(Region.US_EAST)

.withExistingResourceGroup("TestResourceGroup")

.withExistingPrimaryNetworkInterface(networkInterface)

.withLatestWindowsImage("MicrosoftWindowsServer", "WindowsServer", "2012-R2-Datacenter")

.withAdminUsername("jonc")

.withAdminPassword("aReallyGoodPasswordHere")

.withComputerName(vmName)

.withSize("Standard_DS1")

.create();

String vmName = "test-wp1-eus-vm";

// ...

VirtualMachine virtualMachine = azure.virtualMachines()

.define(vmName)

.withRegion(Region.US_EAST)

.withExistingResourceGroup("TestResourceGroup")

.withExistingPrimaryNetworkInterface(networkInterface)

.withLatestWindowsImage("MicrosoftWindowsServer", "WindowsServer", "2012-R2-Datacenter")

.withAdminUsername("jonc")

.withAdminPassword("aReallyGoodPasswordHere")

.withComputerName(vmName)

.withSize("Standard_DS1")

.create();

Azure VM extensions

Let's assume you want to configure and install more software on your virtual machine after the initial deployment. You want this task to use a specific configuration, monitored and executed automatically.

Azure VM extensions are small applications that enable you to configure and automate tasks on Azure VMs after initial deployment.

For more information, see Azure virtual machine extensions and features .

Azure Automation services

Saving time, reducing errors, and increasing efficiency are some of the most significant operational management challenges faced when managing remote infrastructure. If you have numerous infrastructure services, you might want to consider using higher-level services in Azure to help you operate from a higher level.

Azure Automation enables you to integrate services that allow you to automate frequent, time-consuming, and error-prone management tasks with ease. These services include process automation , configuration management , and update management .

- Process Automation . Let's assume you have a VM that is monitored for a specific error event. You want to take action, and fix the problem as soon as it's reported. Process automation enables you to set up watcher tasks that can respond to events that may occur in your datacenter.

Process Automation . Let's assume you have a VM that is monitored for a specific error event. You want to take action, and fix the problem as soon as it's reported. Process automation enables you to set up watcher tasks that can respond to events that may occur in your datacenter.

- Configuration Management . Perhaps you want to track software updates that become available for the operating system that runs on your VM. There are specific updates you may want to include or exclude. Configuration management enables you to track these updates, and take action as required. You use Microsoft Endpoint Configuration Manager to manage your company's PC, servers, and mobile devices. You can extend this support to your Azure VMs with Configuration Manager.

Configuration Management . Perhaps you want to track software updates that become available for the operating system that runs on your VM. There are specific updates you may want to include or exclude. Configuration management enables you to track these updates, and take action as required. You use Microsoft Endpoint Configuration Manager to manage your company's PC, servers, and mobile devices. You can extend this support to your Azure VMs with Configuration Manager.

- Update Management . Use this service to manage updates and patches for your VMs. With this service, you're able to assess the status of available updates, schedule installation, and review deployment results to verify updates applied successfully. Update management incorporates services that provide process and configuration management. You enable update management for a VM directly from your Azure Automation account. You can also enable update management for a single virtual machine from the virtual machine pane in the portal.

Update Management . Use this service to manage updates and patches for your VMs. With this service, you're able to assess the status of available updates, schedule installation, and review deployment results to verify updates applied successfully. Update management incorporates services that provide process and configuration management. You enable update management for a VM directly from your Azure Automation account. You can also enable update management for a single virtual machine from the virtual machine pane in the portal.

Auto-shutdown

Auto-shutdown is a feature in Azure that allows you to automatically shut down your VMs on a schedule. Use Auto-shutdown to save costs by ensuring that your VMs are not running when they aren't needed. You can set the schedule for auto-shutdown to occur daily or weekly, and you can also specify the time zone for the schedule.

To navigate to the Auto-shutdown feature in a VM in the Azure portal, go to the VM's blade in the portal, click on "Auto-shutdown" under the "Operations" section, and then configure the auto-shutdown settings according to your preferences.

For more information, see Auto-shutdown .

As you can see, Azure provides various tools to create and administer resources so that you can integrate management operations into a process that works for you . Let's examine some of the other Azure services to make sure your infrastructure resources are running smoothly.

Unit 5.1.5 - Manage the availability of your Azure VMs

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-virtual-machines/5-high-availability

Manage the availability of your Azure VMs

Frequently, the success of a services company is directly related to the service level agreements (SLA) the company has with its customers. Your customers expect the services you provide always to be available, and their data kept safe. This security is something that Microsoft takes seriously. Azure provides tools you can use to manage availability, data security, and monitoring, so you know your services are always available for your customers.

Administration of an Azure VM isn't limited to managing the operating system, or software that runs on the VM. It helps to know which services Azure provides that ensure service availability and support automation. These services help you to plan your organization's business continuity and disaster recovery strategy.

Here, we cover an Azure service that helps you improve VM availability, streamlines VM management tasks, and keeps your VM data backed up and safe. Let's start by defining availability.

What is availability?

Availability is the percentage of time a service is available for use.

Let's assume you have a website, and you want your customers to be able to always access information. Your expectation is 100% availability concerning website access.

Why do I need to think about availability when using Azure?

Azure VMs run on physical servers hosted within the Azure datacenter. As with most physical devices, there's a chance that there could be a failure. If the physical server fails, the virtual machines hosted on that server also fail. If a failure happens, Azure moves the VM to a healthy host server automatically. However, this self-healing migration could take several minutes, during which the application(s) hosted on that VM aren't available.

Periodic updates initiated by Azure itself can also affect the VMs. These maintenance events range from software updates to hardware upgrades and are required to improve platform reliability and performance. These events usually are performed without impacting any guest VMs, but sometimes the virtual machines reboot to complete an update or upgrade.

Availability zones

Availability zones expands the level of control you have to maintain the availability of the applications and data on your VMs. An Availability Zone is a physically separate zone, within an Azure region. There are three Availability Zones per supported Azure region.

Each Availability Zone has a distinct power source, network, and cooling. By designing your solutions to use replicated VMs in zones, you can protect your apps and data from the loss of a data center. If one zone is compromised, then replicated apps and data are instantly available in another zone.

Virtual Machines Scale Sets

Azure virtual machine scale sets let you create and manage a group of load balanced VMs. The number of VM instances can automatically increase or decrease in response to demand or a defined schedule. Scale sets provide high availability to your applications, and allow you to centrally manage, configure, and update many VMs. There's no cost for the scale set itself, you only pay for each VM instance that you create.

Virtual machines in a scale set can also be deployed into multiple availability zones, a single availability zone, or regionally. Availability zone deployment options may differ based on the orchestration mode .

Load balancer

Combine the Azure Load Balancer with an availability zone or availability set to get the most application resiliency. The Azure Load Balancer distributes traffic between multiple virtual machines. For our Standard tier virtual machines, the Azure Load Balancer is included. Not all virtual machine tiers include the Azure Load Balancer. For more information about load balancing your virtual machines, see Load Balancing virtual machines for Linux or Windows .

Azure Storage redundancy

Azure Storage always stores multiple copies of your data so that it's protected from planned and unplanned events, including transient hardware failures, network or power outages, and massive natural disasters. Redundancy ensures that your storage account meets its availability and durability targets even in the face of failures.

When deciding which redundancy option is best for your scenario, consider the tradeoffs between lower costs and higher availability. The factors that help determine which redundancy option you should choose include:

- How your data is replicated in the primary region

- Whether your data is replicated to a second region that is geographically distant to the primary region, to protect against regional disasters

- Whether your application requires read access to the replicated data in the secondary region if the primary region becomes unavailable for any reason

For more information, see Azure Storage redundancy .

Failover across locations

You can also replicate your infrastructure across sites to handle regional failover. Azure Site Recovery replicates workloads from a primary site to a secondary location. If an outage happens at your primary site, you can fail over to a secondary location. This failover enables users to continue to access your applications without interruption. You can then fail back to the primary location after it's up and running again. Azure Site Recovery is about replication of virtual or physical machines; it keeps your workloads available in an outage.

While there are many attractive technical features to Site Recovery, there are at least two significant business advantages:

- Site Recovery enables the use of Azure as a destination for recovery, thus eliminating the cost and complexity of maintaining a secondary physical datacenter.

Site Recovery enables the use of Azure as a destination for recovery, thus eliminating the cost and complexity of maintaining a secondary physical datacenter.

- Site Recovery makes it incredibly simple to test failovers for recovery drills without impacting production environments. This feature makes it easy to test your planned or unplanned failovers. After all, you don’t have a good disaster recovery plan if you’ve never tried to fail over.

Site Recovery makes it incredibly simple to test failovers for recovery drills without impacting production environments. This feature makes it easy to test your planned or unplanned failovers. After all, you don’t have a good disaster recovery plan if you’ve never tried to fail over.

The recovery plans you create with Site Recovery can be as simple or as complex as your scenario requires. They can include custom PowerShell scripts, Azure Automation runbooks, or manual intervention steps. You can use the recovery plans to replicate workloads to Azure, easily enabling new opportunities for migration, temporary bursts during surge periods, or development and testing of new applications.

Azure Site Recovery works with Azure resources, or Hyper-V, VMware, and physical servers in your on-premises infrastructure. It can be a key part of your organization’s business continuity and disaster recovery (BCDR) strategy by orchestrating the replication, failover, and recovery of workloads and applications if the primary location fails.

Unit 5.1.6 - Back up your virtual machines

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-virtual-machines/6-backup-services

Back up your virtual machines

Data backup and recovery is a necessary piece of the planning for any good infrastructure. Assume a bug erases some company data, or maybe you need to retrieve some archived data for auditing purposes. Maintaining a good backup strategy ensures that you aren't scrambling when data or software needs to be restored.

Azure Backup is a backup as a service offering that protects physical or virtual machines no matter where they reside: on-premises or in the cloud.

Azure Backup can be used for a wide range of data backup scenarios, such as:

- Files and folders on Windows OS machines (physical or virtual, local or cloud)

- Application-aware snapshots (Volume Shadow Copy Service)

- Popular Microsoft server workloads such as Microsoft SQL Server, Microsoft SharePoint, and Microsoft Exchange

- Native support for Azure Virtual Machines, both Windows, and Linux

- Linux and Windows 10 client machines

Advantages of using Azure Backup

Traditional backup solutions don't always take full advantage of the underlying Azure platform. The result is a solution that tends to be expensive or inefficient. The solution either offers too much or too little storage, doesn't offer the correct types of storage, or has cumbersome and long-winded administrative tasks. Azure Backup was designed to work in tandem with other Azure services and provides several distinct benefits.

- Automatic storage management . Azure Backup automatically allocates and manages backup storage and uses a pay-as-you-use model. You only pay for what you use.

Automatic storage management . Azure Backup automatically allocates and manages backup storage and uses a pay-as-you-use model. You only pay for what you use.

- Unlimited scaling . Azure Backup uses the power and scalability of Azure to deliver high availability.

Unlimited scaling . Azure Backup uses the power and scalability of Azure to deliver high availability.

- Multiple storage options . Azure Backup offers locally redundant storage where all copies of the data exist within the same region and geo-redundant storage where your data is replicated to a secondary region.

Multiple storage options . Azure Backup offers locally redundant storage where all copies of the data exist within the same region and geo-redundant storage where your data is replicated to a secondary region.

- Unlimited data transfer . Azure Backup doesn't limit the amount of inbound or outbound data you transfer. Azure Backup also doesn't charge for the data that is transferred.

Unlimited data transfer . Azure Backup doesn't limit the amount of inbound or outbound data you transfer. Azure Backup also doesn't charge for the data that is transferred.

- Data encryption . Data encryption allows for secure transmission and storage of your data in Azure.

Data encryption . Data encryption allows for secure transmission and storage of your data in Azure.

- Application-consistent backup . An application-consistent backup means that a recovery point has all required data to restore the backup copy. Azure Backup provides application-consistent backups.

Application-consistent backup . An application-consistent backup means that a recovery point has all required data to restore the backup copy. Azure Backup provides application-consistent backups.

- Long-term retention . Azure doesn't limit the length of time you keep the backup data.

Long-term retention . Azure doesn't limit the length of time you keep the backup data.

Use Azure Backup

Azure Backup uses several components that you download and deploy to each computer you want to back up. The component that you deploy depends on what you want to protect.

- Azure Backup agent

- System Center Data Protection Manager

- Azure Backup Server

- Azure Backup VM extension

Azure Backup uses a Recovery Services vault for storing the backup data. Azure Storage blobs back up a vault, making it an efficient and economical long-term storage medium. With the vault in place, you can select the machines to back up, and define a backup policy (when snapshots are taken and for how long they’re stored).

Unit 5.1.7 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-virtual-machines/7-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Check your knowledge

Unit 5.1.8 - Summary

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-virtual-machines/8-summary

Summary

In this module, you looked at the decisions you need to make before creating a virtual machine. These decisions include aspects such as the VM size, types of disks used, operating system image selected, and the types of resources created.

You also looked at the options to create and manage virtual machines in Azure. You saw how easy it is to create and manage VMs using the portal. You also learned when to use Resource Manager templates, PowerShell, the Azure CLI, and the Azure Client SDK.

Finally, you looked at the extensions and services available to more easily administer your VMs.

Important

In the optional exercises for this module, you created resources by using your own Azure subscription. Clean up these resources so that you won't continue to be charged for them.

LP 5 M2 - Configure virtual machine availability

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-machine-availability/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 5.2.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-machine-availability/1-introduction

Introduction

Managing virtual machines at scale can be challenging, especially when usage patterns vary and demands on applications fluctuate. Azure Administrators need to be able to adjust their virtual machine resources to match changing demands. At the same time, they need to keep their virtual machine configuration consistent to ensure application stability. Achieving these goals means maintaining throughput and responsiveness while minimizing the costs of continually running a large collection of virtual machines.

Your company website uses virtual machines and manages large workloads. The IT department wants to ensure the virtual machines can dynamically adjust to increases and decreases in workloads. They also want to ensure there's a business continuity plan to provide for highly available machines. You're responsible for deploying highly available virtual machines. You decide to use Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets and the autoscale feature.

In this module, you learn about scaling virtual machines. You learn about availability zones, availability sets, and update and fault domains. You also learn about scale sets and autoscale.

The goal of this module is to learn how to successfully respond to changing virtual machine workloads.

Learning objectives

In this module, you learn how to:

- Implement availability sets and availability zones.

- Implement update and fault domains.

- Implement Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets.

- Autoscale virtual machines.

Skills measured

The content in the module helps you prepare for Exam AZ-104: Microsoft Azure Administrator .

Prerequisites

- Familiarity with creating and managing Azure virtual machines.

- General knowledge of scaling infrastructure resources in fluctuating workloads.

Unit 5.2.2 - Plan for maintenance and downtime

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-machine-availability/2-plan-for-maintenance-downtime

Plan for maintenance and downtime

Azure Administrators prepare for planned and unplanned failures.

Things to know about maintenance planning

An availability plan for Azure virtual machines needs to include strategies for unplanned hardware maintenance, unexpected downtime, and planned maintenance.

- An unplanned hardware maintenance event occurs when the Azure platform predicts that the hardware or any platform component associated to a physical machine is about to fail. When the platform predicts a failure, it issues an unplanned hardware maintenance event. Azure uses Live Migration technology to migrate your virtual machines from the failing hardware to a healthy physical machine. Live Migration is a virtual machine preserving operation that only pauses the virtual machine for a short time, but performance might be reduced before or after the event.

An unplanned hardware maintenance event occurs when the Azure platform predicts that the hardware or any platform component associated to a physical machine is about to fail. When the platform predicts a failure, it issues an unplanned hardware maintenance event. Azure uses Live Migration technology to migrate your virtual machines from the failing hardware to a healthy physical machine. Live Migration is a virtual machine preserving operation that only pauses the virtual machine for a short time, but performance might be reduced before or after the event.

- Unexpected downtime occurs when the hardware or the physical infrastructure for your virtual machine fails unexpectedly. Unexpected downtime can include local network failures, local disk failures, or other rack level failures. When detected, the Azure platform automatically migrates (heals) your virtual machine to a healthy physical machine in the same datacenter. During the healing procedure, virtual machines experience downtime (reboot) and in some cases loss of the temporary drive.

Unexpected downtime occurs when the hardware or the physical infrastructure for your virtual machine fails unexpectedly. Unexpected downtime can include local network failures, local disk failures, or other rack level failures. When detected, the Azure platform automatically migrates (heals) your virtual machine to a healthy physical machine in the same datacenter. During the healing procedure, virtual machines experience downtime (reboot) and in some cases loss of the temporary drive.

- Planned maintenance events are periodic updates made by Microsoft to the underlying Azure platform to improve overall reliability, performance, and security of the platform infrastructure that your virtual machines run on.

Planned maintenance events are periodic updates made by Microsoft to the underlying Azure platform to improve overall reliability, performance, and security of the platform infrastructure that your virtual machines run on.

Note

Microsoft doesn't automatically update your virtual machine operating system or other software. You have complete control and responsibility for those updates. However, the underlying software host and hardware are periodically patched to ensure reliability and high performance.

Unit 5.2.3 - Create availability sets

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-machine-availability/3-setup-availability-sets

Create availability sets

An availability set is a logical feature you can use to ensure a group of related virtual machines are deployed together. The grouping helps to prevent a single point of failure from affecting all of your machines. The grouping ensures that not all of the machines are upgraded at the same time during a host operating system upgrade in the datacenter.

Things to know about availability sets

Let's review some characteristics of availability sets.

- All virtual machines in an availability set should perform the identical set of functionalities.

All virtual machines in an availability set should perform the identical set of functionalities.

- All virtual machines in an availability set should have the same software installed.

All virtual machines in an availability set should have the same software installed.

- Azure ensures that virtual machines in an availability set run across multiple physical servers, compute racks, storage units, and network switches. If a hardware or Azure software failure occurs, only a subset of the virtual machines in the availability set are affected. Your application stays up and continues to be available to your customers.

Azure ensures that virtual machines in an availability set run across multiple physical servers, compute racks, storage units, and network switches.

If a hardware or Azure software failure occurs, only a subset of the virtual machines in the availability set are affected. Your application stays up and continues to be available to your customers.

- You can create a virtual machine and an availability set at the same time. A virtual machine can only be added to an availability set when the virtual machine is created. To change the availability set for a virtual machine, you need to delete and then recreate the virtual machine.

You can create a virtual machine and an availability set at the same time.

A virtual machine can only be added to an availability set when the virtual machine is created. To change the availability set for a virtual machine, you need to delete and then recreate the virtual machine.

- You can build availability sets by using the Azure portal, Azure Resource Manager (ARM) templates, scripting, or API tools.

You can build availability sets by using the Azure portal, Azure Resource Manager (ARM) templates, scripting, or API tools.

Note

Adding your virtual machines to an availability set doesn't protect your applications from operating system or application-specific failures. You need to explore other disaster recovery and backup techniques to provide application-level protection.

Things to consider when using availability sets

Availability sets are an essential capability when you want to build reliable cloud solutions. In your planning for availability sets, keep the following general principles in mind:

- Consider redundancy . To achieve redundancy in your configuration, place multiple virtual machines in an availability set.

Consider redundancy . To achieve redundancy in your configuration, place multiple virtual machines in an availability set.

- Consider separation of application tiers . Each application tier exercised in your configuration should be located in a separate availability set. The separation helps to mitigate single point of failure on all machines.

Consider separation of application tiers . Each application tier exercised in your configuration should be located in a separate availability set. The separation helps to mitigate single point of failure on all machines.

- Consider load balancing . For high availability and network performance, create a load-balanced availability set by using Azure Load Balancer. Load Balancer distributes incoming traffic across working instances of services that are defined in your load-balanced availability set.

Consider load balancing . For high availability and network performance, create a load-balanced availability set by using Azure Load Balancer. Load Balancer distributes incoming traffic across working instances of services that are defined in your load-balanced availability set.

- Consider managed disks . You can use Azure managed disks with your Azure virtual machines in availability sets for block-level storage.

Consider managed disks . You can use Azure managed disks with your Azure virtual machines in availability sets for block-level storage.

Unit 5.2.4 - Review update domains and fault domains

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-machine-availability/4-review-update-fault-domains

Review update domains and fault domains

Azure Virtual Machine Availability Sets implements two node concepts to help Azure maintain high availability and fault tolerance when deploying and upgrading applications: update domains and fault domains . Each virtual machine in an availability set is placed in one update domain and one fault domain.

Things to know about update domains

An update domain is a group of nodes that are upgraded together during the process of a service upgrade (or roll out ). An update domain allows Azure to perform incremental or rolling upgrades across a deployment. Here are some other characteristics of update domains.

- Each update domain contains a set of virtual machines and associated physical hardware that can be updated and rebooted at the same time.

Each update domain contains a set of virtual machines and associated physical hardware that can be updated and rebooted at the same time.

- During planned maintenance, only one update domain is rebooted at a time.

During planned maintenance, only one update domain is rebooted at a time.

- You can specify between 1 and 20 update domains when creating an availability set. If you don't specify a value, Azure defaults to five update domains.

You can specify between 1 and 20 update domains when creating an availability set. If you don't specify a value, Azure defaults to five update domains.

- The update domain count is immutable after creation; to change it, you must delete and recreate the availability set.

The update domain count is immutable after creation; to change it, you must delete and recreate the availability set.

Things to know about fault domains

A fault domain is a group of nodes that represent a physical unit of failure. Think of a fault domain as nodes that belong to the same physical rack.

- A fault domain defines a group of virtual machines that share a common set of hardware (or switches ) that share a single point of failure. An example is a server rack serviced by a set of power or networking switches.

A fault domain defines a group of virtual machines that share a common set of hardware (or switches ) that share a single point of failure. An example is a server rack serviced by a set of power or networking switches.

- Two fault domains work together to mitigate against hardware failures, network outages, power interruptions, or software updates.

Two fault domains work together to mitigate against hardware failures, network outages, power interruptions, or software updates.

Let's look at a scenario with two fault domains that have two virtual machines each. The virtual machines in each fault domain are contained in different availability sets. The web availability set contains two virtual machines with one machine from each fault domain. The SQL availability set contains two different virtual machines with one from each fault domain.

Unit 5.2.5 - Review availability zones

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-machine-availability/5-review-availability-zones

Review availability zones

Availability zones are a high-availability offering that protects your applications and data from datacenter failures. You can use availability zones to build high-availability into your application architecture by colocating your compute, storage, networking, and data resources within a zone and replicating in other zones.

Consider a scenario where you create three or more virtual machines across three zones in an Azure region. Your virtual machines are effectively distributed across three fault domains and three update domains. The Azure platform recognizes this distribution across update domains to make sure that virtual machines in different zones aren't updated at the same time.

Things to know about availability zones

Review the following characteristics of availability zones.

- Availability zones are unique physical locations within an Azure region.

Availability zones are unique physical locations within an Azure region.

- Each zone is made up of one or more datacenters that are equipped with independent power, cooling, and networking.

Each zone is made up of one or more datacenters that are equipped with independent power, cooling, and networking.

- To ensure resiliency, there's a minimum of three separate zones in all enabled regions.

To ensure resiliency, there's a minimum of three separate zones in all enabled regions.

- The physical separation of availability zones within a region protects applications and data from datacenter failures.

The physical separation of availability zones within a region protects applications and data from datacenter failures.

- Zone-redundant services replicate your applications and data across availability zones to protect against single-points-of-failure.

Zone-redundant services replicate your applications and data across availability zones to protect against single-points-of-failure.

Things to consider when using availability zones

Azure services that support availability zones are divided into two categories.

Category

Description

Examples

Zonal services

Azure zonal services pin each resource to a specific zone.

- Azure virtual machines - Azure managed disks

Zone-redundant services

For Azure services that are zone-redundant, the platform replicates automatically across all zones.

- Azure Storage that's zone-redundant - Azure SQL Database

Note

> Note: Standard IP addresses can be configured as zone-redundant (recommended for high availability), zonal (pinned to a specific zone), or non-zonal (regional) depending on your deployment choice.

Note: Standard IP addresses can be configured as zone-redundant (recommended for high availability), zonal (pinned to a specific zone), or non-zonal (regional) depending on your deployment choice.

Tip

To achieve comprehensive business continuity on Azure, build your application architecture with a combination of availability zones and Azure regional pairs .

Unit 5.2.6 - Compare vertical and horizontal scaling

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-machine-availability/6-compare-vertical-horizontal-scaling

Compare vertical and horizontal scaling

A robust virtual machine configuration includes support for scalability. Scalability allows throughput for a virtual machine in proportion to the availability of the associated hardware resources. A scalable virtual machine can handle increases in requests without adversely affecting response time and throughput. For most scaling operations, there are two implementation options: vertical and horizontal .

Things to know about vertical scaling

Vertical scaling, also known as scale up and scale down , involves increasing or decreasing the virtual machine size in response to a workload. Vertical scaling makes a virtual machine more (scale up) or less (scale down) powerful.

Here are some scenarios where using vertical scaling can be advantageous:

- If you have a service built on a virtual machine that's under-utilized such as on the weekend, you can use vertical scaling to decrease the virtual machine size and reduce your monthly costs.

If you have a service built on a virtual machine that's under-utilized such as on the weekend, you can use vertical scaling to decrease the virtual machine size and reduce your monthly costs.

- You can implement vertical scaling to increase your virtual machine size to support larger demand without having to create extra virtual machines.

You can implement vertical scaling to increase your virtual machine size to support larger demand without having to create extra virtual machines.

Things to know about horizontal scaling

Horizontal scaling, also referred to as scale out and scale in , is used to adjust the number of virtual machines in your configuration to support the changing workload. When you implement horizontal scaling, there's an increase (scale out) or decrease (scale in) in the number of virtual machine instances.

Things to consider when using vertical and horizontal scaling

Review the following considerations regarding vertical and horizontal scaling. Think about which implementation might be required to support your company website.

- Consider limitations . Generally speaking, horizontal scaling has fewer limitations than vertical scaling. A vertical scaling implementation depends on the availability of larger hardware, which quickly hits an upper limit and can vary by region. Vertical scaling also usually requires a virtual machine to stop and restart, which can temporarily limit access to applications or data.

Consider limitations . Generally speaking, horizontal scaling has fewer limitations than vertical scaling. A vertical scaling implementation depends on the availability of larger hardware, which quickly hits an upper limit and can vary by region. Vertical scaling also usually requires a virtual machine to stop and restart, which can temporarily limit access to applications or data.

- Consider flexibility . When operating in the cloud, horizontal scaling is more flexible. A horizontal scaling implementation allows you to run potentially thousands of virtual machines to manage changes in workload and throughput.

Consider flexibility . When operating in the cloud, horizontal scaling is more flexible. A horizontal scaling implementation allows you to run potentially thousands of virtual machines to manage changes in workload and throughput.

- Consider reprovisioning . Reprovisioning is the process of removing an existing virtual machine and replacing it with a new machine. A robust availability plan considers where reprovisioning might be required and plans for interruptions to service. If reprovisioning might be required, determine if any data needs to be maintained and migrated to the new machine.

Consider reprovisioning . Reprovisioning is the process of removing an existing virtual machine and replacing it with a new machine. A robust availability plan considers where reprovisioning might be required and plans for interruptions to service. If reprovisioning might be required, determine if any data needs to be maintained and migrated to the new machine.

Unit 5.2.7 - Implement Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-machine-availability/7-implement-scale-sets

Implement Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets

Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets are an Azure Compute resource that you can use to deploy and manage a set of identical virtual machines. When you implement Virtual Machine Scale Sets and configure all your virtual machines in the same way, you gain true autoscaling . Virtual Machine Scale Sets automatically increases the number of your virtual machine instances as application demand increases, and reduces the number of machine instances as demand decreases.

With Virtual Machine Scale Sets, you don't need to pre-provision your virtual machines. It's easier to build large-scale services that target large compute, big data, and containerized workloads. As workloads increase, more virtual machine instances can be added. As workloads decrease, virtual machines instances can be removed. The process of adding and removing machines can be manual or automated, or a combination of both.

Increase app availability and scalability with Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets

Things to know about Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets

Review the following characteristics of Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets.

- Virtual Machine Scale Sets support the use of Azure Load Balancer for basic layer-4 traffic distribution, and Azure Application Gateway for more advanced layer-7 traffic distribution and TLS/SSL termination.

Virtual Machine Scale Sets support the use of Azure Load Balancer for basic layer-4 traffic distribution, and Azure Application Gateway for more advanced layer-7 traffic distribution and TLS/SSL termination.

- You can use Virtual Machine Scale Sets to run multiple instances of your application. If one of the virtual machine instances has a problem, customers continue to access your application through another virtual machine instance with minimal interruption.

You can use Virtual Machine Scale Sets to run multiple instances of your application. If one of the virtual machine instances has a problem, customers continue to access your application through another virtual machine instance with minimal interruption.

- There are two types of orchestration modes available for Azure virtual machine scale sets: Uniform and Flexible. In Uniform orchestration mode , all virtual machine instances are created from the same base operating system image and configuration. In Flexible orchestration mode , VMs can use different images, sizes, or configurations within the same scale set. The orchestration mode must be chosen when the scale set is created.

There are two types of orchestration modes available for Azure virtual machine scale sets: Uniform and Flexible. In Uniform orchestration mode , all virtual machine instances are created from the same base operating system image and configuration. In Flexible orchestration mode , VMs can use different images, sizes, or configurations within the same scale set. The orchestration mode must be chosen when the scale set is created.

- Customer demand for your application might change throughout the day or week. To meet customer demand, Virtual Machine Scale Sets implements autoscaling to automatically increase and decrease the number of virtual machines.

Customer demand for your application might change throughout the day or week. To meet customer demand, Virtual Machine Scale Sets implements autoscaling to automatically increase and decrease the number of virtual machines.

Unit 5.2.8 - Create Virtual Machine Scale Sets

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-machine-availability/8-create-scale-sets

Create Virtual Machine Scale Sets

You can implement Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets in the Azure portal. You specify the number of virtual machines and their sizes, and indicate preferences for using Azure Spot instances, Azure managed disks, and allocation policies.

In the Azure portal, there are several settings to configure to create an Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets implementation.

- Orchestration mode : Choose how the scale set manages the virtual machines. Flexible orchestration is the default and recommended mode for new deployments. For most new workloads, accept the Flexible default unless you have a specific requirement for identical instances.

Orchestration mode : Choose how the scale set manages the virtual machines. Flexible orchestration is the default and recommended mode for new deployments. For most new workloads, accept the Flexible default unless you have a specific requirement for identical instances.

- Image : Choose the base operating system or application for the VM.

Image : Choose the base operating system or application for the VM.

- VM Architecture : Azure provides a choice of x64 or Arm64-based virtual machines to run your applications. x64-based VMs provide the most software compatibility. Arm64-based VMs provide up to 50% better price-performance than comparable x64 VMs.

VM Architecture : Azure provides a choice of x64 or Arm64-based virtual machines to run your applications. x64-based VMs provide the most software compatibility. Arm64-based VMs provide up to 50% better price-performance than comparable x64 VMs.

- Size : Select a VM size to support the workload that you want to run. The size that you choose then determines factors such as processing power, memory, and storage capacity. Azure offers a wide variety of sizes to support many types of uses. Azure charges an hourly price based on the VM's size and operating system.

Size : Select a VM size to support the workload that you want to run. The size that you choose then determines factors such as processing power, memory, and storage capacity. Azure offers a wide variety of sizes to support many types of uses. Azure charges an hourly price based on the VM's size and operating system.

Under the Advanced tab, you can also select the following:

- Spreading algorithm : The spreading algorithm determines how VMs in the scale set are balanced across fault domains. With max spreading, VMs are spread across as many fault domains as possible in each zone. With fixed spreading, VMs are always spread across exactly five fault domains. In the case where fewer than five fault domains are available, a scale set using "Max spreading" completes, while a scale set using "Fixed spreading" fails. For this reason, Microsoft recommends using Max spreading for your implementation.

Unit 5.2.9 - Implement autoscale

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-machine-availability/9-implement-autoscale

Implement autoscale

An Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets implementation can automatically increase or decrease the number of virtual machine instances that run your application. This process is known as autoscaling . Autoscaling allows you to dynamically scale your configuration to meet changing workload demands.

Autoscaling minimizes the number of unnecessary virtual machine instances that run your application when demand is low. Your customers continue to receive an acceptable level of performance as demand grows and more virtual machine instances are automatically added.

Things to consider when using autoscaling

Review the following considerations about autoscaling. Think about how this process can benefit your company website implementation.

- Consider automatic adjusted capacity . You can create autoscaling rules to define the acceptable performance for a positive customer experience. When the defined thresholds are met, the autoscale rules act to adjust the capacity of your Virtual Machine Scale Sets implementation.

Consider automatic adjusted capacity . You can create autoscaling rules to define the acceptable performance for a positive customer experience. When the defined thresholds are met, the autoscale rules act to adjust the capacity of your Virtual Machine Scale Sets implementation.

- Consider scale out . If your application demand increases, the load on the virtual machine instances in your implementation increases. If the increased load is consistent, rather than a brief demand, you can configure autoscale rules to increase the number of virtual machine instances in your implementation.

Consider scale out . If your application demand increases, the load on the virtual machine instances in your implementation increases. If the increased load is consistent, rather than a brief demand, you can configure autoscale rules to increase the number of virtual machine instances in your implementation.

- Consider scale in . On an evening or weekend, your application demand might decrease. If the decreased load is consistent over a period of time, you can configure autoscale rules to decrease the number of virtual machine instances in your implementation. The scale-in action reduces the cost to run your Virtual Machine Scale Sets implementation as you only run the number of instances required to meet the current demand.

Consider scale in . On an evening or weekend, your application demand might decrease. If the decreased load is consistent over a period of time, you can configure autoscale rules to decrease the number of virtual machine instances in your implementation. The scale-in action reduces the cost to run your Virtual Machine Scale Sets implementation as you only run the number of instances required to meet the current demand.

- Consider scheduled events . You can implement autoscaling and schedule events to automatically increase or decrease the capacity of your implementation at fixed times.

Consider scheduled events . You can implement autoscaling and schedule events to automatically increase or decrease the capacity of your implementation at fixed times.

- Consider overhead . Using Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets with autoscaling reduces your management overhead to monitor and optimize the performance of your application.

Consider overhead . Using Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets with autoscaling reduces your management overhead to monitor and optimize the performance of your application.

Unit 5.2.10 - Configure autoscale

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-machine-availability/10-configure-autoscale

Configure autoscale

When you create an Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets implementation in the Azure portal, you can enable manual or autoscaling. For optimal performance, you should define a minimum, maximum, and default number of virtual machine instances to use.

In the Azure portal, you can select the scaling mode.

Scaling mode

- Manually update the capacity : Maintain a fixed instances count. Set the Instance count to the number of virtual machines in the scale set (0 - 1000). Configure the Scale-in policy which is the order virtual machines are selected for deletion. For example, you could balance across zones and then delete the virtual machine with the highest instance ID.

Manually update the capacity : Maintain a fixed instances count. Set the Instance count to the number of virtual machines in the scale set (0 - 1000). Configure the Scale-in policy which is the order virtual machines are selected for deletion. For example, you could balance across zones and then delete the virtual machine with the highest instance ID.

- Autoscaling : Scaling based on a CPU metric, or any schedule.

Autoscaling : Scaling based on a CPU metric, or any schedule.

Configure autoscaling

Autoscaling is based on a scaling condition.

- Default instance count. The initial number of virtual machines deployed in this scale set (0-1000).

Default instance count. The initial number of virtual machines deployed in this scale set (0-1000).

- Instance limit. The minimum instance count you want this condition to scale down to. The maximum instance count you want this condition to scale up to.

Instance limit. The minimum instance count you want this condition to scale down to. The maximum instance count you want this condition to scale up to.

- Scale out. The CPU usage percentage threshold for triggering the scale-out autoscale rule. The number of instances to scale out by.

Scale out. The CPU usage percentage threshold for triggering the scale-out autoscale rule. The number of instances to scale out by.

- Scale in. The CPU usage percentage threshold for triggering the scale-in autoscale rule. The number of instances to scale in by.

Scale in. The CPU usage percentage threshold for triggering the scale-in autoscale rule. The number of instances to scale in by.

- Query duration : This duration is the time the Autoscale engine looks back for the metric usage average. This look back is to allow your metric to stabilize.

Query duration : This duration is the time the Autoscale engine looks back for the metric usage average. This look back is to allow your metric to stabilize.

- Schedule : Specify the start and end dates. You can also repeat the schedule on specific days.

Schedule : Specify the start and end dates. You can also repeat the schedule on specific days.

Unit 5.2.11 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-machine-availability/11-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Your organization has diverse requirements for the configuration and availability of their virtual machines. You're responsible for helping with the configuration to fulfill requests and resolve issues.

- The Admin team is testing an implementation of Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets with five virtual machines. During testing, monitoring alerts show all virtual machines running at maximum capacity. However, you discover that when the CPU is fully consumed more virtual machines aren't deploying in the scale set.

The Admin team is testing an implementation of Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets with five virtual machines. During testing, monitoring alerts show all virtual machines running at maximum capacity. However, you discover that when the CPU is fully consumed more virtual machines aren't deploying in the scale set.

- The DevOps team wants to configure Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets for their production servers. Thursday evening is typically the busiest time in preparation for delivery to customers by COB on Friday. Conversely, early Monday is generally the quietest time. You need a plan to add more machines when the workload is high.

The DevOps team wants to configure Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets for their production servers. Thursday evening is typically the busiest time in preparation for delivery to customers by COB on Friday. Conversely, early Monday is generally the quietest time. You need a plan to add more machines when the workload is high.

- As load increases on applications hosted in Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets, you want to increase the CPU capacity of the existing instances rather than deploy more instances.

As load increases on applications hosted in Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets, you want to increase the CPU capacity of the existing instances rather than deploy more instances.

Answer the following questions

Choose the best response for each question.

Unit 5.2.12 - Summary and resources

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-virtual-machine-availability/12-summary-resources

Summary and resources

Azure provides several high availability options for virtual machines. You can achieve high availability by using availability sets, availability zones, and Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets.

In this module, you learned how to configure virtual machine availability by using availability sets and availability zones with update and fault domains. You discovered how to autoscale virtual machines and configure vertical and horizontal scaling. You reviewed how to implement Virtual Machine Scale Sets, including storage resiliency and scalability options.

The main takeaways from this module are:

- Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets allow for the deployment and management of a group of identical virtual machines, making it easier to build large-scale services.

Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets allow for the deployment and management of a group of identical virtual machines, making it easier to build large-scale services.

- Autoscaling with Virtual Machine Scale Sets helps optimize performance by automatically adjusting the number of instances based on workload demands.

Autoscaling with Virtual Machine Scale Sets helps optimize performance by automatically adjusting the number of instances based on workload demands.

- Availability sets and availability zones are important features in Azure for achieving high availability and fault tolerance for virtual machines.

Availability sets and availability zones are important features in Azure for achieving high availability and fault tolerance for virtual machines.

Learn more with Copilot

Copilot can assist you in configuring Azure infrastructure solutions. Copilot can compare, recommend, explain, and research products and services where you need more information. Open a Microsoft Edge browser and choose Copilot (top right) or navigate to copilot.microsoft.com. Take a few minutes to try these prompts and extend your learning with Copilot.

- How do virtual machine scale sets work with Azure availability zones and sets?

How do virtual machine scale sets work with Azure availability zones and sets?

- What is the difference between manual and autoscaling of Azure virtual machines?

What is the difference between manual and autoscaling of Azure virtual machines?

Learn more with documentation

- Availability options for Azure Virtual Machines . This article provides an overview of the availability options for Azure virtual machines (VMs).

Availability options for Azure Virtual Machines . This article provides an overview of the availability options for Azure virtual machines (VMs).

- Autoscale with Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets . This article reviews when use Virtual Machine Scale Sets.

Autoscale with Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets . This article reviews when use Virtual Machine Scale Sets.

- Create virtual machines in a scale set using Azure portal . This article steps through using Azure portal to create a Virtual Machine Scale Set.

Create virtual machines in a scale set using Azure portal . This article steps through using Azure portal to create a Virtual Machine Scale Set.

Learn more with self-paced training

- Introduction to Azure Virtual Machines (sandbox) . Learn about the decisions you make before creating a virtual machine, the options to create and manage the VM, and the extensions and services you use to manage your VM.

Introduction to Azure Virtual Machines (sandbox) . Learn about the decisions you make before creating a virtual machine, the options to create and manage the VM, and the extensions and services you use to manage your VM.

- Implement scale and high availability with Windows Server VM . You learn how to implement scaling for virtual machine scale sets and load-balanced VMs. You also learn how to implement Azure Site Recovery.

Implement scale and high availability with Windows Server VM . You learn how to implement scaling for virtual machine scale sets and load-balanced VMs. You also learn how to implement Azure Site Recovery.

- Introduction to Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets . Learn about what Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets do, how they work, and when you should use Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets as a solution for your organization.

Introduction to Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets . Learn about what Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets do, how they work, and when you should use Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets as a solution for your organization.

LP 5 M3 - Configure Azure App Service plans

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-app-service-plans/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 5.3.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-app-service-plans/1-introduction

Introduction

Azure Administrators need to be able to scale a web application. Scaling enables an application to remain responsive during periods of high demand. Scaling also helps to save money by reducing the resources required when demand drops.

Suppose you work for a large chain of hotels. You're responsible for maintaining the hotel website. Customers visit the website to make new reservations and view details for their current bookings. At certain times of the year, the volume of website traffic grows because customers are browsing hotels for vacations during national/regional holidays. At other times, traffic declines. These website usage patterns are predictable.

In this module, you learn to implement Azure App Service plans. You learn how different App Service plans provide different pricing and scaling options. You learn how changing the plan affects performance.

The goal of this module is to ensure you can determine the best App Service plan for your application.

Learning objectives

In this module, you learn how to:

- Select an appropriate Azure App Service plan pricing tier.

- Scale an Azure App Service plan.

Skills measured

The content in the module helps you prepare for Exam AZ-104: Microsoft Azure Administrator .

Prerequisites

- Basic knowledge of scaling and performance concepts.

- Familiarity with the Azure portal so you can configure the correct App Service plan.

Unit 5.3.2 - Implement Azure App Service plans

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-app-service-plans/2-implement-azure

Implement Azure App Service plans

An App Service plan defines a set of compute resources for a web application to run. The compute resources are analogous to a server farm in conventional web hosting. One or more applications can be configured to run on the same computing resources (or in the same App Service plan).

Things to know about App Service plans

Let's take a closer look at how to implement and use an App Service plan with your virtual machines.

- When you create an App Service plan in a region, a set of compute resources is created for the plan in the specified region. Any applications that you place into the plan run on the compute resources defined by the plan.

When you create an App Service plan in a region, a set of compute resources is created for the plan in the specified region. Any applications that you place into the plan run on the compute resources defined by the plan.

- Each App Service plan defines these settings: Operating system : Linux or Windows. Region : The region for the App Service plan, such as West US, Central India, North Europe, and so on. Pricing tier : Determines what App Service features you get and how much you pay for the plan. The pricing tiers available to your App Service plan depend on the operating system selected at creation time. Number of VM instances : Determined by your plan. Size of VM instances : Defined by CPU, memory, and remote storage.

Each App Service plan defines these settings:

- Operating system : Linux or Windows.

- Region : The region for the App Service plan, such as West US, Central India, North Europe, and so on.

- Pricing tier : Determines what App Service features you get and how much you pay for the plan. The pricing tiers available to your App Service plan depend on the operating system selected at creation time.

- Number of VM instances : Determined by your plan.

- Size of VM instances : Defined by CPU, memory, and remote storage.

- You can continue to add new applications to an existing plan as long as the plan has enough resources to handle the increasing load.

You can continue to add new applications to an existing plan as long as the plan has enough resources to handle the increasing load.

Things to consider when using App Service plans

Review the following considerations about using Azure App Service plans to run and scale your applications. Think about what conditions might apply to running and scaling the hotel website.

- Consider cost savings . Because you pay for the computing resources that your App Service plan allocates, you can potentially save money by placing multiple applications into the same App Service plan.

Consider cost savings . Because you pay for the computing resources that your App Service plan allocates, you can potentially save money by placing multiple applications into the same App Service plan.

- Consider multiple applications in one plan . Create a single plan to support multiple applications, to make it easier to configure and maintain shared virtual machine instances. Because the applications share the same virtual machine instances, you need to carefully manage your plan resources and capacity.

Consider multiple applications in one plan . Create a single plan to support multiple applications, to make it easier to configure and maintain shared virtual machine instances. Because the applications share the same virtual machine instances, you need to carefully manage your plan resources and capacity.

- Consider plan capacity . Before you add a new application to an existing plan, determine the resource requirements for the new application and identify the remaining capacity of your plan. Important Overloading an App Service plan can potentially cause downtime for new and existing applications.

Consider plan capacity . Before you add a new application to an existing plan, determine the resource requirements for the new application and identify the remaining capacity of your plan.

Important

Overloading an App Service plan can potentially cause downtime for new and existing applications.

- Consider application isolation . Isolate your application into a new App Service plan when: The application is resource-intensive. You want to scale the application independently from the other applications in the existing plan. The application needs resource in a different geographical region.

Consider application isolation . Isolate your application into a new App Service plan when:

- The application is resource-intensive.

- You want to scale the application independently from the other applications in the existing plan.

- The application needs resource in a different geographical region.

Unit 5.3.3 - Determine Azure App Service plan pricing

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-app-service-plans/3-determine-plan-pricing

Determine Azure App Service plan pricing

The pricing tier of an Azure App Service plan determines what App Service features you get and how much you pay for the plan. Pricing tier examples are: Free, Shared, Basic, Standard, Premium, PremiumV2, PremiumV3, Isolated, and IsolatedV2.

How applications run and scale in App Service plans

The Azure App Service plan is the scale unit of App Service applications. Depending on the pricing tier for your Azure App Service plan, your applications run and scale in a different manner. If your plan is configured to run five virtual machine instances, then all applications in the plan run on all five instances. If your plan is configured for autoscaling, then all applications in the plan are scaled out together based on the autoscale settings.

The pricing tiers are grouped into three categories:

- Shared compute : Free and Shared, the two base tiers, run an app on the same Azure VM as other App Service apps, including apps of other customers. These tiers allocate CPU quotas to each app that runs on the shared resources, and the resources can't scale out. These tiers are intended to be used only for development and testing purposes.

- Free and Shared, the two base tiers, run an app on the same Azure VM as other App Service apps, including apps of other customers.

- These tiers allocate CPU quotas to each app that runs on the shared resources, and the resources can't scale out.

- These tiers are intended to be used only for development and testing purposes.

- Dedicated compute : The Basic, Standard, Premium, PremiumV2, and PremiumV3 tiers run apps on dedicated Azure VMs. Only apps in the same App Service plan have the same compute resources. The higher the tier, the more VM instances that are available to you for scale-out.

- The Basic, Standard, Premium, PremiumV2, and PremiumV3 tiers run apps on dedicated Azure VMs.

- Only apps in the same App Service plan have the same compute resources. The higher the tier, the more VM instances that are available to you for scale-out.

- Isolated : The Isolated and IsolatedV2 tiers run dedicated Azure VMs on dedicated Azure virtual networks. This tier provides network isolation on top of compute isolation to your apps. This tier provides the maximum scale-out capabilities.

- The Isolated and IsolatedV2 tiers run dedicated Azure VMs on dedicated Azure virtual networks.

- This tier provides network isolation on top of compute isolation to your apps.

- This tier provides the maximum scale-out capabilities.

Here's a sample of different plan details .

Feature

Free F1

Basic B1

Standard S1

Premium P1V3

Isolated V2

Usage

Development, Testing

Production workloads

Enhanced scale, performance

Network-isolated workloads

Staging slots

N/A

5

20

Auto scale

N/A

Manual

Rules

Rules, Elastic

Rules

Scale instances

N/A

3

10

30

200

Daily backups

N/A

10

50

Free and Shared

The Free and Shared service plans are base tiers that run on the same Azure virtual machines as other applications. Some applications might belong to other customers. These tiers are intended to be used for development and testing purposes only. No SLA is provided for the Free and Shared service plans. Free and Shared plans are metered on a per application basis.

Basic

The Basic service plan is designed for applications that have lower traffic requirements, and don't need advanced auto scale and traffic management features. Pricing is based on the size and number of instances you run. Built-in network load-balancing support automatically distributes traffic across instances. The Basic service plan with Linux runtime environments supports Web App for Containers.

Standard

The Standard service plan is designed for running production workloads. Pricing is based on the size and number of instances you run. Built-in network load-balancing support automatically distributes traffic across instances. The Standard plan includes auto scale that can automatically adjust the number of virtual machine instances running to match your traffic needs. The Standard service plan with Linux runtime environments supports Web App for Containers.

Premium

The Premium service plan is designed for production apps that need higher performance and scale. PremiumV3 is the current Premium tier, offering Dav4 and Ddv4-series virtual machines and SSD storage. PremiumV3 supports standard compute SKUs and memory-optimized SKUs for high-memory workloads. PremiumV3 supports both rule-based autoscaling and automatic scaling. PremiumV3 is recommended for new deployments.

Isolated

The Isolated service plan supports mission-critical workloads needing network isolation. IsolatedV2 is the preferred tier offering newer hardware, up to 200 instances, private environments, and enhanced security. IsolatedV2 is recommended for new workloads due to better performance and simpler pricing.

Task to be done: Select an App Service plan

You can view the available App Service plans in the Azure portal. You can make your choice based on hardware or feature requirements. Hardware considerations include CPU, memory, and scaling instances. Feature considerations include backups, staging slots, and zone redundancy.

Tip

When selecting a service plan, consider both hardware and feature requirements.

- In the Azure portal search for and select App Service plans .

- Create a new App Service plan.

- Select Explore pricing plans to view the available plans.

Unit 5.3.4 - Scale up and scale out Azure App Service

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-app-service-plans/4-scale-up-scale-out

Scale up and scale out Azure App Service

There are two methods for scaling your Azure App Service plan and applications: scale up and scale out . You can scale your applications manually or automatically, which is referred to as autoscale .

Watch the following video about how to implement automatic scaling for your Azure App Service plan and applications.

Things to know about Azure App Service scaling

Let's examine the details of scaling for your Azure App Service plan and App Service applications.

- The scale up method increases the amount of CPU, memory, and disk space. Scaling up gives you extra features like dedicated virtual machines, custom domains and certificates, staging slots, autoscaling, and more. You scale up by changing the pricing tier of the Azure App Service plan where your application is placed.

The scale up method increases the amount of CPU, memory, and disk space. Scaling up gives you extra features like dedicated virtual machines, custom domains and certificates, staging slots, autoscaling, and more. You scale up by changing the pricing tier of the Azure App Service plan where your application is placed.

- The scale-out method increases the number of virtual machine instances that run your application. You can scale out to the maximum number of instances for your pricing tier. Take advantage of App Service Environments in the Isolated tier to further increase your scale-out count to 100 instances. The scale instance count can be configured manually or automatically (autoscale).

The scale-out method increases the number of virtual machine instances that run your application. You can scale out to the maximum number of instances for your pricing tier. Take advantage of App Service Environments in the Isolated tier to further increase your scale-out count to 100 instances. The scale instance count can be configured manually or automatically (autoscale).

- With autoscale, you can automatically increase the scale instance count for the scale-out method. Autoscale is based on predefined rules and schedules.

With autoscale, you can automatically increase the scale instance count for the scale-out method. Autoscale is based on predefined rules and schedules.

- Your App Service plan can be scaled up and down at any time by changing the pricing tier of the plan.

Your App Service plan can be scaled up and down at any time by changing the pricing tier of the plan.

Things to consider when using Azure App Service scaling

Review the following benefits of implementing scaling for your App Service plan and applications. Think about the scaling advantages for your hotel website.

- Consider manually adjusting plan tiers . Start your plan at a lower pricing tier and scale up as needed to acquire more App Service features. Scale down when features are no longer needed, and control your overall costs. Consider a scenario where you start testing your web app by using the Azure App Service Free tier, where you pay nothing to use the service. After a while, you decide to add a custom DNS name to your web app, so you scale your plan up to the Shared tier. Next, you discover you need to create an SSL binding, so you scale your plan up to the Basic tier. Later, you determine a need for staging environments, so you scale up to the Standard tier. When you need more cores, memory, or storage, you can scale up to a bigger virtual machine size in the same tier. The same scaling process works in reverse. If you decide you no longer need capabilities or features of a higher tier, scale your plan down to a lower tier and save money.

Consider manually adjusting plan tiers . Start your plan at a lower pricing tier and scale up as needed to acquire more App Service features. Scale down when features are no longer needed, and control your overall costs.

Consider a scenario where you start testing your web app by using the Azure App Service Free tier, where you pay nothing to use the service. After a while, you decide to add a custom DNS name to your web app, so you scale your plan up to the Shared tier. Next, you discover you need to create an SSL binding, so you scale your plan up to the Basic tier. Later, you determine a need for staging environments, so you scale up to the Standard tier. When you need more cores, memory, or storage, you can scale up to a bigger virtual machine size in the same tier.

The same scaling process works in reverse. If you decide you no longer need capabilities or features of a higher tier, scale your plan down to a lower tier and save money.

- Consider autoscale to support users and reduce costs . Keep serving your users when your application is experiencing high throughput. Implement autoscale to control how many features and support are offered at a given time based on your preference settings and rule conditions. Autoscale helps you save money when the load on your application decreases by automatically reducing your subscribed features.

Consider autoscale to support users and reduce costs . Keep serving your users when your application is experiencing high throughput. Implement autoscale to control how many features and support are offered at a given time based on your preference settings and rule conditions. Autoscale helps you save money when the load on your application decreases by automatically reducing your subscribed features.

- Consider no redeployment . When you change your scale settings, you don't need to change your code or redeploy your applications. Changing your plan scale settings takes only seconds to apply. Your changes affect all applications in your App Service plan.

Consider no redeployment . When you change your scale settings, you don't need to change your code or redeploy your applications. Changing your plan scale settings takes only seconds to apply. Your changes affect all applications in your App Service plan.

- Consider scaling for other Azure services . If your App Service application depends on other Azure services, such as Azure SQL Database or Azure Storage, you can scale these resources separately. The App Service Plan doesn't manage these resources.

Consider scaling for other Azure services . If your App Service application depends on other Azure services, such as Azure SQL Database or Azure Storage, you can scale these resources separately. The App Service Plan doesn't manage these resources.

Unit 5.3.5 - Configure Azure App Service autoscale

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-app-service-plans/5-plan-scaling

Configure Azure App Service autoscale

The autoscale process allows you to have the right amount of resources running to handle the load on your application. You can add resources to support increases in load and save money by removing idle resources.

Things to know about autoscale

Let's take a closer look at how to use autoscale for your Azure App Service plan and applications.

- To use autoscale, you specify the minimum, and maximum number of instances to run by using a set of rules and conditions.

To use autoscale, you specify the minimum, and maximum number of instances to run by using a set of rules and conditions.

- When your application runs under autoscale conditions, the number of virtual machine instances are automatically adjusted based on your rules. When rule conditions are met, one or more autoscale actions are triggered.

When your application runs under autoscale conditions, the number of virtual machine instances are automatically adjusted based on your rules. When rule conditions are met, one or more autoscale actions are triggered.

- An autoscale setting is used by the autoscale engine to determine whether to scale out or in. Autoscale settings are grouped into profiles.

An autoscale setting is used by the autoscale engine to determine whether to scale out or in. Autoscale settings are grouped into profiles.

- Autoscale rules include a trigger and a scale action (in or out). The trigger can be metric-based or time-based. Metric-based rules measure application load and add or remove virtual machines based on the load, such as "do this action when CPU usage is above 50%." Example metrics include CPU time, Average response time, and Requests. Time-based rules (or, schedule-based) allow you to scale when you see time patterns in your load and want to scale before a possible load increase or decrease occurs. An example is "trigger a webhook every 8:00 AM on Saturday in a given time zone."

Autoscale rules include a trigger and a scale action (in or out). The trigger can be metric-based or time-based.

- Metric-based rules measure application load and add or remove virtual machines based on the load, such as "do this action when CPU usage is above 50%." Example metrics include CPU time, Average response time, and Requests.

Metric-based rules measure application load and add or remove virtual machines based on the load, such as "do this action when CPU usage is above 50%." Example metrics include CPU time, Average response time, and Requests.

- Time-based rules (or, schedule-based) allow you to scale when you see time patterns in your load and want to scale before a possible load increase or decrease occurs. An example is "trigger a webhook every 8:00 AM on Saturday in a given time zone."

Time-based rules (or, schedule-based) allow you to scale when you see time patterns in your load and want to scale before a possible load increase or decrease occurs. An example is "trigger a webhook every 8:00 AM on Saturday in a given time zone."

- The autoscale engine uses notification settings. A notification setting defines what notifications should occur when an autoscale event occurs based on satisfying the criteria of an autoscale setting profile. Autoscale can notify one or more email addresses or make calls to one or more webhooks.

The autoscale engine uses notification settings.

A notification setting defines what notifications should occur when an autoscale event occurs based on satisfying the criteria of an autoscale setting profile. Autoscale can notify one or more email addresses or make calls to one or more webhooks.

Things to consider when configuring autoscale

There are several considerations to keep in mind when you configure autoscale for your Azure App Service plan and applications.

- Minimum instance count . Set a minimum instance count to make sure your application is always running even when there's no load.

Minimum instance count . Set a minimum instance count to make sure your application is always running even when there's no load.

- Maximum instance count . Set a maximum instance count to limit your total possible hourly cost.

Maximum instance count . Set a maximum instance count to limit your total possible hourly cost.

- Adequate scale margin . Make sure your maximum and minimum instance count values are different, and set an adequate margin between the two values. You can automatically scale between the minimum and maximum by using rules you create.

Adequate scale margin . Make sure your maximum and minimum instance count values are different, and set an adequate margin between the two values. You can automatically scale between the minimum and maximum by using rules you create.

- Scale rule combinations . Always use a scale-out and scale-in rule combination that performs an increase and decrease. If you don't set a scale-out rule, your application might fail, or performance might degrade under increased loads. If you don't set a scale-in rule, you can experience unnecessary and extensive costs when the load decreases.

Scale rule combinations . Always use a scale-out and scale-in rule combination that performs an increase and decrease. If you don't set a scale-out rule, your application might fail, or performance might degrade under increased loads. If you don't set a scale-in rule, you can experience unnecessary and extensive costs when the load decreases.

- Metric statistics . Carefully choose the appropriate statistic for your diagnostic metrics, including Average, Minimum, Maximum, and Total.

Metric statistics . Carefully choose the appropriate statistic for your diagnostic metrics, including Average, Minimum, Maximum, and Total.

- Default instance count . Always select a safe default instance count. The default instance count is important because autoscale scales your service to the count you specify when metrics aren't available.

Default instance count . Always select a safe default instance count. The default instance count is important because autoscale scales your service to the count you specify when metrics aren't available.

- Notifications . Always configure autoscale notifications. It's important to maintain awareness of how your application is performing as the load changes.

Notifications . Always configure autoscale notifications. It's important to maintain awareness of how your application is performing as the load changes.

Things to consider when configuring automatic scaling

In addition to rule-based autoscale, Azure App Service offers Automatic scaling (also called Elastic scaling) for PremiumV2 and PremiumV3 tiers. This is a separate scaling feature that works differently from the autoscale rules.

- HTTP traffic-based. Automatic scaling responds directly to incoming HTTP requests without requiring you to configure scaling rules.

HTTP traffic-based. Automatic scaling responds directly to incoming HTTP requests without requiring you to configure scaling rules.

- Platform-managed. Azure automatically manages the scaling decisions based on traffic patterns, eliminating the need for rule configuration.

Platform-managed. Azure automatically manages the scaling decisions based on traffic patterns, eliminating the need for rule configuration.

- Always-ready instances. Maintains warmed instances to handle traffic spikes immediately.

Always-ready instances. Maintains warmed instances to handle traffic spikes immediately.

- Tier availability. Available only on PremiumV2 and PremiumV3 tiers.

Tier availability. Available only on PremiumV2 and PremiumV3 tiers.

Choose between Autoscale and Automatic scaling

- Use rule-based Autoscale. You need custom scaling logic, want to scale based on multiple metrics, or need schedule-based scaling.

Use rule-based Autoscale. You need custom scaling logic, want to scale based on multiple metrics, or need schedule-based scaling.

- Use Automatic scaling. You want less management, can't predict load patterns, or need fast response to traffic changes without rule configuration.

Use Automatic scaling. You want less management, can't predict load patterns, or need fast response to traffic changes without rule configuration.

Unit 5.3.6 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-app-service-plans/6-knowledge-check

Module assessment

You're developing a strategy to implement Azure App Service plans to enable scaling requirements for the hotel website. Various teams in your organization submit requests and questions for your consideration.

- The Admin team requests information about scaling options. They prefer an option that can increase CPU and disk space rather than having to add more virtual machines.

The Admin team requests information about scaling options. They prefer an option that can increase CPU and disk space rather than having to add more virtual machines.

- The Production team manages a web app that requires scaling to 10 staging slots.

The Production team manages a web app that requires scaling to 10 staging slots.

- In your website configuration, you need a rule to trigger an event at 8:00 AM on Saturdays.

In your website configuration, you need a rule to trigger an event at 8:00 AM on Saturdays.

Answer the following questions

Choose the best response for each question.

Unit 5.3.7 - Summary and resources

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-app-service-plans/7-summary-resources

Summary and resources

In this module, you learned about Azure App Service plans and how they're used to define the compute resources for running applications in Azure App Service. These plans can be configured with a specific region, number of virtual machine instances, and size of virtual machine instances. The pricing tier of the App Service plan determines the features and cost. Pricing tiers include Free and Shared plans for development and testing purposes. Pricing tiers also include Isolated plans for mission-critical workloads.

You learned about scaling in Azure App Service. Scale up involves increasing the CPU, memory, and disk space by changing the pricing tier. Scale out increases the number of virtual machine instances running the application. Autoscaling allows you to automatically adjust the number of resources based on the load on your application. Autoscale can be configured with metric-based or time-based rules.

The main takeaways from this module are:

- Azure App Service plans are used to define the compute resources for running web applications in Azure App Service.

- The pricing tier of the App Service plan determines the features and cost, with options ranging from Free and Shared plans to Isolated plans.

- Scaling in Azure App Service can be done through scale up (changing the pricing tier) or scale out (increasing the number of virtual machine instances).

- Autoscaling allows for automatic adjustment of resources based on application load, with metric-based and time-based rules.

Learn more with Copilot

Copilot can assist you in configuring Azure infrastructure solutions. Copilot can compare, recommend, explain, and research products and services where you need more information. Open a Microsoft Edge browser and choose Copilot (top right) or navigate to copilot.microsoft.com. Take a few minutes to try these prompts and extend your learning with Copilot.

- In Microsoft Azure, what are app service pricing plans? Provide examples of when to use each plan.

In Microsoft Azure, what are app service pricing plans? Provide examples of when to use each plan.

- In Microsoft Azure, what does scale in and scale out mean? How do I determine when to scale an application?

In Microsoft Azure, what does scale in and scale out mean? How do I determine when to scale an application?

Learn more with documentation

- Azure App Service plans . This article provides an overview of App Service plans.

Azure App Service plans . This article provides an overview of App Service plans.

- Manage an App Service plan in Azure . This guide shows how to create and manage an App Service plan.

Manage an App Service plan in Azure . This guide shows how to create and manage an App Service plan.

- Scale up an app in Azure App Service . This article shows you how to scale your app in Azure App Service.

Scale up an app in Azure App Service . This article shows you how to scale your app in Azure App Service.

Learn more with self-paced training

- Scale apps in Azure App Service . Learn how autoscale operates in App Service. Learn to identify autoscale factors, enable autoscale, and create autoscale conditions.

LP 5 M4 - Configure Azure App Service

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-app-services/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 5.4.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-app-services/1-introduction

Introduction

Azure Administrators are interested in solutions that make it easier to deploy and manage their web, mobile, and API applications. Azure Administrators are interested in solutions that are AI-ready.

Your company provides consumer research, and your team manages the on-premises servers. The servers you administer run the entire company infrastructure from web servers to databases. The hardware is aging and starting to struggle to keep up with some of the new data analysis applications. Rather than upgrade the hardware, the company decided to deploy Azure App Service.

In this module, you learn how to configure and manage Azure App Service. You learn about configuration settings, deployment slots, and custom domain names. You learn about application backup, recovery, and monitoring.

The goal of this module is to provide you with the knowledge and skills to effectively use Azure App Services.

Learning objectives

In this module, you learn how to:

- Identify features and usage cases for Azure App Service.

- Create an app with App Service.

- Configure deployment settings, specifically deployment slots.

- Secure your App Service app.

- Configure custom domain names.

- Back up and restore your App Service app.

- Configure Azure Application Insights.

Skills measured

The content in the module helps you prepare for Exam AZ-104: Microsoft Azure Administrator .

Prerequisites

- Working knowledge of the Azure portal, so you can configure the service.

Working knowledge of the Azure portal, so you can configure the service.

- Familiarity with cloud-based services, specifically web hosting services.

Familiarity with cloud-based services, specifically web hosting services.

Unit 5.4.2 - Implement Azure App Service

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-app-services/2-implement

Implement Azure App Service

Azure App Service brings together everything you need to create websites, mobile backends, and web APIs for any platform or device. Applications run and scale with ease in both Windows and Linux-based environments.

App Service provides Quickstarts for programming languages. These languages include: ASP.NET, Java, Node.js, Python, and PHP.

App Service benefits

There are many advantages to using App Service to develop and deploy your web, mobile, and API apps. Review the following table and think about what features can help you host your App Service instances.

Benefit

Description

Multiple languages and frameworks

App Service has first-class support for ASP.NET, Java, Node.js, PHP, and Python. You can also run PowerShell and other scripts or executables as background services.

DevOps optimization

App Service supports continuous integration and deployment with Azure DevOps, GitHub, BitBucket, Docker Hub, and Azure Container Registry. You can promote updates through test and staging environments. Manage your apps in App Service by using Azure PowerShell or the cross-platform command-line interface (CLI).

Global scale with high availability

App Service helps you scale up or out manually or automatically. You can host your apps anywhere within the Microsoft global datacenter infrastructure, and the App Service SLA offers high availability.

Security and compliance

App Service is ISO, SOC, and PCI compliant. You can authenticate users with Microsoft Entra ID or with social logins via Google, Facebook, X, or Microsoft. Create IP address restrictions and manage service identities.

Application templates

Choose from an extensive list of application templates in Azure Marketplace, such as WordPress, Joomla, and Drupal.

Visual Studio integration

App Service offers dedicated tools in Visual Studio to help streamline the work of creating, deploying, and debugging.

API and mobile features

App Service provides turn-key CORS support for RESTful API scenarios. You can simplify your mobile app scenarios by enabling authentication, offline data sync, push notifications, and more.

Unit 5.4.3 - Create an app with App Service

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-app-services/3-create-app-service

Create an app with App Service

You can use the Web Apps, Mobile Apps, or API Apps features of Azure App Service, and create your own apps in the Azure portal.

Things to know about configuration settings

Let's examine some of the basic configuration settings you need to create an app with App Service.

- Name : The name for your app must be unique. The name identifies and locates your app in Azure. An example name is webappces1.azurewebsites.net . You can map a custom domain name, if you prefer to use that option instead.

Name : The name for your app must be unique. The name identifies and locates your app in Azure. An example name is webappces1.azurewebsites.net . You can map a custom domain name, if you prefer to use that option instead.

webappces1.azurewebsites.net

- Publish : App Service hosts (publishes) your app as code or as a Docker Container.

Publish : App Service hosts (publishes) your app as code or as a Docker Container.

- Runtime stack : App Service uses a software stack to run your app, including the language and SDK versions. For Linux apps and custom container apps, you can set an optional start-up command or file. Your choices for the stack include .NET Core, .NET Framework, Node.js, PHP, and Python. Various versions of each product are available for Linux and Windows.

Runtime stack : App Service uses a software stack to run your app, including the language and SDK versions. For Linux apps and custom container apps, you can set an optional start-up command or file. Your choices for the stack include .NET Core, .NET Framework, Node.js, PHP, and Python. Various versions of each product are available for Linux and Windows.

- Operating system : The operating system for your app runtime stack can be Linux or Windows.

Operating system : The operating system for your app runtime stack can be Linux or Windows.

- Region : The region location that you choose for your app affects the App Service plans that are available.

Region : The region location that you choose for your app affects the App Service plans that are available.

- Pricing plans : Your app needs to be associated with an Azure App Service plan to establish available resources, features, and capacity. You can choose from pricing tiers that are available for the region location you selected.

Pricing plans : Your app needs to be associated with an Azure App Service plan to establish available resources, features, and capacity. You can choose from pricing tiers that are available for the region location you selected.

Post-creation settings

After your app is created, other Configuration settings become available in the Azure portal, including app deployment options and path mapping.

Some of the extra configuration settings can be included in the developer's code, while others can be configured in your app. Here are a few of the extra application settings.

- Always On : You can keep your app loaded even when there's no traffic. This setting is required for continuous WebJobs or for WebJobs that are triggered by using a CRON expression.

Always On : You can keep your app loaded even when there's no traffic. This setting is required for continuous WebJobs or for WebJobs that are triggered by using a CRON expression.

- Session affinity : In a multi-instance deployment, you can ensure your app client is routed to the same instance for the life of the session.

Session affinity : In a multi-instance deployment, you can ensure your app client is routed to the same instance for the life of the session.

- HTTPS Only : When enabled, all HTTP traffic is redirected to HTTPS.

HTTPS Only : When enabled, all HTTP traffic is redirected to HTTPS.

Tip

Consider practicing on your own with the Exercise - Create a web app in the Azure portal . This exercise provides a sandbox.

Unit 5.4.4 - Explore continuous integration and deployment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-app-services/4-explore-continuous-integration-deployment

Explore continuous integration and deployment

The Azure portal provides out-of-the-box continuous integration and deployment with Azure DevOps services, GitHub, Bitbucket, FTP, or a local Git repository on your development machine. You can connect your web app with any of the above sources and App Service handles the rest for you. App Service autosynchronizes your code and any future changes to the code into your web app. With Azure DevOps services, you can also define your own build and release process. Compile your source code, run tests, and build and deploy the release into your web app every time you commit the code. All of the operations happen implicitly without any need for human administration.

Things to know about continuous and manual deployment

When you create your web app with App Service, you can choose continuous or manual deployment. As you review these options, consider which deployment method to implement for your App Service apps. These options are located in the Deployment Center.

Continuous deployment (CI/CD) is a process used to push out new features and bug fixes in a fast and repetitive pattern with minimal impact on end users. Azure supports automated deployment directly from several sources:

- GitHub : Azure supports automated deployment directly from GitHub. Azure supports automated deployment directly from GitHub using two build providers. When you connect your GitHub repository to Azure, you can choose between GitHub Actions (default) and App Service Build Service .

GitHub : Azure supports automated deployment directly from GitHub. Azure supports automated deployment directly from GitHub using two build providers. When you connect your GitHub repository to Azure, you can choose between GitHub Actions (default) and App Service Build Service .

- Bitbucket : With its similarities to GitHub, you can configure an automated deployment with Bitbucket.

Bitbucket : With its similarities to GitHub, you can configure an automated deployment with Bitbucket.

- Local Git : The App Service Web Apps feature offers a local URL that you can add as a repository.

Local Git : The App Service Web Apps feature offers a local URL that you can add as a repository.

- Azure Repos : Azure Repos is a set of version control tools that you can use to manage your code. Whether your software project is large or small, using version control as soon as possible is a good idea.

Azure Repos : Azure Repos is a set of version control tools that you can use to manage your code. Whether your software project is large or small, using version control as soon as possible is a good idea.

Manual deployment enables you to manually push your code to Azure.

- Remote Git : The App Service Web Apps feature offers a Git URL that you can add as a remote repository. Pushing to the remote repository deploys your app.

Unit 5.4.5 - Create deployment slots

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-app-services/5-create-deployment-slots

Create deployment slots

When you deploy your web app, web app on Linux, mobile backend, or API app to Azure App Service, you can use a separate deployment slot instead of the default production slot.

Things to know about deployment slots

Let's take a closer look at the characteristics of deployment slots.

- Deployment slots are live apps that have their own hostnames.

Deployment slots are live apps that have their own hostnames.

- Deployment slots are available in the Standard, Premium, and Isolated v2 App Service pricing tiers. Your app needs to be running in one of these tiers to use deployment slots.

Deployment slots are available in the Standard, Premium, and Isolated v2 App Service pricing tiers. Your app needs to be running in one of these tiers to use deployment slots.

- The Standard, Premium, and Isolated tiers offer different numbers of deployment slots.

The Standard, Premium, and Isolated tiers offer different numbers of deployment slots.

- App content and configuration elements can be swapped between two deployment slots, including the production slot.

App content and configuration elements can be swapped between two deployment slots, including the production slot.

Things to consider when using deployment slots

There are several advantages to using deployment slots with your App Service app. Review the following benefits and think about how they can support your App Service implementation.

- Consider validation . You can validate changes to your app in a staging deployment slot before swapping the app changes with the content in the production slot.

Consider validation . You can validate changes to your app in a staging deployment slot before swapping the app changes with the content in the production slot.

- Consider reductions in downtime . Deploying an app to a slot first and swapping it into production ensures that all instances are ready. This option eliminates downtime when you deploy your app. The traffic redirection is seamless, and no requests are dropped because of swap operations. The entire workflow can be automated by configuring Auto swap when preswap validation isn't needed.

Consider reductions in downtime . Deploying an app to a slot first and swapping it into production ensures that all instances are ready. This option eliminates downtime when you deploy your app. The traffic redirection is seamless, and no requests are dropped because of swap operations. The entire workflow can be automated by configuring Auto swap when preswap validation isn't needed.

- Consider restoring to last known good site . After a swap, the slot with the previously staged app now has the previous production app. If the changes swapped into the production slot aren't as you expected, you can perform the same swap immediately to return to your "last known good site."

Consider restoring to last known good site . After a swap, the slot with the previously staged app now has the previous production app. If the changes swapped into the production slot aren't as you expected, you can perform the same swap immediately to return to your "last known good site."

- Consider Auto swap . Auto swap streamlines Azure Pipeline scenarios where you want to deploy your app continuously with zero cold starts and zero downtime for app customers. When Auto swap is enabled from a slot into production, every time you push your code changes to that slot, App Service automatically swaps the app into production after it's warmed up in the source slot.

Consider Auto swap . Auto swap streamlines Azure Pipeline scenarios where you want to deploy your app continuously with zero cold starts and zero downtime for app customers. When Auto swap is enabled from a slot into production, every time you push your code changes to that slot, App Service automatically swaps the app into production after it's warmed up in the source slot.

Unit 5.4.6 - Add deployment slots

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-app-services/6-add-deployment-slots

Add deployment slots

Deployment slots are configured in the Azure portal. You can swap your app content and configuration elements between deployment slots, including the production slot.

Things to know about creating deployment slots

Let's review some details about how deployment slots are configured.

- New deployment slots can be empty or cloned.

New deployment slots can be empty or cloned.

- Deployment slot settings fall into three categories: Slot-specific app settings and connection strings (if applicable). Continuous deployment settings (when enabled). Azure App Service authentication settings (when enabled).

Deployment slot settings fall into three categories:

- Slot-specific app settings and connection strings (if applicable).

- Continuous deployment settings (when enabled).

- Azure App Service authentication settings (when enabled).

- When you clone a configuration from another deployment slot, the cloned configuration is editable. Some configuration elements follow the content across the swap. Other slot-specific configuration elements stay in the source slot after the swap.

When you clone a configuration from another deployment slot, the cloned configuration is editable. Some configuration elements follow the content across the swap. Other slot-specific configuration elements stay in the source slot after the swap.

Swapped settings versus slot-specific settings

The following table lists settings that are swapped between deployment slots. The table also lists settings that remain in the source slot (slot-specific). As you review these settings, consider which features are required for your App Service apps. Read more about which settings are swapped .

Swapped settings

Slot-specific settings

Language stack and version, 32/64-bit App settings * Connection strings * Mounted storage accounts* Public certificates WebJobs content Hybrid connections ** Service endpoints ** Azure Content Delivery Network ** Path mapping

Custom domain names Nonpublic certificates and TLS/SSL settings Scale settings Always On IP restrictions WebJobs schedulers Diagnostic settings Cross-origin resource sharing (CORS) Virtual network integration Managed identities

* Setting can be configured to be slot-specific.

** Feature isn't currently available.

Unit 5.4.7 - Secure your App Service app

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-app-services/7-secure-app-service

Secure your App Service app

Azure App Service provides built-in authentication and authorization support. You can sign in users and access data by writing minimal or no code in your web app, API, and mobile backend, and also your Azure Functions apps.

Secure authentication and authorization require deep understanding of security, including federation, encryption, JSON web tokens (JWT) management, grant types, and so on. App Service provides these utilities so you can spend more time and energy on providing business value to your customer.

Note

You aren't required to use Azure App Service for authentication and authorization. Many web frameworks are bundled with security features, and you can use your preferred service.

Things to know about app security with App Service

Let's take a closer look at how App Service helps you provide security for your app.

- The authentication and authorization security module in Azure App Service runs in the same environment as your application code, yet separately.

The authentication and authorization security module in Azure App Service runs in the same environment as your application code, yet separately.

- The security module is configured by using app settings. No SDKs, specific languages, or changes to your application code are required.

The security module is configured by using app settings. No SDKs, specific languages, or changes to your application code are required.

- The security module handles several tasks for your app: Authenticate users with the specified provider Validate, store, and refresh tokens Manage the authenticated session Inject identity information into request headers

The security module handles several tasks for your app:

- Authenticate users with the specified provider

- Validate, store, and refresh tokens

- Manage the authenticated session

- Inject identity information into request headers

Things to consider when using App Service for app security

You configure authentication and authorization security in App Service by selecting features In the Azure portal. Review the following options and think about what security can benefit your App Service apps implementation.

- Allow Anonymous requests (no action) . Defer authorization of unauthenticated traffic to your application code. For authenticated requests, App Service also passes along authentication information in the HTTP headers. This feature provides more flexibility for handling anonymous requests. With this feature, you can present multiple sign-in providers to your users.

Allow Anonymous requests (no action) . Defer authorization of unauthenticated traffic to your application code. For authenticated requests, App Service also passes along authentication information in the HTTP headers. This feature provides more flexibility for handling anonymous requests. With this feature, you can present multiple sign-in providers to your users.

- Allow only authenticated requests . Redirect all anonymous requests to /.auth/login/<provider> for the provider you choose. The feature is equivalent to Log in with <provider> . If the anonymous request comes from a native mobile app, the returned response is an HTTP 401 Unauthorized message. With this feature, you don't need to write any authentication code in your app. Important This feature restricts access to all calls to your app. Restricting access to all calls might not be desirable if your app requires a public home page, as is the case for many single-page apps.

Allow only authenticated requests . Redirect all anonymous requests to /.auth/login/<provider> for the provider you choose. The feature is equivalent to Log in with <provider> . If the anonymous request comes from a native mobile app, the returned response is an HTTP 401 Unauthorized message. With this feature, you don't need to write any authentication code in your app.

/.auth/login/<provider>

HTTP 401 Unauthorized

Important

This feature restricts access to all calls to your app. Restricting access to all calls might not be desirable if your app requires a public home page, as is the case for many single-page apps.

- Logging and tracing . View authentication and authorization traces directly in your log files. If you see an authentication error that you didn’t expect, you can conveniently find all the details by looking in your existing application logs. If you enable failed request tracing, you can see exactly how the security module participated in a failed request. In the trace logs, look for references to a module named EasyAuthModule_32/64 .

Logging and tracing . View authentication and authorization traces directly in your log files. If you see an authentication error that you didn’t expect, you can conveniently find all the details by looking in your existing application logs. If you enable failed request tracing, you can see exactly how the security module participated in a failed request. In the trace logs, look for references to a module named EasyAuthModule_32/64 .

EasyAuthModule_32/64

Unit 5.4.8 - Create custom domain names

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-app-services/8-create-custom-domain-names

Create custom domain names

When you create a web app, Azure assigns the app to a subdomain of azurewebsites.net . Suppose your web app is named contoso . Azure creates a URL for your web app as contoso.azurewebsites.net . Azure also assigns a virtual IP address for your app. For a production web app, you might want users to see a custom domain name.

azurewebsites.net

contoso

contoso.azurewebsites.net

What is a custom domain?

A domain name is the address people type into a web browser to reach your website. A custom domain is a domain name that you own and configure to point to your Azure-hosted app, replacing the default Azure domain.

For example:

- Default Azure domain: myapp-00000.westus.azurewebsites.net

myapp-00000.westus.azurewebsites.net

- Custom domain: www.contoso.com

www.contoso.com

Using a custom domain allows you to:

- Establish a branded, user-friendly web address.

- Improve trust and credibility with customers.

- Manage and secure traffic to your application.

Steps to configure a custom domain name for your app

Creating a custom domain name requires providers, security, and naming information.

There are three steps to create a custom domain name.

- Reserve your domain name . The easiest way to set up a custom domain is to buy one directly in the Azure portal. (This name isn't the Azure assigned name of \*.azurewebsites.net .) The registration process enables you to manage your web app's domain name directly in the Azure portal instead of going to a third-party site. Configuring the domain name in your web app is also a simple process in the Azure portal.

Reserve your domain name . The easiest way to set up a custom domain is to buy one directly in the Azure portal. (This name isn't the Azure assigned name of \*.azurewebsites.net .) The registration process enables you to manage your web app's domain name directly in the Azure portal instead of going to a third-party site. Configuring the domain name in your web app is also a simple process in the Azure portal.

\*.azurewebsites.net

- Create DNS records to map the domain to your Azure web app . The Domain Name System (DNS) uses data records to map domain names to IP addresses. There are several types of DNS records. For web apps, you create either an A (Address) record or a CNAME (Canonical Name) record. An A record maps a domain name to an IP address. A CNAME record maps a domain name to another domain name. DNS uses the second name to look up the address. Users still see the first domain name in their browser. As an example, you could map contoso.com to your webapp.azurewebsites.net URL. If the IP address changes, a CNAME entry is still valid, whereas an A record must be updated. Some domain registrars don't allow CNAME records for the root domain or for wildcard domains. In such cases, you must use an A record.

Create DNS records to map the domain to your Azure web app . The Domain Name System (DNS) uses data records to map domain names to IP addresses. There are several types of DNS records.

- For web apps, you create either an A (Address) record or a CNAME (Canonical Name) record. An A record maps a domain name to an IP address. A CNAME record maps a domain name to another domain name. DNS uses the second name to look up the address. Users still see the first domain name in their browser. As an example, you could map contoso.com to your webapp.azurewebsites.net URL.

For web apps, you create either an A (Address) record or a CNAME (Canonical Name) record.

A

CNAME

- An A record maps a domain name to an IP address.

A

- A CNAME record maps a domain name to another domain name. DNS uses the second name to look up the address. Users still see the first domain name in their browser. As an example, you could map contoso.com to your webapp.azurewebsites.net URL.

CNAME

contoso.com

webapp.azurewebsites.net

- If the IP address changes, a CNAME entry is still valid, whereas an A record must be updated.

If the IP address changes, a CNAME entry is still valid, whereas an A record must be updated.

CNAME

A

- Some domain registrars don't allow CNAME records for the root domain or for wildcard domains. In such cases, you must use an A record.

Some domain registrars don't allow CNAME records for the root domain or for wildcard domains. In such cases, you must use an A record.

CNAME

A

- Enable the custom domain . After you have your domain and create your DNS record, use the Azure portal to validate your custom domain and add it to your web app. Be sure to test your domain before publishing.

Enable the custom domain . After you have your domain and create your DNS record, use the Azure portal to validate your custom domain and add it to your web app. Be sure to test your domain before publishing.

Important

App Service offers free managed TLS certificates. Certificates auto-renew 30 days before expiry. In the Azure portal, go to Custom domains → Add binding → App Service Managed Certificate .

Unit 5.4.9 - Back up and restore your App Service app

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-app-services/9-backup-app-service

Back up and restore your App Service app

The Backup and Restore feature in Azure App Service lets you easily create backups manually or on a schedule. You can configure the backups to be retained for a specific or indefinite amount of time. You can restore your app or site to a snapshot of a previous state by overwriting the existing content or restoring to another app or site.

The Backups page lists all the automatic and custom backups for your app and displays the status of each.

Things to know about Backup and Restore

Examine the following details about the Backup and Restore feature. Think about how you can implement this feature for your App Service apps.

- Back up and restore is supported in the Basic, Standard, Premium, and Isolated tiers. For the Basic tier, you can only back up and restore the production slot.

Back up and restore is supported in the Basic, Standard, Premium, and Isolated tiers. For the Basic tier, you can only back up and restore the production slot.

- You need an Azure storage account and container in the same subscription as the app to back up.

You need an Azure storage account and container in the same subscription as the app to back up.

- Azure App Service can back up the following information to the Azure storage account and container you configured for your app: App configuration settings File content Any database connected to your app (SQL Database, Azure Database for MySQL, Azure Database for PostgreSQL, MySQL in-app)

Azure App Service can back up the following information to the Azure storage account and container you configured for your app:

- App configuration settings

- File content

- Any database connected to your app (SQL Database, Azure Database for MySQL, Azure Database for PostgreSQL, MySQL in-app)

- In your storage account, each backup consists of a Zip file and XML file: The Zip file contains the back-up data for your app or site. The XML file contains a manifest of the Zip file contents.

In your storage account, each backup consists of a Zip file and XML file:

- The Zip file contains the back-up data for your app or site.

- The XML file contains a manifest of the Zip file contents.

- You can configure backups manually or on a schedule.

You can configure backups manually or on a schedule.

- Full backups are the default.

Full backups are the default.

- Partial backups are supported. You can specify files and folders to exclude from a backup.

Partial backups are supported. You can specify files and folders to exclude from a backup.

- You restore partial backups of your app or site the same way you restore a regular backup.

You restore partial backups of your app or site the same way you restore a regular backup.

- Backups can hold up to 10 GB of app and database content.

Backups can hold up to 10 GB of app and database content.

- Backups for your app or site are visible on the Containers page of your storage account and app (or site) in the Azure portal.

Backups for your app or site are visible on the Containers page of your storage account and app (or site) in the Azure portal.

Things to consider when creating backups and restoring backups

Let's review some considerations about creating a backup for your app or site, and restoring data and content from a backup.

- Consider full backups . Do a full backup to easily save all configuration settings, all file content, and all database content connected with your app or site. When you restore a full backup, all content on the site is replaced with whatever is in the backup. If a file is on the site, but not in the backup, the file is deleted.

Consider full backups . Do a full backup to easily save all configuration settings, all file content, and all database content connected with your app or site.

When you restore a full backup, all content on the site is replaced with whatever is in the backup. If a file is on the site, but not in the backup, the file is deleted.

- Consider partial backups . Specify a partial backup so you can choose exactly which files to back up. When you restore a partial backup, any content located in an excluded folder or file is left as-is.

Consider partial backups . Specify a partial backup so you can choose exactly which files to back up.

When you restore a partial backup, any content located in an excluded folder or file is left as-is.

- Consider browsing back-up files . Unzip and browse the Zip and XML files associated with your backup to access your backups. This option lets you view the content without actually performing an app or site restore.

Consider browsing back-up files . Unzip and browse the Zip and XML files associated with your backup to access your backups. This option lets you view the content without actually performing an app or site restore.

- Consider firewall on back-up destination . If your storage account is enabled with a firewall, you can't use the storage account as the destination for your backups.

Consider firewall on back-up destination . If your storage account is enabled with a firewall, you can't use the storage account as the destination for your backups.

Unit 5.4.10 - Use Azure Application Insights

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-app-services/10-use-application-insights

Use Azure Application Insights

Azure Application Insights is a feature of Azure Monitor that lets you monitor your live applications. You can integrate Application Insights with your App Service configure to automatically detect performance anomalies in your apps.

Application Insights is designed to help you continuously improve the performance and usability of your apps. The feature offers powerful analytics tools to help you diagnose issues and understand what users actually do with your apps.

Things to know about Application Insights

Let's examine some characteristics of Application Insights for Azure Monitor.

- Application Insights works on various platforms including .NET, Node.js, and Java EE.

Application Insights works on various platforms including .NET, Node.js, and Java EE.

- The feature can be used for configurations that are hosted on-premises, in a hybrid environment, or in any public cloud.

The feature can be used for configurations that are hosted on-premises, in a hybrid environment, or in any public cloud.

- Application Insights integrates with your Azure Pipeline processes, and has connection points to many development tools.

Application Insights integrates with your Azure Pipeline processes, and has connection points to many development tools.

Things to consider when using Application Insights

Application Insights is ideal for supporting your development team. The feature helps developers understand how your app is performing and how it's being used. Consider monitoring the following items in your App Service configuration scenario.

- Consider Request rates, response times, and failure rates . Find out which pages are most popular, at what times of day, and where your users are. See which pages perform best. If your response times and failure rates go high when there are more requests, then perhaps you have a resourcing problem.

Consider Request rates, response times, and failure rates . Find out which pages are most popular, at what times of day, and where your users are. See which pages perform best. If your response times and failure rates go high when there are more requests, then perhaps you have a resourcing problem.

- Consider Dependency rates, response times, and failure rates . Use Application Insights to discover if external services are degrading your app performance.

Consider Dependency rates, response times, and failure rates . Use Application Insights to discover if external services are degrading your app performance.

- Consider Exceptions . Analyze the aggregated statistics, or pick specific instances and drill into the stack trace and related requests. Both server and browser exceptions are reported.

Consider Exceptions . Analyze the aggregated statistics, or pick specific instances and drill into the stack trace and related requests. Both server and browser exceptions are reported.

- Consider Page views and load performance . Collect the number of page views reported by your users' browsers and analyze the load performance.

Consider Page views and load performance . Collect the number of page views reported by your users' browsers and analyze the load performance.

- Consider User and session counts . Application Insights can help you keep track of the number of users and sessions connected to your app.

Consider User and session counts . Application Insights can help you keep track of the number of users and sessions connected to your app.

- Consider Performance counters . Add Application Insights performance counters from your Windows or Linux server machines. Monitor performance output for the CPU, memory, network usage, and so on.

Consider Performance counters . Add Application Insights performance counters from your Windows or Linux server machines. Monitor performance output for the CPU, memory, network usage, and so on.

- Consider Host diagnostics . Integrate diagnostics from Docker or Azure into your app Application Insights.

Consider Host diagnostics . Integrate diagnostics from Docker or Azure into your app Application Insights.

- Consider Diagnostic trace logs . Implement trace logs from your app to help correlate trace events with requests and diagnose issues.

Consider Diagnostic trace logs . Implement trace logs from your app to help correlate trace events with requests and diagnose issues.

- Consider Custom events and metrics . Write your own custom events and metric tracking algorithms as client or server code. Track business events such as number of items sold, or number of games won.

Consider Custom events and metrics . Write your own custom events and metric tracking algorithms as client or server code. Track business events such as number of items sold, or number of games won.

Tip

Consider extending your learning with the Troubleshoot solutions by using Application Insights training module.

Unit 5.4.11 - Exercise: Implement Web Apps

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-app-services/11-simulation-web-apps

Exercise: Implement Web Apps

Lab scenario

Your organization is migrating on-premises web apps to Azure. As the Azure Administrator you need to:

- Host web sites running on Windows servers by using the PHP runtime stack.

- Use Azure Web Apps deployment slots.

Architecture diagram

Job skills

- Create an Azure web app.

- Create a staging deployment slot.

- Configure Web App deployment settings.

- Deploy code to the staging deployment slot.

- Swap the staging slots.

- Configure and test autoscaling of your Azure web app.

Note

Estimated time: 20 minutes.

To complete this exercise, you need an Azure subscription .

Launch the exercise, and follow the instructions. When finished, be sure to return to this page so you can continue learning.

Unit 5.4.12 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-app-services/12-knowledge-check

Module assessment

You're developing a strategy to implement web apps for your company by using Azure App Service. Various teams in your organization submit requests for your consideration as part of the implementation plan.

- The Production team needs information about cloning configurations across deployment slots.

The Production team needs information about cloning configurations across deployment slots.

- The Marketing team needs to know which research web pages are most popular, at what times of day, and where users are located.

The Marketing team needs to know which research web pages are most popular, at what times of day, and where users are located.

- You're investigating automated deployment sources.

You're investigating automated deployment sources.

Answer the following questions

Choose the best response for each question.

Unit 5.4.13 - Summary and resources

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-app-services/13-summary-resources

Summary and resources

Azure App Service is an HTTP-based service for hosting web applications. With App Service, you can develop web apps in your favorite language. The service lets you easily run and scale your web apps on Windows and Linux-based environments.

In this module, you reviewed the features and usage cases for Azure App Service. You learned how to create, secure, and back up your web apps. You explored how to configure deployment settings, including deployment slots, and custom domain names for your web apps. You discovered how to use Azure Application Insights to monitor web apps.

The main takeaways for this module

- Azure App Service lets you develop and deploy web, mobile, and API apps.

Azure App Service lets you develop and deploy web, mobile, and API apps.

- Azure App Service configuration settings include runtime stack, operating system, region, and App Service plan.

Azure App Service configuration settings include runtime stack, operating system, region, and App Service plan.

- Deployment slots help you manage different app stages. For example, development, test, stage, and production.

Deployment slots help you manage different app stages. For example, development, test, stage, and production.

- The default Azure App Service domain name can be customized for your organization.

The default Azure App Service domain name can be customized for your organization.

- Azure Application Insights is a feature of Azure Monitor that lets you monitor your live applications. You can integrate Application Insights with your App Service configure to automatically detect performance anomalies in your apps.

Azure Application Insights is a feature of Azure Monitor that lets you monitor your live applications. You can integrate Application Insights with your App Service configure to automatically detect performance anomalies in your apps.

- Application Insights lets you continuously monitor the performance and usability of your apps.

Application Insights lets you continuously monitor the performance and usability of your apps.

Learn more with Copilot

Copilot can assist you in configuring Azure infrastructure solutions. Copilot can compare, recommend, explain, and research products and services where you need more information. Open a Microsoft Edge browser and choose Copilot (top right) or navigate to copilot.microsoft.com. Take a few minutes to try these prompts and extend your learning with Copilot.

- What are the main tasks to configure an Azure App Service web app?

What are the main tasks to configure an Azure App Service web app?

- What options are available for scaling an Azure App Service web app?

What options are available for scaling an Azure App Service web app?

Learn more with documentation

- App Service overview . This article provides an overview of the App Service and why you would use this service.

App Service overview . This article provides an overview of the App Service and why you would use this service.

- Configure an App Service app . This article explains how to configure common settings for web apps, mobile back end, or API app.

Configure an App Service app . This article explains how to configure common settings for web apps, mobile back end, or API app.

- Set up staging environments in Azure App Service . The article covers deployment slots and swap operations.

Set up staging environments in Azure App Service . The article covers deployment slots and swap operations.

Learn more with self-paced training

- Stage a web app deployment for testing and rollback by using App Service deployment slots . Learn to use deployment slots to streamline deployment and roll back.

Stage a web app deployment for testing and rollback by using App Service deployment slots . Learn to use deployment slots to streamline deployment and roll back.

- Explore Azure App Service deployment slots . Learn how slot swapping works and how to route traffic to different slots.

Explore Azure App Service deployment slots . Learn how slot swapping works and how to route traffic to different slots.

- Host a web application with Azure App Service . Learn how to create a website through the hosted web app platform in Azure App Service.

Host a web application with Azure App Service . Learn how to create a website through the hosted web app platform in Azure App Service.

LP 5 M5 - Configure Azure Container Instances

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-container-instances/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 5.5.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-container-instances/1-introduction

Introduction

Containers and virtual machines are both forms of virtualization, but there are some key differences between them.

To provide context, let's consider a scenario: You're an Azure Administrator responsible for deploying and managing applications in a cloud environment. Your organization is looking for a solution that offers fast startup times, easy management, and the ability to run applications in isolated containers. You want to understand the benefits of using Azure Container Instances and how it compares to virtual machines.

In this module, you learn when to use Azure Container Instances instead of virtual machines. You also get an overview of features and use cases.

The goal of this module is to introduce you to AI-ready Azure Container Instances.

Learning objectives

In this module, you learn how to:

- Identify when to use containers versus virtual machines.

- Identify the features and usage cases of Azure Container Instances.

- Implement Azure container groups.

Skills measured

The content in the module helps you prepare for Exam AZ-104: Microsoft Azure Administrator .

Prerequisites

- Working knowledge of containerization concepts and terminology.

- Familiarity with cloud computing and experience with the Azure portal.

Unit 5.5.2 - Compare containers to virtual machines

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-container-instances/2-compare-containers-to-virtual-machines

Compare containers to virtual machines

Hardware virtualization makes it possible to run multiple isolated instances of operating systems concurrently on the same physical hardware. Containers represent the next stage in the virtualization of computing resources.

Container-based virtualization allows you to virtualize the operating system. This approach lets you run multiple applications within the same instance of an operating system, while maintaining isolation between the applications. The containers within a virtual machine provide functionality similar to that of virtual machines within a physical server.

Things to know about containers versus virtual machines

To better understand container-based virtualization, let's compare containers and virtual machines .

Compare

Containers

Virtual machines

Isolation

A container typically provides lightweight isolation from the host and other containers, but a container doesn't provide as strong a security boundary as a virtual machine.

A virtual machine provides complete isolation from the host operating system and other virtual machines. This separation is useful when a strong security boundary is critical, such as hosting apps from competing companies on the same server or cluster.

Operating system

Containers run the user mode portion of an operating system and can be tailored to contain just the needed services for your app. This approach helps you use fewer system resources.

Virtual machines run a complete operating system including the kernel, which requires more system resources (CPU, memory, and storage).

Deployment

You can deploy individual containers by using Docker via the command line. You can deploy multiple containers by using an orchestrator such as Azure Kubernetes Service.

You can deploy individual virtual machines by using Windows Admin Center or Hyper-V Manager. You can deploy multiple virtual machines by using PowerShell or System Center Virtual Machine Manager.

Persistent storage

Containers use Azure Disks for local storage for a single node, or Azure Files (SMB shares) for storage shared by multiple nodes or servers.

Virtual machines use a virtual hard disk (VHD) for local storage for a single machine, or an SMB file share for storage shared by multiple servers.

Fault tolerance

If a cluster node fails, the orchestrator on another cluster node rapidly recreates any containers running on the node.

Virtual machines can fail over to another server in a cluster, where the virtual machine's operating system restarts on the new server.

Things to consider when using containers

Containers offer several advantages over physical and virtual machines. Review the following benefits and consider how you can implement containers for the internal apps for your company.

- Consider flexibility and speed . Gain increased flexibility and speed when developing and sharing your containerized application code.

Consider flexibility and speed . Gain increased flexibility and speed when developing and sharing your containerized application code.

- Consider testing . Choose containers for your configuration to allow for simplified testing of your apps.

Consider testing . Choose containers for your configuration to allow for simplified testing of your apps.

- Consider app deployment . Implement containers to gain streamlined and accelerated deployment of your apps.

Consider app deployment . Implement containers to gain streamlined and accelerated deployment of your apps.

- Consider workload density . Support higher workload density and improve your resource utilization by working with containers.

Consider workload density . Support higher workload density and improve your resource utilization by working with containers.

Unit 5.5.3 - Review Azure Container Instances

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-container-instances/3-review

Review Azure Container Instances

Containers are becoming the preferred way to package, deploy, and manage cloud applications. There are many options for teams to build and deploy cloud native and containerized applications on Azure. In this unit, we review Azure Container Instances (ACI).

Azure Container Instances offers the fastest and simplest way to run a container in Azure, without having to manage any virtual machines and without having to adopt a higher-level service. Azure Container Instances is a great solution for any scenario that can operate in isolated containers.

Understand container images

All containers are created from container images. A container image is a lightweight, standalone, executable package of software that encapsulates everything needed to run an application. It includes the following components:

- Code : The application’s source code.

- Runtime : The environment required to execute the application.

- System tools : Utilities necessary for the application to function.

- System libraries : Shared libraries used by the application.

- Settings : Configuration parameters specific to the application.

When you create a container image, it becomes a portable unit that can run consistently across different computing environments. These images are the building blocks for containers, which are instances of these images running at runtime.

The following illustration shows a web server container built with Azure Container Instances. The container is running on a virtual machine in a virtual network.

Things to know about Azure Container Instances

Let's review some of the benefits of using Azure Container Instances . As you review these points, think about how you can implement Container Instances for your internal applications.

- Fast startup times . Containers can start in seconds without the need to deploy and manage virtual machines.

Fast startup times . Containers can start in seconds without the need to deploy and manage virtual machines.

- Public IP connectivity and DNS names . Containers can be directly exposed to the internet with an IP address and FQDN (fully qualified domain name).

Public IP connectivity and DNS names . Containers can be directly exposed to the internet with an IP address and FQDN (fully qualified domain name).

- Custom sizes . You specify CPU cores (from 0.1 to 4 vCPU) and memory (from 0.1 to 16 GB) for each container at deployment time. Resource allocation is fixed for the lifetime of the container group.

Custom sizes . You specify CPU cores (from 0.1 to 4 vCPU) and memory (from 0.1 to 16 GB) for each container at deployment time. Resource allocation is fixed for the lifetime of the container group.

- Persistent storage . Containers support direct mounting of Azure Files file shares.

Persistent storage . Containers support direct mounting of Azure Files file shares.

- Linux and Windows containers . Container Instances can schedule both Windows and Linux containers. Specify the operating system type when you create your container groups.

Linux and Windows containers . Container Instances can schedule both Windows and Linux containers. Specify the operating system type when you create your container groups.

- Coscheduled groups . Container Instances supports scheduling of multi-container groups that share host machine resources.

Coscheduled groups . Container Instances supports scheduling of multi-container groups that share host machine resources.

- Virtual network deployment . Linux container groups can be deployed into an Azure virtual network for private communication with other Azure resources. Virtual network deployed containers receive no public IP address and communicate only within the virtual network or peered networks.

Virtual network deployment . Linux container groups can be deployed into an Azure virtual network for private communication with other Azure resources. Virtual network deployed containers receive no public IP address and communicate only within the virtual network or peered networks.

Unit 5.5.4 - Implement container groups

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-container-instances/4-implement-container-groups

Implement container groups

The top-level resource in Azure Container Instances is the container group . A container group is a collection of containers that get scheduled on the same host machine. The containers share a lifecycle, resources, local network, and storage volumes.

Things to know about container groups

Let's review some of details about container groups for Azure Container Instances.

- A container group is similar to a pod in Kubernetes. A pod typically has a 1:1 mapping with a container, but a pod can contain multiple containers. The containers in a multi-container pod can share related resources.

A container group is similar to a pod in Kubernetes. A pod typically has a 1:1 mapping with a container, but a pod can contain multiple containers. The containers in a multi-container pod can share related resources.

- Azure Container Instances allocates resources to a multi-container group by adding together the resource requests of all containers in the group. Resources can include items such as CPUs, memory, and GPUs.

Azure Container Instances allocates resources to a multi-container group by adding together the resource requests of all containers in the group. Resources can include items such as CPUs, memory, and GPUs.

- There are three common ways to deploy a multi-container group. Azure Resource Manager template . JSON-based infrastructure as code, ideal when deploying alongside other Azure resources. Bicep . Microsoft's recommended infrastructure as code language, more concise than Azure Resource Manager templates. Bicep includes full IntelliSense support. YAML files . Container-focused format, ideal for deployments that include only container instances.

There are three common ways to deploy a multi-container group.

- Azure Resource Manager template . JSON-based infrastructure as code, ideal when deploying alongside other Azure resources.

Azure Resource Manager template . JSON-based infrastructure as code, ideal when deploying alongside other Azure resources.

- Bicep . Microsoft's recommended infrastructure as code language, more concise than Azure Resource Manager templates. Bicep includes full IntelliSense support.

Bicep . Microsoft's recommended infrastructure as code language, more concise than Azure Resource Manager templates. Bicep includes full IntelliSense support.

- YAML files . Container-focused format, ideal for deployments that include only container instances.

YAML files . Container-focused format, ideal for deployments that include only container instances.

- Container groups can share an external-facing IP address, one or more ports on the IP address, and a DNS label with an FQDN. External client access . You must expose the port on the IP address and from the container to enable external clients to reach a container in your group. Port mapping . Port mapping isn't supported because containers in a group share a port namespace. Deleted groups . When a container group is deleted, its IP address and FQDN are released.

Container groups can share an external-facing IP address, one or more ports on the IP address, and a DNS label with an FQDN.

- External client access . You must expose the port on the IP address and from the container to enable external clients to reach a container in your group.

External client access . You must expose the port on the IP address and from the container to enable external clients to reach a container in your group.

- Port mapping . Port mapping isn't supported because containers in a group share a port namespace.

Port mapping . Port mapping isn't supported because containers in a group share a port namespace.

- Deleted groups . When a container group is deleted, its IP address and FQDN are released.

Deleted groups . When a container group is deleted, its IP address and FQDN are released.

Configuration example

Consider the following example of a multi-container group with two containers.

The multi-container group has the following characteristics and configuration:

- The container group is scheduled on a single host machine, and is assigned a DNS name label.

- The container group exposes a single public IP address with one exposed port.

- One container in the group listens on port 80. The other container listens on port 1433.

- The group includes two Azure Files file shares as volume mounts. Each container in the group mounts one of the file shares locally.

Things to consider when using container groups

Multi-container groups are useful when you want to divide a single functional task into a few container images. Different teams can deliver the images, and the images can have separate resource requirements.

Consider the following scenarios for working with multi-container groups. Think about what options can support your internal apps for the online retailer.

- Consider web app updates . Support updates to your web apps by implementing a multi-container group. One container in the group serves the web app and another container pulls the latest content from source control.

Consider web app updates . Support updates to your web apps by implementing a multi-container group. One container in the group serves the web app and another container pulls the latest content from source control.

- Consider log data collection . Use a multi-container group to capture logging and metrics data about your app. Your application container outputs logs and metrics. A logging container collects the output data and writes the data to long-term storage.

Consider log data collection . Use a multi-container group to capture logging and metrics data about your app. Your application container outputs logs and metrics. A logging container collects the output data and writes the data to long-term storage.

- Consider app monitoring . Enable monitoring for your app with a multi-container group. A monitoring container periodically makes a request to your application container to ensure your app is running and responding correctly. The monitoring container raises an alert if it identifies possible issues with your app.

Consider app monitoring . Enable monitoring for your app with a multi-container group. A monitoring container periodically makes a request to your application container to ensure your app is running and responding correctly. The monitoring container raises an alert if it identifies possible issues with your app.

- Consider front-end and back-end support . Create a multi-container group to hold your front-end container and back-end container. The front-end container can serve a web app. The back-end container can run a service to retrieve data.

Consider front-end and back-end support . Create a multi-container group to hold your front-end container and back-end container. The front-end container can serve a web app. The back-end container can run a service to retrieve data.

Unit 5.5.5 - Review Azure Container Apps

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-container-instances/5-review-docker-platform

Review Azure Container Apps

There are many options for teams to build and deploy cloud native and containerized applications on Azure. Let's understand which scenarios and use cases are best suited for Azure Container Apps and how it compares to other container options on Azure. Listen to a developer's view of Azure Container Instances.

Things to know about Azure Container Apps

Azure Container Apps is a serverless platform that allows you to maintain less infrastructure and save costs while running containerized applications. Instead of worrying about server configuration, container orchestration, and deployment details, Container Apps provides all the up-to-date server resources required to keep your applications stable and secure.

Common uses of Azure Container Apps include:

- Deploying API endpoints

- Hosting background processing jobs

- Handling event-driven processing

- Running microservices

Applications built on Azure Container Apps can dynamically scale based on the following characteristics:

- HTTP traffic

- Event-driven processing

- CPU or memory load

- Any KEDA-supported scaler

Things to consider when using Azure Container Apps

Azure Container Apps enables you to build serverless microservices and jobs based on containers. Distinctive features of Container Apps include:

- Optimized for running general purpose containers, especially for applications that span many microservices deployed in containers.

- Powered by Kubernetes and open-source technologies like Dapr, KEDA, and envoy.

- Supports Kubernetes-style apps and microservices with features like service discovery and traffic splitting.

- Enables event-driven application architectures by supporting scale based on traffic and pulling from event sources like queues, including scale to zero.

- Supports running on demand, scheduled, and event-driven jobs.

Azure Container Apps doesn't provide direct access to the underlying Kubernetes APIs. If you would like to build Kubernetes-style applications and don't require direct access to all the native Kubernetes APIs and cluster management, Container Apps provides a fully managed experience based on best-practices. For these reasons, many teams prefer to start building container microservices with Azure Container Apps.

Compare container management solutions

Azure offers several container platforms for different scenarios. Azure Container Instances (ACI) is best for isolated, short-lived tasks. Azure Container Apps (ACA) serves serverless microservices. Azure Kubernetes Service (AKS) provides full Kubernetes control for complex orchestration needs.

Feature

Azure Container Apps (ACA)

Azure Kubernetes Service (AKS)

Overview

ACA is a serverless container platform that simplifies the deployment and management of microservices-based applications by abstracting away the underlying infrastructure.

AKS simplifies deploying a managed Kubernetes cluster in Azure by offloading the operational overhead to Azure. It’s suitable for complex applications that require orchestration.

Deployment

ACA provides a PaaS experience with quick deployment and management capabilities.

AKS offers more control and customization options for Kubernetes environments, making it suitable for complex applications and microservices.

Management

ACA builds upon AKS and offers a simplified PaaS experience for running containers.

AKS provides a more granular control over the Kubernetes environment, suitable for teams with Kubernetes expertise.

Scalability

ACA supports both HTTP-based autoscaling and event-driven scaling, making it ideal for applications that need to respond quickly to changes in demand.

AKS offers horizontal pod autoscaling and cluster autoscaling, providing robust scalability options for containerized applications.

Use Cases

ACA is designed for microservices and serverless applications that benefit from rapid scaling and simplified management.

AKS is best for complex, long-running applications. These applications require full Kubernetes features and tight integration with other Azure services.

Unit 5.5.6 - Exercise: Implement Container Instances

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-container-instances/6-simulation-containers

Exercise: Implement Container Instances

Lab scenario

Your organization has a web application that runs on a virtual machine in your on-premises data center. The organization wants to move all applications to the cloud but doesn’t want to have a large number of servers to manage. You decide to evaluate Azure Container Instances and Docker.

Architecture diagram

Job skills

- Deploy an Azure Container Instance using a Docker image.

- Test and verify deployment of an Azure Container Instance.

Note

Estimated time: 15 minutes.

To complete this exercise, you need an Azure subscription .

Launch the exercise, and follow the instructions. When finished, be sure to return to this page so you can continue learning.

Unit 5.5.7 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-container-instances/7-knowledge-check

Module assessment

You're working on the app deployment and management strategy for your company's online retail site. You're reviewing a few scenarios as part of the implementation planning.

- The Admin team requested input about where containers on Windows can be more advantageous than virtual machines.

The Admin team requested input about where containers on Windows can be more advantageous than virtual machines.

- You're examining features of Azure Container Instances to support site-related apps hosted on-premises in Azure to share hardware resources, network usage, and storage volumes.

You're examining features of Azure Container Instances to support site-related apps hosted on-premises in Azure to share hardware resources, network usage, and storage volumes.

- The development team needs a container management solution that simplifies deployment and provides orchestration.

The development team needs a container management solution that simplifies deployment and provides orchestration.

Answer the following questions

Choose the best response for each question.

Unit 5.5.8 - Summary and resources

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/configure-azure-container-instances/8-summary-resources

Summary and resources

In this module, you learned how to identify when to use Azure Container Instances versus Azure virtual machines. You explored the features and usage cases of Azure Container Instances. You discovered how to implement Azure container groups.

The main takeaways from this module are:

- Containers provide lightweight isolation and use fewer system resources compared to virtual machines.

- Containers can be deployed individually using Docker or with an orchestrator like Azure Container Apps.

- Containers use Azure Disks or Azure Files for storage.

- A container group is a collection of containers that get scheduled on the same host machine.

- Containers can be rapidly recreated on another cluster node if a node fails.

Learn more with Copilot

Copilot can assist you in configuring Azure infrastructure solutions. Copilot can compare, recommend, explain, and research products and services where you need more information. Open a Microsoft Edge browser and choose Copilot (top right) or navigate to copilot.microsoft.com. Take a few minutes to try these prompts and extend your learning with Copilot.

- Compare benefits and usage cases for containers and virtual machines.

Compare benefits and usage cases for containers and virtual machines.

- What are the best practices for configuring Azure Container Instances for task-based workloads? Explain the restart policies.

What are the best practices for configuring Azure Container Instances for task-based workloads? Explain the restart policies.

- How do I deploy a multi-container group in Azure Container Instances using Bicep? Show an example with environment variables.

How do I deploy a multi-container group in Azure Container Instances using Bicep? Show an example with environment variables.

Learn more with documentation

- Containers versus virtual machines . This article reviews the key similarities and differences between containers and virtual machines (VMs), and when you might want to use each.

Containers versus virtual machines . This article reviews the key similarities and differences between containers and virtual machines (VMs), and when you might want to use each.

- Quickstart: Deploy a container instance in Azure using the Azure portal . In this quickstart, you use the Azure portal to deploy an isolated Docker container and make its application available with a fully qualified domain name (FQDN). After configuring a few settings and deploying the container, you can browse to the running application:

Quickstart: Deploy a container instance in Azure using the Azure portal . In this quickstart, you use the Azure portal to deploy an isolated Docker container and make its application available with a fully qualified domain name (FQDN). After configuring a few settings and deploying the container, you can browse to the running application:

- Container groups in Azure Container Instances . This article describes what container groups are and the types of scenarios they enable.

Container groups in Azure Container Instances . This article describes what container groups are and the types of scenarios they enable.

Learn more with self-paced training

- Run container images in Azure Container Instances . Learn how Azure Container Instances can help you quickly deploy containers, how to set environment variables, and specify container restart policies.

Run container images in Azure Container Instances . Learn how Azure Container Instances can help you quickly deploy containers, how to set environment variables, and specify container restart policies.

- Implement Azure Container Apps . Learn how Azure Container Apps can help you deploy and manage microservices and containerized apps on a serverless platform that runs on top of Azure Kubernetes Service.

Implement Azure Container Apps . Learn how Azure Container Apps can help you deploy and manage microservices and containerized apps on a serverless platform that runs on top of Azure Kubernetes Service.

- Introduction to Docker containers . Learn the benefits of using Docker containers as a containerization platform. Discuss the infrastructure provided by the Docker platform.

Introduction to Docker containers . Learn the benefits of using Docker containers as a containerization platform. Discuss the infrastructure provided by the Docker platform.

LP 6 M1 - Introduction to Azure Backup

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-backup/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 6.1.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-backup/1-introduction

Introduction

Information technology workers understand the importance of data to the organization. The need to protect that data drives decisions around storage, backups, and security. Many companies implement policies that dictate backup specifications for frequency, duration of backup storage, and restore policies.

For on-premises scenarios, backup solutions might have included local redundant storage solutions or off-site storage. Scenarios using backup to tape drives and storing offsite come with the resulting delay in restoring the data (because of the need to transport the tapes back to the server rooms and from performing the restore operation). This can result in significant downtime.

These backup solutions might not always address some of the most important considerations, such as security of the backups, the potential for the company to be impacted by a ransomware attack, or human error in the backup and restore operations. An ideal solution would be cost-effective, simple to use, and secure. This is where Azure Backup comes in.

Azure Backup can also address scenarios for your Azure environments, with support for:

- Azure VMs

- Azure Managed Disks

- Azure Files

- SQL Server in Azure VMs

- SAP HANA databases in Azure VMs

- Azure Database for PostgreSQL servers

- Azure Blobs

- Azure Database for PostgreSQL - Flexible servers

- Azure Database for MySQL - Flexible servers

- Azure Kubernetes cluster

Example scenario

You're running an application powered by SQL Server. The database is running in an always-on availability group across three Azure VMs. You want to back up the databases using an Azure native backup service. You're looking to store the backup for 10 years in cheaper storage for your audit and compliance needs. You'd like to monitor the backup jobs daily for all such databases.

What will we be doing?

We'll evaluate the features and capabilities of Azure Backup to help decide if:

- Azure Backup can offer a solution for your backup needs.

- You can back up and restore the data you need for your organization.

- Azure Backup offers secure storage of your data.

What is the main goal?

By the end of this session, you'll be able to decide if Azure Backup is the right solution to consider for your data-protection needs.

Unit 6.1.2 - What is Azure Backup?

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-backup/2-what-is-azure-backup

What is Azure Backup?

Let's start by defining Azure Backup and taking a quick tour of the core features. This overview should help you decide whether Azure Backup might be a good fit for your data-protection needs.

What is Azure Backup?

The Azure Backup service provides simple, secure, and cost-effective solutions to back up your data and recover it from the Microsoft Azure cloud.

Azure Backup definition

Azure Backup is an Azure service that provides cost effective, secure, and zero-infrastructure backup solutions for all Azure-managed data assets.

The centralized management interface makes it easy to define backup policies and protect a wide range of enterprise workloads, including Azure Virtual Machines, Azure Disks, SQL and SAP databases, Azure file shares, and blobs.

When to use Azure Backup

As the IT admin of your organization, you're responsible for meeting the compliance needs for all the data assets of the firm, and backup is a critical aspect. There are also various application admins in your company who need to do self-service backup and restore to take care of issues like data corruption or rogue-admin scenarios. You're looking for an enterprise-class backup solution to protect all your workloads and manage them from a central place.

Azure Backup can provide backup services for the following data assets:

- On-premises files, folders, and system state

- Azure Virtual Machines (VMs)

- Azure Managed Disks

- Azure Files Shares

- SQL Server in Azure VMs

- SAP HANA (High-performance Analytic Appliance) databases in Azure VMs

- Azure Database for PostgreSQL servers

- Azure Blobs

- Azure Database for PostgreSQL - Flexible servers

- Azure Database for MySQL - Flexible servers

- Azure Kubernetes cluster

Key features

Let's look at some key features of Azure Backup.

Feature

Description

Usage

Zero-infrastructure backup solution

Unlike conventional backup solutions, no backup server or infrastructure is needed. Similarly, no backup storage needs to be deployed, because Azure Backup automatically manages and scales it.

Zero-infrastructure solution eliminates capital expenses and reduces operational expenses. It increases ease of use by automating storage management.

At-scale management

Natively manage your entire backup estate from a central console called Backup Center. Use APIs, PowerShell, and Azure CLI to automate Backup policy and security configurations.

Backup center simplifies data protection management at-scale by enabling you to discover, govern, monitor, operate, and optimize backup management from one unified console, which helps you to drive operational efficiency with Azure.

Security

Azure Backup provides built-in security to your backup environment, both when your data is in transit and at rest by using capabilities encryption, private endpoints, alerts, and so on.

Your backups are automatically secured against ransomware, malicious admins, and accidental deletions.

How do Recovery Time Objective and Recovery Point Objective work?

Recovery Time Objective (RTO) is the target time within which a business process must be restored after a disaster occurs to avoid unacceptable consequences. For instance, if a critical application goes down due to a server failure and the business can only tolerate a maximum of four hours of downtime, then the RTO is four hours.

Recovery Point Objective (RPO) is the maximum amount of data loss, measured in time, that your organization can sustain during an event.

The following example scenario describes both the RPO and RTO concepts:

Your organization has an RPO of one hour for your customer database, which means you perform backups every hour. If a data-loss incident occurs, you lose not more than one hour of data. When you set RTO to three hours, then if a system failure occurs, you aim to restore access to the database within three hours to minimize the impact on operations.

Unit 6.1.3 - How Azure Backup works

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-backup/3-how-azure-backup-works

How Azure Backup works

Let's take a look at how Azure Backup works to provide the data protection you need. Particularly, let's look at how the different aspects of the backup service make it easy to back up various types of data, and how it offers security for your backups as well. In this unit, we cover the following aspects of the Azure Backup Service:

- Workload integration layer - Backup Extension : Integration with the actual workload, such as Azure virtual machines (VMs) or Azure Blobs, happens at this layer.

- Data Plane - Access Tiers : There are three access tiers where the backups could be stored: Snapshot tier Standard tier Archive tier

- Snapshot tier

- Standard tier

- Archive tier

- Data Plane - Availability and Security : The backup data is replicated across zones or regions, based on the redundancy the user specifies.

- Management Plane – Recovery Services vault/Backup vault and Backup center : The vault provides an interface for the user to interact with the backup service.

What data is backed up and how?

The simplest explanation of Azure Backup is that it backs up data, machine state, and workloads running on on-premises machines and VM instances to the Azure cloud. Azure Backup stores the backed-up data in Recovery Services vaults and Backup vaults.

For on-premises Windows machines, you can back up directly to Azure with the Azure Backup Microsoft Azure Recovery Services (MARS) agent. Alternatively, you can back up these Windows machines to a backup server, perhaps a System Center Data Protection Manager (DPM) or Microsoft Azure Backup Server (MABS). You can then back that server up to a Recovery Services vault in Azure.

If you're using Azure VMs, you can back them up directly. Azure Backup installs a backup extension to the Azure VM agent that's running on the VM, which allows you to back up the entire VM. If you only want to back up the files and folders on the VM, you can do so by running the MARS agent.

Azure Backup stores backed-up data in vaults: Recovery Services vaults and Backup vaults. A vault is an online-storage entity in Azure that's used to hold data such as backup copies, recovery points, and backup policies.

Supported backup types

Azure Backup supports full backups and incremental backups. Your initial backup is a full backup. DPM/MABS use the incremental backup for disk backups, and all backups to Azure also use incremental backups. As the name suggests, incremental backups only focus on the blocks of data that changed since the previous backup.

Azure Backup also supports SQL Server backup types. The following table outlines the support for SQL Server type backups:

Type

Description

Usage

Full

A full database backup backs up the entire database. It contains all the data in a specific database or in a set of filegroups or files. A full backup also contains enough logs to recover that data.

At most, you can trigger one full backup per day. You can choose to make a full backup on a daily or weekly interval.

Differential

A differential backup is based on the most recent full-data backup. It captures only the data that changed since the full backup.

At most, you can trigger one differential backup per day. You can't configure a full backup and a differential backup on the same day.

Multiple backups per day

Back up Azure VMs hourly with a minimum recovery point objective (RPO) of 4 hours and a maximum of 24 hours.

You can use Enhanced backup policy to set the backup schedule to 4, 6, 8, 12, and 24 hours (respectively) for new Azure offerings, such as Trusted Launch VM.

Selective disk backup

Selectively back up a subset of the data disks that are attached to your VM, then restore a subset of the disks that are available in a recovery point, both from instant restore and vault tier. Selective disk backup helps you manage critical data in a subset of the VM disks and use database backup solutions when you want to back up only their OS disk to reduce cost.

Azure Backup provides Selective Disk backup and restore capability using Enhanced backup policy.

Transaction Log

A log backup enables point-in-time restoration up to a specific second.

At most, you can configure transactional log backups every 15 minutes.

Workload integration layer - Backup Extension

A backup extension specific to each workload is installed on the source VM or a worker VM. At the time of backup (as defined by the user in the Backup Policy) the backup extension generates the backup, which could be:

- Storage : Snapshots when using an Azure VM or Azure Files.

Storage : Snapshots when using an Azure VM or Azure Files.

- Stream backup : For databases like SQL or High-performance Analytic Appliance (HANA) running in VMs.

Stream backup : For databases like SQL or High-performance Analytic Appliance (HANA) running in VMs.

The backup data is eventually transferred to Azure Backup managed storage in the data plane by using secure Azure networks Network Security Groups (NSG), Firewalls, or more sophisticated private endpoints.

Data Plane - Access Tiers

There are three access tiers where the backups can be stored:

- Snapshot tier : (Workload-specific term) In the first phase of a virtual machine backup, the snapshot is taken and stored along with the disk. This form of storage is referred to as a snapshot tier. Restoring a snapshot tier is faster than restoring from a vault, because it eliminates the wait time for snapshots to be copied from the vault before triggering the restore operation. The snapshots of the VM/Azure Files/Azure Blobs/and so on are retained in the customer's subscription in a specified resource group. This container ensures that restores are quick, because the backup/snapshot is available locally to the customer.

Snapshot tier : (Workload-specific term) In the first phase of a virtual machine backup, the snapshot is taken and stored along with the disk. This form of storage is referred to as a snapshot tier. Restoring a snapshot tier is faster than restoring from a vault, because it eliminates the wait time for snapshots to be copied from the vault before triggering the restore operation. The snapshots of the VM/Azure Files/Azure Blobs/and so on are retained in the customer's subscription in a specified resource group. This container ensures that restores are quick, because the backup/snapshot is available locally to the customer.

- Vault-standard tier : Backup data for all workloads supported by Azure Backup is stored in vaults, which hold backup storage, an autoscaling set of storage accounts managed by Azure Backup. The Vault-standard tier is an online storage tier that allows you to store an isolated copy of backup data in a Microsoft-managed tenant, thus creating an extra layer of protection. For workloads where snapshot tier is supported, there's a copy of the backup data in both the snapshot tier and the Vault-standard tier. The Vault-standard tier ensures that backup data is available even if the data source being backed up is deleted or compromised.

Vault-standard tier : Backup data for all workloads supported by Azure Backup is stored in vaults, which hold backup storage, an autoscaling set of storage accounts managed by Azure Backup. The Vault-standard tier is an online storage tier that allows you to store an isolated copy of backup data in a Microsoft-managed tenant, thus creating an extra layer of protection. For workloads where snapshot tier is supported, there's a copy of the backup data in both the snapshot tier and the Vault-standard tier. The Vault-standard tier ensures that backup data is available even if the data source being backed up is deleted or compromised.

- Archive tier : Customers rely on Azure Backup for storing backup data, including their Long-Term Retention (LTR) backup data, with retention needs defined in the organization's compliance rules. In most cases, the older backup data is rarely accessed and is only stored for compliance needs. Azure Backup supports backup of long-term retention points in the archive tier.

Archive tier : Customers rely on Azure Backup for storing backup data, including their Long-Term Retention (LTR) backup data, with retention needs defined in the organization's compliance rules. In most cases, the older backup data is rarely accessed and is only stored for compliance needs.

Azure Backup supports backup of long-term retention points in the archive tier.

All tiers offer different recovery time objectives (RTO) and are priced differently.

Data Plane - Availability and Security

The backup data is replicated across zones or regions, based on the redundancy you specify. You can choose from locally redundant storage (LRS), Geo-redundant storage (GRS), or zone-redundant storage (ZRS). These options provide you with highly available data storage capabilities.

The data is kept safe by encrypting it and implementing Azure role-based access control (RBAC). You choose who can perform backup and restore operations. Azure Backup also provides protection against malicious deletion of your backup by using soft-delete operations. A deleted backup is stored for 14 days, free of charge, which allows you to recover the backup if needed.

Azure Backup also supports a backup data lifecycle-management scenario that allows you to comply with retention policies.

Management Plane – Recovery Services vault/Backup vault and Backup center

Azure Backup uses Recovery Services vaults and Backup vaults to orchestrate and manage backups. It also uses vaults to store backed-up data. The vault provides an interface for the user to interact with the backup service. Azure Backup Policies within each vault define when the backups should get triggered and how long they need to be retained.

You can use a single vault or multiple vaults to organize and manage your backup. If you manage your workloads with a single subscription and single resource, you can use a single vault to monitor and manage your backup estate. If your workloads are spread across multiple subscriptions, you can create multiple vaults with one or more vaults per subscription.

Backup center allows you to have a single pane of glass to manage all tasks related to backups. Backup center is designed to function well across a large and distributed Azure environment. You can use Backup center to efficiently manage backups spanning multiple workload types, vaults, subscriptions, regions, and Azure Lighthouse tenants.

Unit 6.1.4 - When to use Azure Backup

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-backup/4-when-to-use-azure-backup

When to use Azure Backup

Here, we discuss how you can decide if Azure Backup is the right choice for your data-protection needs. In this unit, we highlight common backup scenarios where Azure Backup provides benefits, such as:

- Ensuring availability of your data.

- Protecting your Azure workloads.

- Securing your data.

Decision criteria

Azure Backup is an Azure service that provides secure and zero-infrastructure backup solutions for all Azure-managed data assets. It protects a wide range of enterprise workloads. Including, Azure Virtual Machines (VMs), Azure Disks, SQL and SAP databases, and Azure file shares and blobs.

The main criteria that we're evaluating are outlined in the following table. The table contains some key areas where Azure Backup can provide services to you for data protection.

Criteria

Consideration

Azure workloads

Azure VMs, Azure Disks, SQL Server in Azure VMs, SAP HANA databases in Azure VMs, Azure Blobs, Azure Files shares, Azure Database for PostgreSQL.

Compliance

Customer-defined backup policy with long-term retention across multiple zones or regions.

Operational recoveries

With self-service backup and restores, the application administrator can take care of issues that might arise such as accidental deletion or data corruption.

Apply the criteria

In the introduction, we presented a scenario where your organization might have an application that relies on data from a back-end SQL Server installation. SQL Server is running on three Azure VMs. The data in the backup must be retained for up to 10 years to meet compliance requirements. You also want to be able to monitor the backups.

Before we dive into how Azure Backup can help meet these needs, it's important to understand what isn't currently supported. If your three Azure VMs are deployed across multiple subscriptions or regions, you should note that Azure Backup doesn’t support cross-region backup for most workloads. However, it does support cross-region restore in a paired secondary region.

Can Azure Backup protect the Azure VMs hosting the SQL Server instances?

Azure Backup is able to back up entire Windows and Linux VMs using backup extensions. As a result, you can back up the entire VM that hosts SQL Server. If you only want to back up the files, folders, and system state on the Azure VMs, you can use the Microsoft Azure Recovery Services (MARS) agent.

If your main concern is to only back up the SQL Server data, Azure Backup provides support for that as well. Azure Backup offers a stream-based, specialized solution to back up SQL Servers running in Azure VMs. This solution aligns with Azure Backup's benefits of zero-infrastructure backup, long-term retention, and central management.

Additionally, Azure Backup provides the following advantages specifically for SQL Server:

- Workload aware backups that support all backup types: full, differential, and log

- 15-minute recovery point objective (RPO) with frequent log backups

- Point-in-time recovery up to a second

- Individual database-level backup and restore

Does Azure Backup help with compliance?

You can implement required access-control mechanisms for your backups. Vaults (Recovery Services and Backup vaults) provide the management capabilities and are accessible via the Azure portal, Backup Center, Vault dashboards, SDK, CLI, and even REST APIs. It's also an Azure role-based access control (Azure RBAC) boundary, providing you with the option to restrict access to backups only to authorized Backup Admins.

Short-term retention can be minutes or daily . Retention for weekly , monthly , or yearly backup points is referred to as Long-term retention .

Long-term retention can be:

- Planned (compliance requirements) : If you know in advance that data is required years from the current time, use Long-term retention.

- Unplanned (on-demand requirement) : If you don't know in advance, then you can use on-demand backup with specific custom retention settings. Your policy settings don't impact these custom retention settings.

- On-demand backup with custom retention : If you need to take a backup not scheduled via backup policy, then you can use an on-demand backup. It can be useful for taking backups that don’t fit your scheduled backup or for taking granular backup (for example, multiple IaaS VM backups per day since scheduled backup permits only one backup per day). It's important to note that the retention policy defined in scheduled policy doesn't apply to on-demand backups.

You can also implement policy management to help with compliance. Azure Backup Policies within each vault define when the backups should be triggered and how long they need to be retained. You can also manage these policies and apply them across multiple items.

Does Azure Backup simplify monitoring and administration?

Azure Backup integrates with Log Analytics for monitoring and reporting and provides reports via Workbooks.

Azure Backup provides in-built job monitoring for operations such as configuring backup, backing up, restoring, deleting backups, and so on. Azure Backup is scoped to the vault, making it ideal for monitoring a single vault.

If you need to monitor operational activities at scale, Backup Explorer provides an aggregated view of your entire backup estate, enabling detailed drill-down analysis and troubleshooting. It's a built-in Azure Monitor workbook that provides a single, central location to help you monitor operational activities across the entire backup estate on Azure, spanning tenants, locations, subscriptions, resource groups, and vaults.

Unit 6.1.5 - Module assessment

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-backup/5-knowledge-check

Module assessment

Unit 6.1.6 - Summary

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-azure-backup/6-summary

Summary

Our goal was to help you evaluate whether Azure Backup would offer the features and capabilities you need to help you protect your data. During the module, we explored how Azure Backup might address:

- Ensuring availability of your data.

- Protecting your Azure workloads.

- Securing your data.

We applied the criteria to a scenario where your company was hosting an application that used a SQL Server database instance running on multiple Azure VMs. We noted how Azure Backup could provide data protection by backing up our Azure VMs or the files, folders, and system state on those VMs.

We also saw how Azure Backup helps with compliance by offering retention options for the data and security with encryption and RBAC. Using Backup center, we showed how easy it is to manage these backups.

Backup center simplifies data protection management at-scale by allowing you to discover, govern, monitor, operate, and optimize backup management, all from one unified console. This helps you to drive operational efficiency with Azure. Your backups are automatically secured against ransomware, malicious admins, and accidental deletions.

References

- Azure Backup website

- Azure Backup compliance standards

LP 6 M2 - Protect your virtual machines by using Azure Backup

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/protect-virtual-machines-with-azure-backup/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 6.2.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/protect-virtual-machines-with-azure-backup/1-introduction

Introduction

Your company has several critical virtual machine (VM) workloads running on Azure. As the lead solution architect, you're asked to ensure that the company can recover these VMs if there's data loss or corruption. You're asked to use the built-in capabilities of Azure Backup to help protect these VMs.

Azure Backup is a service that allows you to back up Azure virtual machines, on-premises servers, Azure file shares, and SQL Server or SAP HANA (High-performance Analytic Appliance) running on Azure VMs, and other application workloads.

In this module, you learn about Azure Backup and you see how you can use the Azure portal to back up and restore a VM.

Learning objectives

In this module, you:

- Identify the scenarios for which Azure Backup provides backup and restore capabilities.

- Back up and restore an Azure virtual machine.

Prerequisites

- Basic knowledge of Azure virtual machines.

- Basic knowledge of disk storage for virtual machines.

Note

For this module, you need use your own subscription to complete the optional exercises. A trial subscription or a subscription that you already have access to works for these exercises.

Unit 6.2.2 - Azure Backup features and scenarios

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/protect-virtual-machines-with-azure-backup/2-azure-backup-features-scenarios

Azure Backup features and scenarios

Your company's business continuity and disaster recovery (BCDR) plan requires a full backup and restore capability for all of your high-risk servers. You're asked to enable and test the backup and restore functionality for these critical Windows and Linux assets.

In this unit, you look at how Azure Backup works, and study some of the supported use cases for Azure Backup.

What is Azure Backup?

Azure Backup is a built-in Azure service that provides secure backup for all Azure-managed data assets. It uses zero-infrastructure solutions to enable self-service backups and restores, with at-scale management at a lower and predictable cost. Azure Backup currently offers specialized backup solutions for Azure and on-premises virtual machines (VMs). Azure Backup also gives workloads like SQL Server or SAP HANA (High-performance Analytic Appliance) running in Azure VMs enterprise-class backup and restore options.

In contrast to traditional backup solutions that can take considerable effort to set up, Azure Backup is easily managed through the Azure portal.

Azure Backup versus Azure Site Recovery

Both Azure Backup and Azure Site Recovery aim to make the system more resilient to faults and failures, but they use two different approaches. The primary goal of Backup is to maintain copies of stateful data that allow you to go back in time. Site Recovery, however, replicates the data in almost real time and allows for a failover.

In that sense, if there are issues like network or power outages, you can use availability zones. For a region-wide disaster (such as natural disasters), Site Recovery is used. Backups are used in cases of accidental data loss, data corruption, or ransomware attacks.

Additionally, the choice of a recovery approach depends on the criticality of the application, recovery point objective (RPO) and recovery time objective (RTO) requirements, and the cost implications.

Why use Azure Backup?

Traditional backup solutions, such as disk and tape, don't offer the highest level of integration with cloud-based solutions. Azure Backup has several benefits over more traditional backup solutions:

Zero-infrastructure backup : Azure Backup eliminates the need to deploy and manage any backup infrastructure or storage. There's no overhead in maintaining backup servers or scaling the storage up or down as the needs vary.

Long-term retention : Meet rigorous compliance and audit needs by retaining backups for many years, after which the built-in lifecycle management capability prunes the recovery points automatically.

Security : Azure Backup provides security to your backup environment, both when your data is in transit and at rest:

- Azure role-based access control : Role-based access control allows you to segregate duties within your team and grant only the amount of access to users necessary to do their jobs.

Azure role-based access control : Role-based access control allows you to segregate duties within your team and grant only the amount of access to users necessary to do their jobs.

- Encryption of backups : Backup data is automatically encrypted using Microsoft-managed keys. Alternatively, you can encrypt your backed-up data using customer-managed keys stored in the Azure Key Vault.

Encryption of backups : Backup data is automatically encrypted using Microsoft-managed keys. Alternatively, you can encrypt your backed-up data using customer-managed keys stored in the Azure Key Vault.

- No internet connectivity required : When you use Azure VMs, all the data transfer happens only on the Azure backbone network without needing to access your virtual network. So no access to any IPs or fully qualified domain names (FQDNs) is required.

No internet connectivity required : When you use Azure VMs, all the data transfer happens only on the Azure backbone network without needing to access your virtual network. So no access to any IPs or fully qualified domain names (FQDNs) is required.

- Soft delete : With soft delete, the backup data is retained for 14 more days even after the deletion of the backup item. This retention protects against accidental deletion or malicious deletion scenarios, allowing the recovery of those backups with no data loss. Azure Backup also provides Enhanced soft delete that enables you to retain a deleted item in the soft deleted state for a longer duration.

Soft delete : With soft delete, the backup data is retained for 14 more days even after the deletion of the backup item. This retention protects against accidental deletion or malicious deletion scenarios, allowing the recovery of those backups with no data loss. Azure Backup also provides Enhanced soft delete that enables you to retain a deleted item in the soft deleted state for a longer duration.

Azure Backup also offers the ability to back up VMs encrypted with Azure Disk Encryption.

High availability : Azure Backup offers three types of replication:

- Locally redundant storage (LRS) : The lowest-cost option with basic protection against server rack and drive failures. We recommend it for noncritical scenarios.

Locally redundant storage (LRS) : The lowest-cost option with basic protection against server rack and drive failures. We recommend it for noncritical scenarios.

- Geo-redundant storage (GRS) : The intermediate option has failover capabilities in a secondary region. We recommend it for backup scenarios.

Geo-redundant storage (GRS) : The intermediate option has failover capabilities in a secondary region. We recommend it for backup scenarios.

- Zone-redundant storage (ZRS) : This option protects against datacenter-level failures by replicating your storage account synchronously across three Azure availability zones. We recommend it for high-availability scenarios.

Zone-redundant storage (ZRS) : This option protects against datacenter-level failures by replicating your storage account synchronously across three Azure availability zones. We recommend it for high-availability scenarios.

Centralized monitoring and management : Azure Backup provides built-in monitoring and alerting capabilities in a Recovery Services vault. These capabilities are available without any other management infrastructure.

Azure Backup supported scenarios

Azure Backup supports the following scenarios:

- Azure VMs - Back up Windows or Linux Azure VMs Azure Backup provides independent and isolated backups to guard against unintended destruction of the data on your VMs. Backups are stored in a Recovery Services vault with built-in management of recovery points. Configuration and scaling are simple, backups are optimized, and you can easily restore as needed.

- On-premises - Back up files, folders, and system state using the Microsoft Azure Recovery Services (MARS) agent . Or use Microsoft Azure Backup Server (MABS) or Data Protection Manager (DPM) server to protect on-premises VMs (Hyper-V and VMware) and other on-premises workloads.

- Azure Files shares - Azure Files provides snapshot management by Azure Backup.

- SQL Server in Azure VMs and SAP HANA databases in Azure VMs - Azure Backup offers stream-based, specialized solutions to back up SQL Server, or SAP HANA running in Azure VMs. These solutions take workload-aware backups that support different backup types such as full, differential and log, 15-minute RPO, and point-in-time recovery.

Unit 6.2.3 - Back up an Azure virtual machine by using Azure Backup

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/protect-virtual-machines-with-azure-backup/3-back-up-azure-virtual-machine

Back up an Azure virtual machine by using Azure Backup

You want to ensure that the backup and restore jobs you put in place offer a way to recover your company's servers. With this requirement in mind, you want to investigate the best way to implement backup for your virtual machines (VMs).

VMs that are hosted on Azure can take advantage of Azure Backup. You can easily back up and restore machines without installing extra software.

In this unit, you explore all the methods of backing up Azure VMs provided by Azure Backup and make a decision on which to implement.

Azure VMs are backed up by taking snapshots of the underlying disks at user-defined intervals and transferring those snapshots to the Recovery Services vault as per the customer-defined policy.

Recovery Services vault

Azure Backup uses a Recovery Services vault to manage and store the backup data. A vault is a storage-management entity, which provides a simple experience to carry out and monitor backup and restore operations. With Azure Backup, you don't need to worry about deploying or managing storage accounts. In fact, all you need to specify is the vault that you want to back up the virtual machine (VM) to. The backup data is transferred to the Azure Backup storage accounts (in a separate fault domain) in the background. The vault also acts as a role-based access control boundary to allow secure access to the data.

Snapshots

A snapshot is a point-in-time backup of all disks on the VM. For Azure VMs, Azure Backup uses different extensions for each supporting operating system:

Extension

OS

Description

VM Snapshot

Windows

The extension works with Volume Shadow Copy Service (VSS) to take a copy of the data on disk and in memory.

VM SnapshotLinux

Linux

The snapshot is a copy of the disk.

Depending on how the snapshot is taken and what it includes, you can achieve different levels of consistency:

- Application consistent The snapshot captures the VM as a whole. It uses VSS writers to capture the content of the machine memory and any pending I/O operations. For Linux machines, you need to write custom pre or post scripts per app to capture the application state. You can get complete consistency for the VM and all running applications.

- The snapshot captures the VM as a whole. It uses VSS writers to capture the content of the machine memory and any pending I/O operations.

- For Linux machines, you need to write custom pre or post scripts per app to capture the application state.

- You can get complete consistency for the VM and all running applications.

- File system consistent If VSS fails on Windows, or the pre and post scripts fail on Linux, Azure Backup still creates a file-system-consistent snapshot. During a recovery, no corruption occurs within the machine. But installed applications need to do their own cleanup during startup to become consistent.

- If VSS fails on Windows, or the pre and post scripts fail on Linux, Azure Backup still creates a file-system-consistent snapshot.

- During a recovery, no corruption occurs within the machine. But installed applications need to do their own cleanup during startup to become consistent.

- Crash consistent This level of consistency typically occurs if the VM is shut down at the time of the backup. No I/O operations or memory contents are captured during this type of backup. This method doesn't guarantee data consistency for the OS or app.

- This level of consistency typically occurs if the VM is shut down at the time of the backup.

- No I/O operations or memory contents are captured during this type of backup. This method doesn't guarantee data consistency for the OS or app.

Backup policy

You can define the backup frequency and retention duration for your backups. Currently, the VM backup can be triggered daily or weekly, and can be stored for multiple years. The backup policy supports two access tiers: snapshot tier and the vault tier . By using the Enhanced policy, you can trigger hourly backups.

Selective disk backup : Azure Backup provides Selective Disk backup and restore capability using Enhanced policy . By using this capability, you can selectively back up a subset of the data disks that are attached to your VM. Then, you can restore a subset of the disks that are available in a recovery point, both from instant restore and vault tier. It helps you manage critical data in a subset of the VM disks and use database backup solutions when you want to back up only their OS disk to reduce cost.

Snapshot tier : All the snapshots are stored locally for a maximum period of five days, in what is called the snapshot tier. For all types of operation recoveries, we recommended that you restore from the snapshots because it's faster to do so. This capability is called instant restore .

Vault tier : All snapshots are additionally transferred to the vault for more security and longer retention. At this point, the recovery point type changes to "snapshot and vault."

Backup process for an Azure virtual machine

Here's how Azure Backup completes a backup for Azure VMs:

- For Azure VMs that are selected for backup, Azure Backup starts a backup job according to the backup frequency you specify in the backup policy.

For Azure VMs that are selected for backup, Azure Backup starts a backup job according to the backup frequency you specify in the backup policy.

- During the first backup, a backup extension is installed on the VM, if the VM is running: For Windows VMs, the VM Snapshot extension is installed. For Linux VMs, the VM SnapshotLinux extension is installed.

During the first backup, a backup extension is installed on the VM, if the VM is running:

- For Windows VMs, the VM Snapshot extension is installed.

- For Linux VMs, the VM SnapshotLinux extension is installed.

- After the snapshot is taken, the data is stored locally and transferred to the vault. The backup is optimized by backing up each VM disk in parallel. For each disk that's being backed up, Azure Backup reads the blocks on the disk and identifies and transfers only the data blocks that changed (the delta) since the previous backup. Snapshot data might not be immediately copied to the vault. It might take several hours at peak times. Total backup time for a VM is less than 24 hours for daily backup policies.

After the snapshot is taken, the data is stored locally and transferred to the vault.

- The backup is optimized by backing up each VM disk in parallel.

- For each disk that's being backed up, Azure Backup reads the blocks on the disk and identifies and transfers only the data blocks that changed (the delta) since the previous backup.

- Snapshot data might not be immediately copied to the vault. It might take several hours at peak times. Total backup time for a VM is less than 24 hours for daily backup policies.

You can additionally enable vault encryption with customer-managed keys (CMK) . By using Enhanced soft delete for a Recovery Services vault, you can protect backups from deletion. You can also keep Enhanced soft delete always on to prevent turning it off, thus protecting your backups from accidental deletion or from malware attacks.

Unit 6.2.4 - Exercise - Back up an Azure virtual machine

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/protect-virtual-machines-with-azure-backup/4-exercise-back-up-azure-virtual-machine

Exercise - Back up an Azure virtual machine

Your company runs a combination of Windows and Linux workloads. You're asked to prove that Azure Backup is a good fit for both kinds of virtual machines (VMs). By using a combination of the Azure CLI and the Azure portal, you help protect both kinds of virtual machines with Azure Backup.

Azure Backup can be quickly enabled for virtual machines in Azure. You can enable Azure Backup from the portal, from the Azure CLI, or by using PowerShell commands.

In this exercise, you create a virtual machine (VM), set up a backup, and start a backup.

Note

This exercise is optional. If you don't have an Azure account, you can read through the instructions so you understand how to back up virtual machines by using Azure Backup.

If you want to complete this exercise, but you don't have an Azure subscription or you prefer not to use your own account, create a free account before you begin.

Create a backup for Azure virtual machines

Set up the environment

- Sign in to the Azure portal , and select the icon to open Azure Cloud Shell.

Sign in to the Azure portal , and select the icon to open Azure Cloud Shell.

- Create a resource group to contain all the resources for this exercise. RGROUP=$(az group create --name vmbackups --location westus2 --output tsv --query name)

Create a resource group to contain all the resources for this exercise.

RGROUP=$(az group create --name vmbackups --location westus2 --output tsv --query name)

- Use Cloud Shell to create the NorthwindInternal virtual network and the NorthwindInternal1 subnet. az network vnet create \

--resource-group $RGROUP \

--name NorthwindInternal \

--address-prefixes 10.0.0.0/16 \

--subnet-name NorthwindInternal1 \

--subnet-prefixes 10.0.0.0/24

Use Cloud Shell to create the NorthwindInternal virtual network and the NorthwindInternal1 subnet.

az network vnet create \

--resource-group $RGROUP \

--name NorthwindInternal \

--address-prefixes 10.0.0.0/16 \

--subnet-name NorthwindInternal1 \

--subnet-prefixes 10.0.0.0/24

az network vnet create \

--resource-group $RGROUP \

--name NorthwindInternal \

--address-prefixes 10.0.0.0/16 \

--subnet-name NorthwindInternal1 \

--subnet-prefixes 10.0.0.0/24

Create a Windows virtual machine by using the Azure CLI

Create the NW-APP01 virtual machine by running the following command. Replace <password> with a password of your choice, enclosed in double quotes. For example, --admin-password "PassWord123!" .

<password>

--admin-password "PassWord123!"

az vm create \

--resource-group $RGROUP \

--name NW-APP01 \

--size Standard_DS1_v2 \

--public-ip-sku Standard \

--vnet-name NorthwindInternal \

--subnet NorthwindInternal1 \

--image Win2016Datacenter \

--admin-username admin123 \

--no-wait \

--admin-password <password>

az vm create \

--resource-group $RGROUP \

--name NW-APP01 \

--size Standard_DS1_v2 \

--public-ip-sku Standard \

--vnet-name NorthwindInternal \

--subnet NorthwindInternal1 \

--image Win2016Datacenter \

--admin-username admin123 \

--no-wait \

--admin-password <password>

Create a Linux virtual machine by using the Azure CLI

Create the NW-RHEL01 virtual machine by running the following command.

az vm create \

--resource-group $RGROUP \

--name NW-RHEL01 \

--size Standard_DS1_v2 \

--image RedHat:RHEL:8-gen2:latest \

--authentication-type ssh \

--generate-ssh-keys \

--vnet-name NorthwindInternal \

--subnet NorthwindInternal1

az vm create \

--resource-group $RGROUP \

--name NW-RHEL01 \

--size Standard_DS1_v2 \

--image RedHat:RHEL:8-gen2:latest \

--authentication-type ssh \

--generate-ssh-keys \

--vnet-name NorthwindInternal \

--subnet NorthwindInternal1

Note

If you get a securityProfile.securityType is invalid error running the preceding command, run the following commands to register UseStandardSecurityType , then re-run the preceding command.

securityProfile.securityType is invalid

UseStandardSecurityType

az feature register --name UseStandardSecurityType --namespace Microsoft.Compute

az feature show --name UseStandardSecurityType --namespace Microsoft.Compute

az feature register --name UseStandardSecurityType --namespace Microsoft.Compute

az feature show --name UseStandardSecurityType --namespace Microsoft.Compute

The command can take a few minutes to complete. Wait for it to finish before moving on to the next step.

Enable backup for a virtual machine by using the Azure portal

- In the Azure portal, search for and select Virtual machines . The Virtual machines pane appears.

In the Azure portal, search for and select Virtual machines .

The Virtual machines pane appears.

- From the list, select the NW-RHEL01 virtual machine that you created. The NW-RHEL01 virtual machine pane appears.

From the list, select the NW-RHEL01 virtual machine that you created.

The NW-RHEL01 virtual machine pane appears.

- In the middle menu pane, select the Capabilities tab, then scroll down to and select Backup . The Backup pane for the NW-RHEL01 virtual machine appears.

In the middle menu pane, select the Capabilities tab, then scroll down to and select Backup . The Backup pane for the NW-RHEL01 virtual machine appears.

- Select the radio button for Standard . You can accept the defaults for the following options: Backup vault : vaultXXX for the name. Backup policy : DailyPolicy-xxxxxxxx , which creates a daily backup at 12:00 PM UTC with a retention range of 180 days.

Select the radio button for Standard . You can accept the defaults for the following options:

- Backup vault : vaultXXX for the name.

- Backup policy : DailyPolicy-xxxxxxxx , which creates a daily backup at 12:00 PM UTC with a retention range of 180 days.

- Select the Enable backup button.

Select the Enable backup button.

- Once deployment completes, go back to the NW-RHEL01 virtual machine, select the Capabilities tab, then scroll down to and select Backup . The Backup pane for the NW-RHEL01 virtual machine appears.

Once deployment completes, go back to the NW-RHEL01 virtual machine, select the Capabilities tab, then scroll down to and select Backup . The Backup pane for the NW-RHEL01 virtual machine appears.

- To perform the first backup for this server, in the top menu bar, select Backup now . The Backup Now pane for NW-RHEL01 appears.

To perform the first backup for this server, in the top menu bar, select Backup now .

The Backup Now pane for NW-RHEL01 appears.

- Select OK .

Select OK .

Enable a backup by using the Azure CLI

- First, create the azure-backup vault by using Cloud Shell: az backup vault create \

--resource-group vmbackups \

--location westus2 \

--name azure-backup

First, create the azure-backup vault by using Cloud Shell:

az backup vault create \

--resource-group vmbackups \

--location westus2 \

--name azure-backup

az backup vault create \

--resource-group vmbackups \

--location westus2 \

--name azure-backup

- Using Cloud Shell, enable a backup for the NW-APP01 virtual machine. az backup protection enable-for-vm \

--resource-group vmbackups \

--vault-name azure-backup \

--vm NW-APP01 \

--policy-name EnhancedPolicy

Using Cloud Shell, enable a backup for the NW-APP01 virtual machine.

az backup protection enable-for-vm \

--resource-group vmbackups \

--vault-name azure-backup \

--vm NW-APP01 \

--policy-name EnhancedPolicy

az backup protection enable-for-vm \

--resource-group vmbackups \

--vault-name azure-backup \

--vm NW-APP01 \

--policy-name EnhancedPolicy

- Monitor the progress of the setup using the Azure CLI. az backup job list \

--resource-group vmbackups \

--vault-name azure-backup \

--output table Keep running the preceding command until you see that ConfigureBackup is finished. Name Operation Status Item Name Start Time UTC Duration

------------------------------------ --------------- ---------- ----------- -------------------------------- --------------

a3df79b4-be4f-4cc9-8b2c-a5ead44a6a12 ConfigureBackup Completed NW-APP01 2019-08-01T06:19:12.101048+00:00 0:00:31.305975

5e1531a9-8b3d-4983-a642-86ee982f7036 Backup InProgress NW-RHEL01 2019-08-01T06:18:35.955118+00:00 0:01:22.734182

860d4dca-9603-4a4e-9f3b-93f242a0a64d ConfigureBackup Completed NW-RHEL01 2019-08-01T06:13:33.860598+00:00 0:00:31.256773

Monitor the progress of the setup using the Azure CLI.

az backup job list \

--resource-group vmbackups \

--vault-name azure-backup \

--output table

az backup job list \

--resource-group vmbackups \

--vault-name azure-backup \

--output table

Keep running the preceding command until you see that ConfigureBackup is finished.

ConfigureBackup

Name Operation Status Item Name Start Time UTC Duration

------------------------------------ --------------- ---------- ----------- -------------------------------- --------------

a3df79b4-be4f-4cc9-8b2c-a5ead44a6a12 ConfigureBackup Completed NW-APP01 2019-08-01T06:19:12.101048+00:00 0:00:31.305975

5e1531a9-8b3d-4983-a642-86ee982f7036 Backup InProgress NW-RHEL01 2019-08-01T06:18:35.955118+00:00 0:01:22.734182

860d4dca-9603-4a4e-9f3b-93f242a0a64d ConfigureBackup Completed NW-RHEL01 2019-08-01T06:13:33.860598+00:00 0:00:31.256773

Name Operation Status Item Name Start Time UTC Duration

------------------------------------ --------------- ---------- ----------- -------------------------------- --------------

a3df79b4-be4f-4cc9-8b2c-a5ead44a6a12 ConfigureBackup Completed NW-APP01 2019-08-01T06:19:12.101048+00:00 0:00:31.305975

5e1531a9-8b3d-4983-a642-86ee982f7036 Backup InProgress NW-RHEL01 2019-08-01T06:18:35.955118+00:00 0:01:22.734182

860d4dca-9603-4a4e-9f3b-93f242a0a64d ConfigureBackup Completed NW-RHEL01 2019-08-01T06:13:33.860598+00:00 0:00:31.256773

- Do an initial backup of the virtual machine, instead of waiting for the schedule to run it. az backup protection backup-now \

--resource-group vmbackups \

--vault-name azure-backup \

--container-name NW-APP01 \

--item-name NW-APP01 \

--retain-until 18-10-2030 \

--backup-management-type AzureIaasVM There's no need to wait for the backup to finish, because the next section shows you how to monitor the progress in the portal.

Do an initial backup of the virtual machine, instead of waiting for the schedule to run it.

az backup protection backup-now \

--resource-group vmbackups \

--vault-name azure-backup \

--container-name NW-APP01 \

--item-name NW-APP01 \

--retain-until 18-10-2030 \

--backup-management-type AzureIaasVM

az backup protection backup-now \

--resource-group vmbackups \

--vault-name azure-backup \

--container-name NW-APP01 \

--item-name NW-APP01 \

--retain-until 18-10-2030 \

--backup-management-type AzureIaasVM

There's no need to wait for the backup to finish, because the next section shows you how to monitor the progress in the portal.

Monitor backups in the portal

View the status of a backup for a single virtual machine

- On the Azure portal menu or from the Home page, select All resources .

On the Azure portal menu or from the Home page, select All resources .

- Enter Virtual machines in the search field at the top of the page and select Virtual machines from the results.

Enter Virtual machines in the search field at the top of the page and select Virtual machines from the results.

- Select the NW-APP01 virtual machine. The NW-APP01 virtual machine pane appears.

Select the NW-APP01 virtual machine. The NW-APP01 virtual machine pane appears.

- In the middle menu pane, select the Capabilities tab, then scroll to and select Backup . The Backup pane for the NW-APP01 virtual machine appears. Under the Backup status section, the Last backup status field displays the current status of the backup.

In the middle menu pane, select the Capabilities tab, then scroll to and select Backup . The Backup pane for the NW-APP01 virtual machine appears.

Under the Backup status section, the Last backup status field displays the current status of the backup.

View the status of backups in the Recovery Services vault

- On the Azure portal menu or from the Home page, select All resources .

On the Azure portal menu or from the Home page, select All resources .

- Sort the list by Type , and then select the azure-backup Recovery Services vault. The Azure-backup recovery services vault pane appears.

Sort the list by Type , and then select the azure-backup Recovery Services vault. The Azure-backup recovery services vault pane appears.

- On the Overview pane, select the interior Backup tab to display a summary of all the backup items, the storage being used, and the current status of any backup jobs.

On the Overview pane, select the interior Backup tab to display a summary of all the backup items, the storage being used, and the current status of any backup jobs.

Unit 6.2.5 - Restore virtual machine data

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/protect-virtual-machines-with-azure-backup/5-restore-virtual-machine-data

Restore virtual machine data

Companies that have a business continuity and disaster recovery (BCDR) plan typically schedule test runs to ensure that the business can successfully recover from disasters. Now that you successfully backed up your virtual machines, you want to explore the options available for restoring them as part of your BCDR testing.

In this unit, you learn about the options for restoring an Azure virtual machine (VM) from a previous backup.

Restore types

Azure Backup provides many ways to restore a VM. As explained earlier, you can either instantly restore from the snapshot tier (optimal for operational recoveries) or from the vault tier.

Restore option

Details

Create a new VM

Quickly creates and gets a basic VM up and running from a restore point. The new VM must be created in the same region as the source VM.

Restore disk

Restores a VM disk, which can then be used to create a new VM. The disks are copied to the resource group you specify. Azure Backup provides a template to help you customize and create a VM. Alternatively, you can attach the disk to an existing VM, or create a new VM. This option is useful if you want to customize the VM, add configuration settings that weren't there at the time of backup. Or, add settings that must be configured using the template or PowerShell.

Replace existing

You can restore a disk and use it to replace a disk on the existing VM. Azure Backup takes a snapshot of the existing VM before replacing the disk and stores it in the staging location you specify. Existing disks connected to the VM are replaced with the selected restore point. The current VM must exist. You can't use this option if the VM is deleted.

Cross region (secondary region)

Cross region restore can be used to restore Azure VMs in the secondary region, which is an Azure paired region. This feature is available for the following options: Create a VM Restore Disks We don't currently support the Replace existing disks option.

- Create a VM

- Restore Disks We don't currently support the Replace existing disks option.

Cross Subscription Restore

Backup Admins and App admins can perform the restore operation on secondary regions. Cross Subscription Restore: - Allows you to restore Azure Virtual Machines or disks to a different subscription within the same tenant as the source subscription. As per the Azure role-based access control capabilities from restore points. - Allowed only if the Cross Subscription Restore property is enabled for your Recovery Services vault. - Works with Cross Region Restore and Cross Zonal Restore. - You can trigger Cross Subscription Restore for managed virtual machines only. - Cross Subscription Restore is supported for Restore with Managed System Identities (MSI). - It's unsupported for snapshots tier recovery points. - It's unsupported for unmanaged VMs and VMs encrypted with Advanced Digital Encryption (ADE).

Cross Zonal Restore

Allows you to restore Azure Virtual Machines or disks pinned to any zone to different available zones (as per the Azure Role-based access control capabilities) from restore points. When you select a zone to restore, it selects the logical zone (and not the physical zone) as per the Azure subscription you use to restore to. - You can trigger Cross Zonal Restore for managed virtual machines only. - Cross Zonal Restore is supported for Restore with Managed System Identities (MSI). - Cross Zonal Restore supports restore of an Azure zone pinned/non-zone pinned VM from a vault with Zone-redundant storage (ZRS) enabled. Learn how to set Storage Redundancy. - You can only use Cross Zonal Restore to restore a VM pinned to an Azure zone from a vault with Cross Region Restore (CRR) under these conditions: The secondary region supports zones, or Zone Redundant Storage (ZRS) is enabled. - Cross Zonal Restore is supported from secondary regions. - It's unsupported from snapshots restore point. - It's unsupported for Encrypted Azure VMs.

Selective disk backup

Allows you to back up and restore selective VM disks through Enhanced policy. Using this capability, you can selectively back up a subset of the data disks that are attached to your VM. Then, you can restore a subset of the disks that are available in a recovery point, both from instant restore and vault tier. Selective disk backup is useful when you: - Manage critical data in a subset of the VM disks. - Use database backup solutions and want to back up only their OS disk to reduce cost.

Recover files from a backup

You can also recover individual files from a recovery point by mounting the snapshot on the target machine using the iSCSI initiator in the machine. To learn more, see Recover files from Azure virtual machine backup .

Restore an encrypted virtual machine

Azure Backup supports the backup and restore of machines encrypted through Azure Disk Encryption. Disk Encryption works with Azure Key Vault to manage the relevant secrets that are associated with the encrypted disk. For an extra layer of security, you can use key vault encryption keys (KEKs) to encrypt the secrets before they're written to the key vault.

Certain limitations apply when you restore encrypted VMs:

- Azure Backup supports only standalone key encryption. Any key that's part of a certificate isn't currently supported.

- File-level or folder-level restores aren't supported with encrypted VMs. To restore to that level of granularity, the entire VM has to be restored. You can then manually copy the file or folders.

- The Replace existing VM option isn't available for encrypted VMs.

Check your knowledge

Unit 6.2.6 - Exercise - Restore Azure virtual machine data

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/protect-virtual-machines-with-azure-backup/6-exercise-restore-virtual-machine-data

Exercise - Restore Azure virtual machine data

A few days after you backed up your first Azure virtual machine (VM), the server had issues. The VM needs to be restored from a backup. You want to restore the VM's disk and attach it to the problematic live server, and then track the restore to ensure that it finished successfully.

In this exercise, you see how to restore a successful backup to replace a VM that became corrupted, and monitor its progress.

Restore a virtual machine in the Azure portal

Create a storage account to use as a staging location

- If you closed Azure, sign in to the Azure portal by using the same account that you used in the previous exercise.

If you closed Azure, sign in to the Azure portal by using the same account that you used in the previous exercise.

- In the Azure portal, enter Storage accounts in the top search bar, and then select it. The Storage accounts pane appears.

In the Azure portal, enter Storage accounts in the top search bar, and then select it.

The Storage accounts pane appears.

- In the menu bar, select Create . The Create a storage account pane appears.

In the menu bar, select Create . The Create a storage account pane appears.

- On the Basics tab, enter the following values for each setting to create a storage account. Setting Value Resource group From the dropdown list, select vmbackups . Instance details Storage account name Enter a unique name like restorestagingYYYYMMDD , where YYYYMMDD is replaced with today's date. Region From the dropdown list, select (US) West US 2 .

On the Basics tab, enter the following values for each setting to create a storage account.

Setting

Value

Resource group

From the dropdown list, select vmbackups .

Instance details

Storage account name

Enter a unique name like restorestagingYYYYMMDD , where YYYYMMDD is replaced with today's date.

Region

From the dropdown list, select (US) West US 2 .

- Select Review + create .

Select Review + create .

- After validation passes, select Create . Wait for the storage account to be deployed.

After validation passes, select Create .

Wait for the storage account to be deployed.

Stop the virtual machine

A backup can't be restored if the VM is allocated and running. If you forget to stop the VM and attempt to restore it, you see an error that's similar to the following example.

To prevent this error, follow these steps:

- In the top left of the Azure portal, select Home , select Virtual Machines , and then select NW-APP01 . The NW-APP01 virtual machine pane appears.

In the top left of the Azure portal, select Home , select Virtual Machines , and then select NW-APP01 .

The NW-APP01 virtual machine pane appears.

- In the menu bar, select Stop .

In the menu bar, select Stop .

- In the Stop this virtual machine dialog box, select OK .

In the Stop this virtual machine dialog box, select OK .

Restore the virtual machine

The Recovery Services vaults are accessible at the subscription level. When you're viewing the VM, Azure provides a quick link to the specific vault under Operations .

- In the menu pane, scroll to Operations , and select Backup .

In the menu pane, scroll to Operations , and select Backup .

- To restore the virtual machine, in the menu bar, select Restore VM . The Restore Virtual Machine pane for NW-APP01 appears.

To restore the virtual machine, in the menu bar, select Restore VM . The Restore Virtual Machine pane for NW-APP01 appears.

- Under the Restore point text box, choose Select . The Select restore point pane appears.

Under the Restore point text box, choose Select . The Select restore point pane appears.

- By default, the start and end date are set for a two week range. Set the Start date to an appropriate date for our restore points ( 07/05/2021 ), select the restore point to use for the recovery, and then select OK . The Restore Virtual Machine pane for NW-APP01 appears.

By default, the start and end date are set for a two week range. Set the Start date to an appropriate date for our restore points ( 07/05/2021 ), select the restore point to use for the recovery, and then select OK .

The Restore Virtual Machine pane for NW-APP01 appears.

- Configure the restore point using the following values for each setting. Setting Value Restore Configuration Replace existing Select this option. Staging Location From the dropdown list, select the storage account that you previously created.

Configure the restore point using the following values for each setting.

Setting

Value

Restore Configuration

Replace existing

Select this option.

Staging Location

From the dropdown list, select the storage account that you previously created.

- Select Restore . The Backup pane for the NW-APP01 virtual machine appears. Notice the notifications in the top right of the toolbar. The latest notification shows Triggering restore for NW-APP01

Select Restore . The Backup pane for the NW-APP01 virtual machine appears. Notice the notifications in the top right of the toolbar. The latest notification shows Triggering restore for NW-APP01

Track a restore

- In the Alerts and Jobs section, select View all Jobs . The Backup Jobs pane appears.

In the Alerts and Jobs section, select View all Jobs . The Backup Jobs pane appears.

- In the Details column, select View details for the Restore job. The Restore pane appears for NW-APP01 .

In the Details column, select View details for the Restore job.

The Restore pane appears for NW-APP01 .

- You can monitor the progress of the VM restore job: Job details : Details about the restore job you launched for this VM. Job status : Real-time progress of the restore job. Sub tasks : Name and status of the tasks within the job.

You can monitor the progress of the VM restore job:

- Job details : Details about the restore job you launched for this VM.

- Job status : Real-time progress of the restore job.

- Sub tasks : Name and status of the tasks within the job.

Unit 6.2.7 - Summary

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/protect-virtual-machines-with-azure-backup/7-summary

Summary

In this module, you learned the importance of having a tested backup and recovery strategy for your organization. You learned about the different types of Azure backups, and the reasons why you would choose one backup type versus another depending on your scenario.

You learned that you can back up Azure virtual machines or on-premises machines. In addition, you learned how to back up an Azure virtual machine (VM). You then restored it by using the various options available to you, and you were able to monitor the progress.

You can now use Azure Backup to help protect your environment against data loss or disk corruption. You can restore services according to your business continuity and disaster recovery plan.

Important

In this module you created resources using your Azure subscription. You want to clean up these resources so that you will not continue to be charged for them. You can delete resources individually or delete the resource group to delete the entire set of resources.

Learn more

For more information about Azure Backup, see the following articles:

- Latest Azure Backup pricing and availability

- Documentation for the Azure Backup service

- Support matrix for Azure VM backup

- Security features in Azure Backup

- Built-in monitoring and alerting capabilities

- Azure Files - Snapshot management by Azure Backup

- Back up SQL Server databases running on Azure VMs

- Backup SAP HANA (High-performance Analytic Appliance) databases running on Azure VMs

- Azure Data Protection Manager (DPM) and Azure Backup Server (MABS)

LP 6 M3 - Monitor your Azure virtual machines with Azure Monitor

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/monitor-azure-vm-using-diagnostic-data/?WT.mc_id=api_CatalogApi

Unit 6.3.1 - Introduction

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/monitor-azure-vm-using-diagnostic-data/1-introduction

Introduction

Suppose you're the IT administrator for a musical group's website hosted on Azure virtual machines (VMs). The website runs mission-critical services for the group, including ticket booking, venue information, and tour updates. The website must respond quickly and remain accessible during frequent updates and spikes in traffic.

You need to maintain sufficient VM size and memory to effectively host the website without incurring unnecessary costs. You also need to proactively prevent and quickly respond to any access, security, and performance issues. To help achieve these objectives, you want to quickly and easily monitor your VMs' traffic, health, performance, and events.

Azure Monitor provides built-in and customizable monitoring abilities. You can use these to track the health, performance, and behavior of the VM host and the operating system, workloads, and applications running on your VM. This learning module shows you how to view VM host monitoring data, set up recommended alert rules, and use VM insights and custom data collection rules (DCRs) to collect and analyze monitoring data from inside your VMs.

Prerequisites

To complete this module, you need the following prerequisites:

- Familiarity with virtualization, Azure portal navigation, and Azure VMs.

- Access to an Azure subscription with at least Contributor role. If you don't have an Azure subscription, create a free account and add a subscription before you begin. If you're a student, you can take advantage of the Azure for students offer.

Learning objectives

- Understand which monitoring data you need to collect from your VM.

- Enable and view recommended alerts and diagnostics.

- Use Azure Monitor to collect and analyze VM host data.

- Use Azure Monitor Agent to collect VM client performance metrics and event logs.

Unit 6.3.2 - Monitoring for Azure VMs

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/monitor-azure-vm-using-diagnostic-data/2-monitor-vm-health

Monitoring for Azure VMs

In this unit, you explore Azure monitoring capabilities for VMs, and the types of monitoring data you can collect and analyze with Azure Monitor. Azure Monitor is a comprehensive monitoring solution for collecting, analyzing, and responding to monitoring data from Azure and non-Azure resources, including VMs. Azure Monitor has two main monitoring features: Azure Monitor Metrics and Azure Monitor Logs.

Metrics are numerical values collected at predetermined intervals to describe some aspect of a system. Metrics can measure VM performance, resource utilization, error counts, user responses, or any other aspect of the system that you can quantify. Azure Monitor Metrics automatically monitors a predefined set of metrics for every Azure VM, and retains the data for 93 days with some exceptions.

Logs are recorded system events that contain a timestamp and different types of structured or free-form data. Azure automatically records activity logs for all Azure resources. This data is available at the resource level. Azure Monitor doesn't collect logs by default, but you can configure Azure Monitor Logs to collect from any Azure resource. Azure Monitor Logs stores log data in a Log Analytics workspace for querying and analysis.

VM monitoring layers

Azure VMs have several layers that require monitoring. Each of the following layers has a distinct set of telemetry and monitoring requirements.

- Host VM

- Guest operating system (OS)

- Client workloads

- Applications that run on the VM

Host VM monitoring

The VM host represents the compute, storage, and network resources that Azure allocates to the VM.

VM host metrics

VM host metrics measure technical aspects of the VM such as processor utilization and whether the machine is running. You can use VM host metrics to:

- Trigger an alert when your VM is reaching its disk or CPU limits.

- Identify trends or patterns.

- Control your operational costs by sizing VMs according to usage and demand.

Azure automatically collects basic metrics for VM hosts. On the VM's Overview page in the Azure portal, you can see built-in graphs for the following important VM host metrics.

- VM availability

- CPU usage percentage (average)

- OS disk usage (total)

- Network operations (total)

- Disk operations per second (average)

You can use Azure Monitor Metrics Explorer to plot more metrics graphs, investigate changes, and visually correlate metrics trends for your VMs. With Metrics Explorer you can:

- Plot multiple metrics on a graph to see how much traffic hits your VM and how the VM performs.

- Track the same metric over multiple VMs in a resource group or other scope, and use splitting to show each VM on the graph.

- Select flexible time ranges and granularity.

- Specify many other settings such as chart type and value ranges.

- Send graphs to workbooks or pin them to dashboards for quickly viewing health and performance.

- Group metrics by time intervals, geographic regions, server clusters, or application components.

Recommended alert rules

Alerts proactively notify you of specified occurrences and patterns in your VM host metrics. Recommended alert rules are a predefined set of alert rules based on commonly monitored host metrics. These rules define recommended CPU, memory, disk, and network usage levels to alert on. The rules also include VM availability, which alerts you when the VM stops running.

You can quickly enable and configure recommended alert rules when you create an Azure VM, or afterwards from the VM's portal page. You can also view, configure, and create custom alerts by using Azure Monitor Alerts.

Activity logs

Azure Monitor automatically records and displays activity logs for Azure VMs. Activity logs include information like VM startup or modifications. You can create diagnostic settings to send activity logs to the following destinations:

- Azure Monitor Logs: For more complex querying and alerting, and for longer retention up to two years.

- Azure Storage: For cheaper, long-term archiving.

- Azure Event Hubs: To forward outside of Azure.

Boot diagnostics

Boot diagnostics are host logs you can use to help troubleshoot boot issues with your VMs. You can enable boot diagnostics by default when you create a VM, or afterwards for existing VMs.

Once you enable boot diagnostics, you can see screenshots from the VM's hypervisor for both Windows and Linux machines, and view the serial console log output of the VM boot sequence for Linux machines. Boot diagnostics stores data in a managed storage account.

Guest OS, client workload, and application monitoring

VM client monitoring can include monitoring the operating system (OS), workloads, and applications that run on the VM. To collect metrics and logs from guest OS and client workloads and applications, you need to install Azure Monitor Agent and set up a DCR.

DCRs define what data to collect and where to send that data. You can use a DCR to send Azure Monitor metrics data, or performance counters , to Azure Monitor Logs or Azure Monitor Metrics. You can also send event log data to Azure Monitor Logs. In other words, Azure Monitor Metrics can store only metrics data, but Azure Monitor Logs can store both metrics and event logs.

VM insights

VM insights is an Azure Monitor feature that helps get you started monitoring your VM clients. VM insights is especially useful for exploring overall VM usage and performance when you don't yet know the metric of primary interest. VM insights provides:

- Simplified Azure Monitor Agent onboarding to enable monitoring a VM's guest OS and workloads.

- A preconfigured DCR that monitors and collects the most common performance counters for Windows and Linux.

- Predefined trending performance metrics charts and workbooks from the VM's guest OS.

- A set of predefined workbooks that show collected VM client metrics over time.

- Optionally, a collection of processes running on the VM, dependencies with other services, and a dependency map that displays interconnected components with other VMs and external sources.

Predefined VM insights workbooks show performance, connections, active ports, traffic, and other collected data from one or several VMs. You can view VM insights data directly from a single VM, or see a combined view of multiple VMs to view and assess trends and patterns across VMs. You can edit the prebuilt workbook configurations, or create your own custom workbooks.

Client event log data

VM insights creates a DCR that collects a specific set of performance counters. To collect other data, such as event logs, you can create a separate DCR that specifies the data you want to collect from the VM and where to send it. Azure Monitor stores collected log data in a Log Analytics workspace. From there, you can access and analyze the data by using log queries written in Kusto Query Language (KQL).

Check your knowledge

Unit 6.3.3 - Monitor VM host data

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/monitor-azure-vm-using-diagnostic-data/3-exercise-create-virtual-machine

Monitor VM host data

You want to monitor the VMs that host your website, so you decide to quickly create a VM in the Azure portal and evaluate its built-in monitoring capabilities. In this unit, you use the Azure portal to create a Linux VM with recommended alerts and boot diagnostics enabled. As soon as the VM starts up, Azure automatically begins collecting basic metrics and activity logs. You can then view built-in metrics graphs, activity logs, and boot diagnostics.

Create a VM and enable recommended alerts

- Sign in to the Azure portal , and in the Search field, enter virtual machines .

Sign in to the Azure portal , and in the Search field, enter virtual machines .

- On the Virtual machines page, select Create , and then select Azure virtual machine .

On the Virtual machines page, select Create , and then select Azure virtual machine .

- On the Basics tab of the Create a virtual machine page: In the Subscription field, select the correct subscription if not already selected. Under Resource group : Select Create new . Under Name , enter learn-monitor-vm-rg . Select OK . For Virtual machine name , enter monitored-linux-vm . For Image , select Ubuntu Server 20.04 LTS - x64 Gen2 .

On the Basics tab of the Create a virtual machine page:

- In the Subscription field, select the correct subscription if not already selected.

- Under Resource group : Select Create new . Under Name , enter learn-monitor-vm-rg . Select OK .

- Select Create new .

- Under Name , enter learn-monitor-vm-rg .

- Select OK .

- For Virtual machine name , enter monitored-linux-vm .

- For Image , select Ubuntu Server 20.04 LTS - x64 Gen2 .

- Leave the other settings at their current values, and select the Monitoring tab.

Leave the other settings at their current values, and select the Monitoring tab.

- On the Monitoring tab, select the checkbox next to Enable recommended alert rules .

On the Monitoring tab, select the checkbox next to Enable recommended alert rules .

- On the Set up recommended alert rules screen: Select all the listed alert rules if not already selected, and adjust the values if desired. Under Notify me by , select the checkbox next to Email , and enter an email address to receive alert notifications. Select Save .

On the Set up recommended alert rules screen:

- Select all the listed alert rules if not already selected, and adjust the values if desired.

- Under Notify me by , select the checkbox next to Email , and enter an email address to receive alert notifications.

- Select Save .

- Under Diagnostics , for Boot diagnostics , ensure that Enable with managed storage account (recommended) is selected. Note Don't select Enable OS guest diagnostics . The Linux Diagnostics Agent (LAD) is deprecated, and you can enable OS guest and client monitoring later.

Under Diagnostics , for Boot diagnostics , ensure that Enable with managed storage account (recommended) is selected.

Note

Don't select Enable OS guest diagnostics . The Linux Diagnostics Agent (LAD) is deprecated, and you can enable OS guest and client monitoring later.

- Select Review + create at the bottom of the page, and when validation passes, select Create .

Select Review + create at the bottom of the page, and when validation passes, select Create .

- On the Generate new key pair popup dialog box, select Download private key and create resource .

On the Generate new key pair popup dialog box, select Download private key and create resource .

It can take a few minutes to create the VM. When you get the notification that the VM is created, select Go to resource to see basic metrics data.

View built-in metrics graphs

Once your VM is created, Azure starts collecting basic metrics data automatically. Built-in metrics graphs, along with the recommended alerts you enabled, can help you monitor whether and when your VM encounters health or performance issues. You can then use more advanced monitoring and analytics capabilities to investigate issue causes and remediation.

- To view basic metrics graphs, on the VMs Overview page, select the Monitoring tab.

To view basic metrics graphs, on the VMs Overview page, select the Monitoring tab.

- Under Performance and utilization > Platform metrics , review the following metrics graphs related to the VMs performance and utilization. Select Show more metrics if all the graphs don't appear immediately. VM Availability CPU (average) Disk bytes (total) Network (total) Disk operations/sec (average)

Under Performance and utilization > Platform metrics , review the following metrics graphs related to the VMs performance and utilization. Select Show more metrics if all the graphs don't appear immediately.

- VM Availability

- CPU (average)

- Disk bytes (total)

- Network (total)

- Disk operations/sec (average)

- Under Guest OS metrics , notice that guest OS metrics aren't being collected yet. In the next units, you configure VM insights and data collection rules to collect guest OS metrics.

Under Guest OS metrics , notice that guest OS metrics aren't being collected yet. In the next units, you configure VM insights and data collection rules to collect guest OS metrics.

View the activity log

You can view the VMs activity log by selecting Activity log from the VMs left navigation menu. You can also retrieve entries by using PowerShell or the Azure CLI.

View boot diagnostics

You enabled boot diagnostics when you created the VM. You can view boot diagnostics to view boot data and troubleshoot startup issues.

- In the left navigation menu for the VM, select Boot diagnostics under Help .

In the left navigation menu for the VM, select Boot diagnostics under Help .

- On the Boot diagnostics page, select Screenshot to see a startup screenshot from the VMs hypervisor. Select Serial log to view log messages created when the VM started.

On the Boot diagnostics page, select Screenshot to see a startup screenshot from the VMs hypervisor. Select Serial log to view log messages created when the VM started.

Check your knowledge

Unit 6.3.4 - Use Metrics Explorer to view detailed host metrics

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/monitor-azure-vm-using-diagnostic-data/4-view-host-metrics

Use Metrics Explorer to view detailed host metrics

You want to investigate how traffic flowing into your VM affects its CPU capability. If the built-in metrics charts for a VM don't already show the data you need, you can use Metrics Explorer to create customized metrics charts. In this unit, you plot a graph that displays your VM's maximum percentage CPU and average inbound flow data together.

Azure Monitor Metrics Explorer offers a UI for exploring and analyzing VM metrics. You can use Metrics Explorer to view and create custom charts for many VM host metrics in addition to the metrics shown on the built-in graphs.

Understand Metrics Explorer

To open Metrics Explorer, you can:

- Select Metrics from the VM's left navigation menu under Monitoring .

- Select the See all Metrics link next to Platform metrics on the Monitoring tab of the VM's Overview page.

- Select Metrics from the left navigation menu on the Azure Monitor Overview page.

In Metrics Explorer, you can select the following values from the dropdown fields:

- Scope: If you open Metrics Explorer from a VM, this field is prepopulated with the VM name. You can add more items with the same resource type (VMs) and location.

- Metric Namespace : Most resource types have only one namespace, but for some types, you must pick a namespace. For example, storage accounts have separate namespaces for files, tables, blobs, and queues.

- Metric : Each metrics namespace has many metrics available to choose from.

- Aggregation : For each metric, Metrics Explorer applies a default aggregation. You can use a different aggregation to get different information about the metric.

You can apply the following aggregation functions to metrics:

- Count : Counts the number of data points.

- Average (Avg) : Calculates the arithmetic mean of values.

- Maximum (Max) : Identifies the highest value.

- Minimum (Min) : Identifies the lowest value.

- Sum : Adds up all the values.

You can select flexible time ranges for graphs from the past 30 minutes to the last 30 days, or custom ranges. You can specify time interval granularity from one minute to one month.

Create a metrics graph

To create a Metrics Explorer graph that shows host VM maximum percentage CPU and inbound flows together for the past 30 minutes:

- Open Metrics Explorer by selecting See all Metrics on the VM's Monitoring tab or selecting Metrics from the VM's left navigation menu.

Open Metrics Explorer by selecting See all Metrics on the VM's Monitoring tab or selecting Metrics from the VM's left navigation menu.

- Scope and Metric Namespace are already populated for the host VM. Select Percentage CPU from the Metrics dropdown list.

Scope and Metric Namespace are already populated for the host VM. Select Percentage CPU from the Metrics dropdown list.

- Aggregation is automatically populated with Avg , but change it to Max .

Aggregation is automatically populated with Avg , but change it to Max .

- Select Add metric at upper left.

Select Add metric at upper left.

- Under Metric , select Inbound Flows . Leave Aggregation at Avg .

Under Metric , select Inbound Flows . Leave Aggregation at Avg .

- At upper right, select Local Time: Last 24 hours (Automatic - 15 minutes) , change it to Last 30 minutes , and select Apply .

At upper right, select Local Time: Last 24 hours (Automatic - 15 minutes) , change it to Last 30 minutes , and select Apply .

Your graph should look similar to the following screenshot:

Check your knowledge

Unit 6.3.5 - Collect client performance counters by using VM insights

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/monitor-azure-vm-using-diagnostic-data/5-enable-vm-insights

Collect client performance counters by using VM insights

Besides monitoring your VM host's health, utilization, and performance, you need to monitor the software and processes running on your VM. These are called the VM guest or client. In this unit, you enable the Azure Monitor VM insights feature, which offers a quick way to start monitoring the VM client.

The VM client includes the operating system and other workloads and applications. To monitor the software running on your VM, you install the Azure Monitor Agent, which collects data from inside the VM. VM insights:

- Installs Azure Monitor Agent on your VM.

- Creates a DCR that collects and sends a predefined set of client performance data to a Log Analytics workspace.

- Presents the data in curated workbooks.

Although you don't need to use VM insights to install Azure Monitor Agent, create DCRs, or set up workbooks, VM insights makes setting up VM client monitoring easy. VM insights provides you with a basis for monitoring the performance of your VM client and mapping the processes running on your machine.

Enable VM insights

- In the Azure portal, on your VM's Overview page, select Insights from the left navigation menu under Monitoring .

In the Azure portal, on your VM's Overview page, select Insights from the left navigation menu under Monitoring .

- On the Insights page, select Enable .

On the Insights page, select Enable .

- Under Data collection rule , note the properties of the DCR that VM insights creates. In the DCR description, Processes and dependencies (Map) is set to Disabled , which you can change to Enabled or review this article on how-to if greyed out. Also a default Log Analytics workspace is created or assigned.

Under Data collection rule , note the properties of the DCR that VM insights creates. In the DCR description, Processes and dependencies (Map) is set to Disabled , which you can change to Enabled or review this article on how-to if greyed out. Also a default Log Analytics workspace is created or assigned.

- Select Configure . Configuration of the workspace and the agent installation typically takes 5 to 10 minutes. It can take another 5 to 10 minutes for data to become available to view in the portal.

Select Configure .

Configuration of the workspace and the agent installation typically takes 5 to 10 minutes. It can take another 5 to 10 minutes for data to become available to view in the portal.

- When the deployment finishes, confirm that the Azure Monitor Agent is installed by looking on the Properties tab of the VM's Overview page under Extensions + applications . On the Monitoring tab of the Overview page, under Performance and utilization , you can see that Guest OS metrics are now being collected.

When the deployment finishes, confirm that the Azure Monitor Agent is installed by looking on the Properties tab of the VM's Overview page under Extensions + applications .

On the Monitoring tab of the Overview page, under Performance and utilization , you can see that Guest OS metrics are now being collected.

View VM insights

VM insights creates a DCR that sends client VM performance counters to Azure Monitor Logs. Because the DCR sends its metrics to Azure Monitor Logs, you don't use Metrics Explorer to view the metrics data that VM insights collects.

To view the VM insights performance graphs and maps:

- Select Insights from the VM's left navigation menu under Monitoring .

Select Insights from the VM's left navigation menu under Monitoring .

- Near the top of the Insights page, select the Performance tab. The prebuilt VM insights Performance workbook shows charts and graphs with performance-related data for the current VM. You can customize the view by specifying a different Time range at the top of the page and different aggregations at the top of each graph. Select View Workbooks to select from other available prebuilt VM insights workbooks. Select Go To Gallery to select from a gallery of other VM insights workbooks and workbook templates, or to edit and create your own workbooks.

Near the top of the Insights page, select the Performance tab. The prebuilt VM insights Performance workbook shows charts and graphs with performance-related data for the current VM.

- You can customize the view by specifying a different Time range at the top of the page and different aggregations at the top of each graph.

You can customize the view by specifying a different Time range at the top of the page and different aggregations at the top of each graph.

- Select View Workbooks to select from other available prebuilt VM insights workbooks. Select Go To Gallery to select from a gallery of other VM insights workbooks and workbook templates, or to edit and create your own workbooks.

Select View Workbooks to select from other available prebuilt VM insights workbooks. Select Go To Gallery to select from a gallery of other VM insights workbooks and workbook templates, or to edit and create your own workbooks.

- If enabled earlier, select the Map tab on the Insights page to see the workbook for the Map feature. The map visualizes the VM's dependencies by discovering running process groups and processes that have active network connections over a specified time range.

If enabled earlier, select the Map tab on the Insights page to see the workbook for the Map feature. The map visualizes the VM's dependencies by discovering running process groups and processes that have active network connections over a specified time range.

Check your knowledge

Unit 6.3.6 - Collect VM client event logs

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/monitor-azure-vm-using-diagnostic-data/6-collect-log-data

Collect VM client event logs

Azure Monitor Metrics and VM insights performance counters help you identify performance anomalies, and alert when thresholds are reached. But to analyze the root causes of issues you detect, you need to analyze log data to see which system events caused or contributed to the issues. In this unit, you set up a DCR to collect Linux VM Syslog data, and view the log data in Azure Monitor Log Analytics by using a simple Kusto Query Language (KQL) query.

VM insights installs the Azure Monitor Agent, and creates a DCR that collects predefined performance counters, maps process dependencies, and presents the data in prebuilt workbooks. You can create your own DCRs to collect VM performance counters that the VM insights DCR doesn't collect, or to collect log data.

When you create DCRs in the Azure portal, you can select from a range of performance counters and sampling rates or add custom performance counters. Alternatively, you can select from a predefined set of log types and severity levels or define custom log schemas. You can associate a single DCR to any or all VMs in your subscription, but you might need multiple DCRs to collect different types of data from different VMs.

Create a DCR to collect log data

In the Azure portal, search for and select monitor to go to the Azure Monitor Overview page.

Create a Data Collection Endpoint

You must have a data collection endpoint to send log data to. To create an endpoint:

- In the Azure Monitor left navigation menu under Settings , select Data Collection Endpoints .

- On the Data Collection Endpoints page, select Create .

- On the Create data collection endpoint page, for Name , enter linux-logs-endpoint .

- Select the same Subscription , Resource group , and Region as your VM uses.

- Select Review + create , and when validation passes, select Create .

Create the Data Collection Rule

To create the DCR to collect the event logs:

- In the Monitor left navigation menu under Settings , select Data Collection Rules .

In the Monitor left navigation menu under Settings , select Data Collection Rules .

- On the Data Collection Rules page, you can see the DCR that VM insights created. Select Create to create a new data collection rule.

On the Data Collection Rules page, you can see the DCR that VM insights created. Select Create to create a new data collection rule.

- On the Basics tab of the Create Data Collection Rule screen, provide the following information: Rule name : Enter collect-events-linux . Subscription , Resource Group , and Region : Select the same as for your VM. Platform Type : Select Linux .

On the Basics tab of the Create Data Collection Rule screen, provide the following information:

- Rule name : Enter collect-events-linux .

- Subscription , Resource Group , and Region : Select the same as for your VM.

- Platform Type : Select Linux .

- Select Next: Resources or the Resources tab.

Select Next: Resources or the Resources tab.

- On the Resources screen, select Add resources .

On the Resources screen, select Add resources .

- On the Select a scope screen, select the monitored-linux-vm VM, and then select Apply .

On the Select a scope screen, select the monitored-linux-vm VM, and then select Apply .

- On the Resources screen, select Enable Data Collection Endpoints .

On the Resources screen, select Enable Data Collection Endpoints .

- Under Data collection endpoint for the monitored-linux-vm , select the linux-logs-endpoint you created.

Under Data collection endpoint for the monitored-linux-vm , select the linux-logs-endpoint you created.

- Select Next: Collect and deliver , or the Collect and deliver tab.

Select Next: Collect and deliver , or the Collect and deliver tab.

- On the Collect and deliver tab, select Add data source .

On the Collect and deliver tab, select Add data source .

- On the Add data source screen, under Data source type , select Linux Syslog .

On the Add data source screen, under Data source type , select Linux Syslog .

- On the Add data source screen, select Next: Destination or the Destination tab, and make sure the Account or namespace matches the Log Analytics workspace that you want to use. You can use the default Log Analytics workspace that VM insights set up, or create or use another Log Analytics workspace.

On the Add data source screen, select Next: Destination or the Destination tab, and make sure the Account or namespace matches the Log Analytics workspace that you want to use. You can use the default Log Analytics workspace that VM insights set up, or create or use another Log Analytics workspace.

- On the Add data source screen, select Add data source .

On the Add data source screen, select Add data source .

- On the Create Data Collection Rule screen, select Review + create , and when validation passes, select Create .

On the Create Data Collection Rule screen, select Review + create , and when validation passes, select Create .

View log data

You can view and analyze the log data collected by your DCR by using KQL log queries. A set of sample KQL queries is available for VMs, but you can write a query to look at the events your DCR is collecting.

- On your VM's Overview page, select Logs from the left navigation menu under Monitoring . Log Analytics opens an empty query window with the scope set to your VM. You can also access log data by selecting Logs from the left navigation of the Azure Monitor Overview page. If necessary, select Select scope at the top of the query window to scope the query to the desired Log Analytics workspace and VM. Note The Queries window with sample queries might open when you open Log Analytics. For now, close this window, because you're going to manually create a simple query.

On your VM's Overview page, select Logs from the left navigation menu under Monitoring . Log Analytics opens an empty query window with the scope set to your VM.

You can also access log data by selecting Logs from the left navigation of the Azure Monitor Overview page. If necessary, select Select scope at the top of the query window to scope the query to the desired Log Analytics workspace and VM.

Note

The Queries window with sample queries might open when you open Log Analytics. For now, close this window, because you're going to manually create a simple query.

- In the empty query window, type Syslog , and then select Run . All the system log events the DCR collected within the Time range are displayed.

In the empty query window, type Syslog , and then select Run . All the system log events the DCR collected within the Time range are displayed.

- You can refine your query to identify events of interest. For example, you can display only the events that had a SeverityLevel of warning .

You can refine your query to identify events of interest. For example, you can display only the events that had a SeverityLevel of warning .

Check your knowledge

Unit 6.3.7 - Summary

https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/monitor-azure-vm-using-diagnostic-data/7-summary

Summary

Azure Monitor helps you collect, analyze, and alert on various types of host and client monitoring data from your Azure VMs.

- Azure Monitor provides a set of VM host logs and performance and usage metrics for all Azure VMs.

- You can enable recommended alert rules when you create VMs or afterwards to alert on important VM host metrics.

- Azure Monitor Metrics Explorer lets you graph and analyze metrics for Azure VMs and other resources.

- VM insights provides a simple way to monitor important VM client performance counters and processes running on your VM.

- You can create data collection rules to collect other metrics and logs from your VM client.

- You can use Log Analytics to query and analyze log data.

Now that you understand these tools, you're confident that Azure Monitor can effectively monitor your Azure VMs and help you keep your website running effectively.

Clean up resources

In this module, you created a VM in your Azure subscription. To prevent further charges for this VM, you can delete it or the resource group that contains it.

To delete the resource group that contains the VM and its resources:

- Select the Resource group link at the top of the Essentials section on the VM's Overview page.

- At the top of the resource group page, select Delete resource group .

- On the delete screen, select the checkbox next to Apply force delete for selected virtual machines and virtual machine scale sets . Enter the resource group name in the field, and then select Delete .

Learn more

To learn more about monitoring your VMs with Azure Monitor, see the following resources:

- Azure Monitor documentation

- Monitor virtual machines with Azure Monitor

- Supported metrics with Azure Monitor

- Send Azure Monitor Activity log data

- Supported metrics for Microsoft.Compute/virtualMachines

- Overview of VM insights

- Create interactive reports with VM insights workbooks

- Use the Map feature of VM insights to understand application components

- Azure Monitor Agent overview

- Collect data with Azure Monitor Agent

- Tutorial: Collect guest logs and metrics from an Azure virtual machine